<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><n-document xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" guid="0" synced="true" validated="true">
  <n-docbody>
    <standard.doc precedenttype="contract">
      <prelim>
        <product.name>product.name0</product.name>
        <title>Services agreement: short form (with contract details cover sheet; pro-supplier)</title>
        <author><link href="http://uk.practicallaw.com/about/our-team/uk-commercial" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practical Law Commercial</ital></link></author>
        <resource.type>Standard documents</resource.type>
        <juris>juris0</juris>
        <juris>juris1</juris>
      </prelim>
      <abstract>
        <para>
          <paratext>A short form agreement for the supply of services, drafted from the supplier's perspective, with key commercial information listed in a table at the front of the agreement. It is intended for use in business-to-business transactions.</paratext>
        </para>
      </abstract>
      <toc.identifier hasToc="true"/>
      <body>
        <drafting.note id="a828321" jurisdiction="">
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>About this document</headtext>
          </head>
          <division id="a000002" level="1">
            <para>
              <paratext>This document is a short form agreement for the supply of services in a business-to-business (b2b) context. It is drafted from the supplier's perspective.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>In the interests of producing a short form services agreement, we have omitted or shortened various clauses that would usually be included in a longer form services agreement. For more information, see <internal.reference refid="a225344"><ital>Drafting note, Omitted, shortened and optional clauses</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>For information on common legal issues that impact the drafting of services agreements, such as implied terms and limitations of liability, see <link anchor="a728978" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): Drafting note: Legal issues</ital></link>.</paratext>
            </para>
          </division>
          <division id="a59625" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Short form agreement considerations</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>In assessing whether it is appropriate to use a short form agreement, relevant considerations include:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>The type of transaction</bold>. Is it a routine transaction where the risks are known and assessed as not justifying the time and expense of negotiating a long form agreement?</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>The nature and value of the services</bold>. Are the services of a low value? Are the services straight-forward to deliver and not particularly bespoke to the customer? How crucial are the services to each party's business?</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Each party's risk profile</bold>. What level of risk is each party willing to accept? The more risks that a party faces, the more it is likely to want to use a longer form agreement with wider contractual protections.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>The budget for negotiations</bold>. Is there a limited budget for legal and professional fees?</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>The transaction timetable</bold>. Is there enough time to negotiate a long form agreement?</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </division>
          <division id="a180028" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Drawbacks of using a short form agreement</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>A short form supply of services agreement will, by its nature, not incorporate as full a range of supplier-protection provisions as a longer form agreement. Users of this document should therefore consider carefully whether a short form agreement is appropriate in the context of the particular transaction they are working on.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>Even if confident that a short form agreement is suitable for a particular transaction, we advise that you have regard to a long form supply of services agreement when drafting (for links, see <internal.reference refid="a178760"><ital>Drafting note, Alternative agreements</ital></internal.reference>). If there are aspects of the transaction that are of particular importance or concern to the supplier and are not fully addressed in this short form document, relevant provisions from the long form agreement could be included.</paratext>
            </para>
          </division>
          <division id="a225344" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Omitted, shortened and optional clauses</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>In the interests of keeping the document as short as possible, certain clauses from our longer form services agreements have been omitted, shortened or made optional.</paratext>
            </para>
            <division id="a73083" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Omitted clauses</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>These include clauses that deal with the following:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Transfer of employees.</bold> Under the <link href="2-505-5915" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Transfer of Undertakings (Protection of Employment) Regulations 2006 (SI 2006/246)</ital></link> (TUPE), if there is a "service provision change" (essentially a change in the entity responsible for providing services), any employees assigned to an organised group whose main purpose is performing those services will automatically transfer to the new service provider on their current employment terms. A service provision change can happen where a customer engages a supplier to provide services for the first time, or changes its supplier of services, or terminates a service contract and starts to perform services in-house. For full information on when TUPE will apply on a service provision change, see <link href="8-204-4041" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, TUPE (3): service provision changes</ital></link>. If there is a risk that individuals may transfer to the supplier via TUPE when the services begin, the supplier should consider obtaining appropriate warranties and indemnities from the customer, for which see <link anchor="a960361" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): Schedule 6</ital></link>. A short form services agreement is often used where the services are relatively low value. In that scenario, there may not be an organised group whose main purpose is providing the services. For that reason, TUPE may not apply and we have not included TUPE clauses as standard in this agreement.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Specific compliance requirements. </bold>This short form agreement does not include individual clauses to address compliance-related issues such as anti-bribery, modern slavery and prevention of tax evasion and fraud. Instead, there is a generic obligation on the supplier at <internal.reference refid="a998830"><ital>clause 3.2(c)(i)</ital></internal.reference> to comply with applicable laws and business policies. The supplier should consider whether these commitments will be sufficient for its customers. For more detailed drafting for compliance risks, see <link anchor="a610594" href="w-031-0618" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Toolkit, Supply chain compliance toolkit: Compliance clauses: general or specific</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Varying the service description.</bold> There is no formal change control mechanism for proposing and agreeing changes to the services. For a supplier-friendly change control procedure, see <link anchor="a950521" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 9</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Servicing affiliates. </bold>The supplier only services the customer under this agreement. There is no drafting to enable the supplier to service customer affiliates on the terms of this agreement. For this drafting, see <link anchor="a525258" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 6</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Exclusive purchasing. </bold>There is no clause requiring the customer to buy specific services exclusively from the supplier. For this drafting, see <link href="w-035-9068" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Exclusive purchasing and supply clause: short form</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Non-solicitation. </bold>Longer form, supplier-friendly services agreements often contain drafting preventing the customer from poaching the supplier's staff (see <link anchor="a578846" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 7</ital></link>). This drafting is not included in this short form agreement.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Governance. </bold>This short form agreement does not include any drafting for review meetings, reports or the use of contract managers to manage the relationship. For governance drafting, see <link href="w-012-6160" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Governance</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Dispute resolution. </bold>While this agreement contains a governing law and jurisdiction clause, there is no dispute resolution procedure (for example, requiring disputes to be referred to mediation). For dispute resolution drafting, see <link anchor="a363312" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 30</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>As this agreement is drafted from the supplier's perspective, the above list does not include additional provisions that might benefit the customer. For a pro-customer agreement, see <link href="8-599-9827" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement: short form (with contract details cover sheet; pro-customer)</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
            <division id="a153035" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Shortened clauses</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The following clauses are significantly shorter than those in longer form services agreements. The drafting notes to the clauses link to more extensive drafting and a discussion of the relevant provisions.</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Interpretation</bold> (<internal.reference refid="a987444"><ital>clause 1</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Intellectual property rights</bold> (<internal.reference refid="a443100"><ital>clause 6</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Termination</bold> (<internal.reference refid="a321263"><ital>clause 9</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>General</bold> (<internal.reference refid="a989592"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
            </division>
          </division>
          <division id="a178760" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Alternative agreements</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>For a fuller agreement covering the supply of services, see the following standard documents:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Services agreement (pro-supplier)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="6-203-1252" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Simple framework services agreement (pro-supplier)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </division>
          <division id="a759038" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Drafting assumptions</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>This agreement is drafted on the following assumptions:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Services agreed upfront.</bold> This agreement is for the provision of an agreed set of services. It does not provide for the procurement and provision of other services through statements of work (SOWs) under its terms. If this is required, see <link href="6-203-1252" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Simple framework services agreement (pro-supplier)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Primarily services</bold>. The agreement is primarily for the provision of services, although some materials may be provided as part of or result from the services.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>B2B</bold>. The parties are dealing with each other in the course of their respective businesses, meaning that the UK rules protecting consumers will not apply. This agreement is therefore not suitable for use in business-to-consumer transactions. For resources on consumer law, including business-to-consumer terms and conditions, see <link href="7-525-0330" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Consumer law toolkit</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Terms not industry specific. </bold>This agreement does not account for any industry-specific laws or rules that may apply to certain transactions.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>UK companies</bold>. The customer and supplier are companies incorporated in England and Wales. This agreement is not for use by public bodies procuring services. The procurement of services by public bodies is subject to specific procurement rules. For a services agreement that can be used by a public sector body, see <link href="2-501-1525" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement for use by public sector bodies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>English law</bold>. The agreement is subject to English law.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </division>
          <division id="a113535" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Document structure</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>The document is made up of the following parts:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Contract Details.</bold> At the front of the document is a cover sheet entitled "Contract Details" which, when completed, will contain the key variable terms. Putting these terms here should make it easier to prepare the document. It also provides a quick overview of key terms and may perhaps give the impression (to the supplier's benefit) that the other terms are not to be changed.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Conditions.</bold> The main terms of the agreement are in the Conditions attached to the cover sheet. The cover sheet has a section for recording any agreed amendments to the Conditions.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Schedules.</bold> The agreement allows for the incorporation of optional schedules, including:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><bold>Schedule 1.</bold> A full specification for the services can be set out in a schedule where there is insufficient space to describe the services in the cover sheet. For the importance of a comprehensive services description, see <internal.reference refid="a888035"><ital>Drafting note, Services (optional schedule)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><bold>Schedule 2.</bold> The charges and invoicing arrangements could be set out in a schedule, if they will not fit on the cover sheet.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><bold>Schedule 3.</bold> The supplier can list business policies that it will adhere to, for example, in relation to ethical business conduct and anti-bribery measures. In a pro-supplier agreement, the supplier may choose to omit compliance with policies from a first draft. If the supplier does include a commitment to comply with policies (for example, because customers frequently expect this), it may prefer to list its own business conduct policies. This should make compliance easier and remove the need for the supplier to review customer policies and check for differences with its own.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><bold>Schedule 4. </bold>If the supplier is processing personal data on behalf of the customer, it can include the terms necessary to satisfy the <link href="w-026-8528" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>UK GDPR</ital></link> in this schedule.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </list.item>
            </list>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Contract Details, Conditions, and Schedules are incorporated into the agreement by the wording in paragraph 1 at the bottom of the table on the cover sheet. The priority of the various parts making up the agreement is set out in paragraph 2, followed by the signature block.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>Ensure that there is a page break between the Contract Details and the Conditions.</paratext>
            </para>
          </division>
        </drafting.note>
        <preamble>
          <drafting.note id="a583092" jurisdiction="">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Contract Details</headtext>
            </head>
            <division id="a000003" level="1">
              <division id="a408435" level="2">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Date</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The contract should be dated the day the last party signs it.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a109466" level="2">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Services and deliverables</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The services and deliverables should be described in the Contract Details table. Further detail can be added in <internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference> if necessary. Delete the references to <internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>, and the schedule itself, if it is not used.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a771373" level="2">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Charges</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The charges for the services should be specified either in the Contract Details table or in <internal.reference refid="a598248"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>. Alternatively, the supplier could refer to a price list current at the date of the agreement. Delete the reference to <internal.reference refid="a598248"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>, and the schedule itself, if it is not used.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a221104" level="2">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Special terms</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This document envisages that the Conditions will remain unchanged. Any amendments can be set out opposite the words "Special terms" in the Contract Details table, using the optional text as appropriate for when a clause is deleted, added or amended.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>If the changes are lengthy they could be set out in an additional schedule. If there are no special terms then delete this row of the table and the reference to "Special terms".</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a103819" level="2">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Schedules</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Remove any schedules that are not used from the Contract Details table.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a778662" level="2">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Priority of documents</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Underneath the Contract Details table, paragraph 1 explains the different parts of the contract and paragraph 2 sets out the order of precedence in the event of conflicts between them. Check that the order proposed is correct for your contract. In any event, the different parts should be closely scrutinised and amended to resolve any conflicts which can be identified in advance.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A court will, insofar as possible, read the different parts as complementing each other and only resort to the order of precedence in the case of a clear and irreconcilable discrepancy. For more information on conflicts clauses, see <link href="7-107-3836" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Conflict</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </division>
          </drafting.note>
          <para>
            <paratext><bold>SUPPLY OF SERVICES CONTRACT</bold></paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext><bold>CONTRACT DETAILS</bold></paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext><bold>DATE:</bold></paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext>
              <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
                <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="34"/>
                  <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="65"/>
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>[Contract No:]</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[CONTRACT NUMBER]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Customer:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[COMPANY NAME] LIMITED (No. [NUMBER])</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Customer's address:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[POSTAL ADDRESS]</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Email: [EMAIL ADDRESS]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Supplier:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[COMPANY NAME] LIMITED (No. [NUMBER])</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Supplier's address:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[POSTAL ADDRESS]</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Email: [EMAIL ADDRESS]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Supplier's VAT number:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[NUMBER]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Effective Date:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[[DATE] <bold>OR</bold> The date when the Contract has been signed by all the parties.]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Services:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[DESCRIPTION][, as further detailed in <internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>].</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Deliverables:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[DESCRIPTION][, as further detailed in <internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>].</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Charges:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[[SUMS][, as further detailed in <internal.reference refid="a598248"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>] <bold>OR</bold> the charges for the Services set out in the Supplier's price list at the Effective Date displayed at [WHERE CHARGES ARE SHOWN]].</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>[Special terms:]</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[In the Conditions:</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[(a) Clause [NUMBER] deleted: The entire text of clause [NUMBER] is deleted and replaced with the words "Not used".]</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[(b) Clause [NUMBER] replaced: The entire text of clause [NUMBER] is deleted and replaced with: "[NEW CLAUSE]."]</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[(c) Clause [NUMBER] added: A new clause [NUMBER] is inserted into the Conditions: "[NEW CLAUSE]."]</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[d) Clause [NUMBER] amended: This clause is amended to read as follows: "[AMENDED CLAUSE IN FULL]."]]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><bold>Schedules:</bold></paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[<internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>: Services.</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><internal.reference refid="a598248"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>: Charges.</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><internal.reference refid="a381794"><ital>Schedule 3</ital></internal.reference>: Policies.</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext><internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>: Data protection.</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>[INSERT DETAILS OF ADDITIONAL SCHEDULES].]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
            </paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext>1. This Contract is made up of the following:</paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext>(a) The Contract Details.</paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext>(b) The Conditions.</paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext>[(c) The Schedules specified in the Contract Details.]</paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext>2. If there is any conflict or ambiguity between the terms of the documents listed in paragraph 1, a term contained in a document higher in the list has priority over one contained in a document lower in the list.</paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext>This Contract has been entered into on the date stated at the beginning of it.</paratext>
          </para>
          <para>
            <paratext>
              <table frame="none" pgwide="1">
                <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="64"/>
                  <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="35"/>
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Signed by [NAME OF DIRECTOR]</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>for and on behalf of [NAME OF CUSTOMER]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>...................................</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Director</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Signed by [NAME OF DIRECTOR]</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>for and on behalf of [NAME OF SUPPLIER]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>...................................</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Director</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
            </paratext>
          </para>
        </preamble>
        <operative xrefname="clause">
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>Agreed terms</headtext>
          </head>
          <clause id="a987444">
            <identifier>1.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Interpretation</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a525199" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Interpretation</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000004" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>In the interests of saving space, we have used a short form interpretation clause. For a full clause, and information on the interpretation provisions in this agreement, see <link href="5-107-3795" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Interpretation</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a738679">
              <identifier>1.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Definitions</bold>:</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a882031" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Definitions</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000005" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>When reviewing this agreement:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Delete any definition that is not used in this agreement.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Consider whether any definitions need to be added.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Check each definition carefully to make sure it means what you intend it to mean and amend where necessary.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Be consistent. Where a capitalised term is used, do not introduce it without capitals later on or use a different form of words to mean the same thing.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a142316">
                <defn.term>Affiliate</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in relation to a party, any entity that directly or indirectly controls, is controlled by, or is under common control with that party [from time to time <bold>OR</bold> at the Effective Date].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a110084" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Affiliate (optional definition)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000006" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This definition is used optionally in this agreement, including in:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><internal.reference refid="a664363"><ital>Clause 6.3(a)</ital></internal.reference> allowing the customer to sub-license the right to use the deliverables to its affiliates.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><internal.reference refid="a228377"><ital>Clause 10.2</ital></internal.reference> allowing the parties to transfer rights and obligations under this agreement to their affiliates.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><internal.reference refid="a991699"><ital>Clause 10.3(b)</ital></internal.reference> allowing the recipient of confidential information to share it with affiliates.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Delete this definition and the references to the term in this agreement if the term does not need to be used.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a284283">
                <defn.term>Applicable Laws</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all applicable laws, statutes, regulations [and codes] from time to time in force.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a196880">
                <defn.term>Business Day</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>a day other than a Saturday, Sunday or public holiday in England, when banks in London are open for business.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a850049">
                <defn.term>Charges</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the charges payable by the Customer for the supply of the Services by the Supplier, as set out in the Contract Details [and <internal.reference refid="a598248"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a512545">
                <defn.term>Conditions</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>these terms and conditions set out in <internal.reference refid="a987444"><ital>clause 1</ital></internal.reference> to <internal.reference refid="a989592"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference> (inclusive).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a579086">
                <defn.term>Confidential Information</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all information (however recorded or preserved) that one party discloses or makes available to the other party (<defn.term>recipient</defn.term>) in connection with the Contract and which would be regarded as confidential by a reasonable business person. It includes any information [of a confidential nature] relating to the Charges or the operations, products or customers of [the Supplier <bold>OR</bold> either party] [(or any of its Affiliates)]. It does not include information that is or becomes generally available to the public through no fault of the recipient; is independently developed by or for the recipient; or was, is or becomes available to the recipient on a non-confidential basis from a person who, to the recipient's knowledge, is under no confidentiality obligation with respect to that information.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a691180">
                <defn.term>Contract</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the contract between the Customer and the Supplier for the supply of the Services comprising the Contract Details[, these Conditions and any Schedules specified in the Contract Details <bold>OR</bold> and these Conditions].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a906984">
                <defn.term>control</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>has the meaning given in section 1124 of the Corporation Tax Act 2010, and <defn.term>controls</defn.term> and <defn.term>controlled</defn.term> shall be interpreted accordingly.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a655942">
                <defn.term>Customer Materials</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all documents, information, [software,] items and materials (whether owned by the Customer or a third party), which are provided by the Customer to the Supplier in connection with the Services.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a392592">
                <defn.term>Deliverables</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the deliverables to be provided by the Supplier as specified in the Contract Details [and <internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>] [and all other documents, products, [software] and other materials developed by the Supplier for the Customer in the performance of the Services].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a938425" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Deliverables</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000007" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The deliverables refer to the output (if any) of the services, for example, a report. The nature of the deliverables should be tailored to reflect the type of service being provided.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Without the second set of wording in brackets, the deliverables are limited to those specified in the Contract Details cover sheet and, optionally, <internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>. This makes it a narrow definition, which is more favourable to the supplier, although the wording in square brackets can be used to broaden the definition to any materials developed in the performance of the services if there is push-back from customers.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a135194">
                <defn.term>Effective Date</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>as set out in the Contract Details.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a854493">
                <defn.term>Intellectual Property Rights</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>patents, [utility models,] rights to inventions, copyright and [neighbouring and] related rights, [moral rights,] trade marks [and service marks], business names and domain names, rights in get-up [and trade dress], goodwill and the right to sue for passing off [or unfair competition], rights in designs, [rights in computer software,] database rights, rights to use, and protect the confidentiality of, confidential information (including know-how [and trade secrets]) and all other intellectual property rights, in each case whether registered or unregistered and including all applications and rights to apply for and be granted renewals or extensions of, and rights to claim priority from, those rights and all similar or equivalent rights or forms of protection which subsist or will subsist now or in the future in any part of the world.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a167449">
                <defn.term>Losses</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all liabilities, damages, losses (including loss of profits, loss of business, loss of reputation, loss of savings and loss of opportunity), fines, expenses and costs (including all interest, penalties, legal costs (calculated on a full indemnity basis) and [reasonable] professional costs and expenses).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a629042">
                <defn.term>Policies</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the [Supplier's <bold>OR</bold> Customer's] business policies set out in <internal.reference refid="a381794"><ital>Schedule 3</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a325889" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Policies (optional definition)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000008" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The supplier may optionally commit to comply with certain business policies. These policies may include those on modern slavery and human trafficking, values and ethics and anti-bribery. If the supplier chooses to commit to comply with policies, it may prefer to put forward its own policies in an attempt to avoid customers requiring it to comply with their policies. For more information on compliance with policies, see <link href="6-618-9498" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Compliance with laws and policies</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a280250">
                <defn.term>Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the services, including any Deliverables, set out in the Contract Details [and <internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a343069">
              <identifier>1.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Interpretation</bold>:</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a711853" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Interpretation of certain references</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000009" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For information on the individual provisions in this clause, see <link href="5-107-3795" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Interpretation</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
              <subclause2 id="a637272">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A <defn.term>person </defn.term>includes a natural person, corporate or unincorporated body (whether or not having separate legal personality).</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a867928">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Unless expressly provided otherwise in the Contract, a <bold>OR</bold> A] reference to legislation or a legislative provision:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a693318">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>is a reference to it as [amended, extended or re-enacted from time to time <bold>OR</bold> it is in force as at the Effective Date]; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a449694">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>includes all subordinate legislation made [from time to time <bold>OR</bold> as at the Effective Date] under that legislation or legislative provision.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a396489">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Any words following the terms <bold>including</bold>, <bold>include</bold>, <bold>in particular</bold>, <bold>for example</bold> or any similar expression shall be interpreted as illustrative and shall not limit the sense of the words preceding those terms.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a569301">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A reference to <bold>writing</bold> or <bold>written</bold> excludes fax but not email.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a871864">
            <identifier>2.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Term</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a362426" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Term</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000010" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a871864"><ital>clause 2</ital></internal.reference> envisages a minimum term during which the parties can only terminate the agreement for breach or insolvency (see <internal.reference refid="a321263"><ital>clause 9</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>After this initial period, the contract continues, but both parties also have the right to terminate it by giving written notice to the other.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A supplier should not agree to an indefinite term with no right to terminate for convenience, particularly if no price increase mechanism has been agreed.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For information on commencement clauses, drafting options for different arrangements and the implications of not specifying a start date, see <link href="2-381-1963" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clauses, Commencement and duration</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a366788" numbering="none">
            <para>
              <paratext>The Contract [starts <bold>OR</bold> is deemed to have started on] the Effective Date and continues, unless terminated earlier in accordance with its terms, until either party gives to the other not less than [NUMBER] months' notice to terminate, expiring on or after the [first] anniversary of the Effective Date.</paratext>
            </para>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a241318">
            <identifier>3.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Supply of services</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a988210" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Supply of services</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000011" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a241318"><ital>clause 3</ital></internal.reference> sets out the principal obligations of the supplier with regard to the services. While it would be possible to include fewer obligations, the key areas of concern for customers have been included in the interests of reaching an agreement.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Services contracts are governed by the <link href="3-507-0623" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982</ital></link> (SGSA) and the common law. For information on terms implied into services contracts by the SGSA and common law, see <link href="2-501-7221" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Drafting standard terms and conditions for the supply of services</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a709049">
              <identifier>3.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall supply the Services to the Customer from the Effective Date in accordance with the Contract [in all material respects].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a568551">
              <identifier>3.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>In supplying the Services, the Supplier shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a722241">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>perform the Services with reasonable care and skill [in accordance with the generally recognised standards and practices in its industry];</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a959771" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Care and skill in the provision of the services</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000012" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The <link href="3-507-0623" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>SGSA</ital></link> implies a term that the supplier will carry out services with reasonable care and skill (<link href="2-507-0628" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 13</ital></link>). The supplier could therefore omit this clause.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>However, many suppliers opt to include a clause on the standard of services because customers expect to see it and to pre-empt customers inserting wording that imposes a higher standard, for example by reference to "best industry practice".</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Use the optional wording in brackets where the supplier wants to make clear that its performance will be in line with standard practice in its industry.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <division id="a663832" level="2">
                      <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                        <headtext>Service levels</headtext>
                      </head>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>This agreement does not commit the supplier to meeting service levels or include a scheme whereby the customer receives credits against the cost of the services if service levels are not achieved. Instead, if the supplier fails to achieve the required standard for the services, the customer will have to claim damages and possibly terminate (see <internal.reference refid="a335731"><ital>clause 8</ital></internal.reference> for limitations on the supplier's liability and <internal.reference refid="a321263"><ital>clause 9</ital></internal.reference> for the customer's contractual termination rights).</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Drafting for a service level and service credit regime can be found in <link anchor="a113713" href="5-213-3958" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Outsourcing agreement: shorter form: clause 7</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Although service credits may seem to be pro-customer provisions, provided they are well drafted they can benefit a supplier if they are the customer's exclusive remedy for a certain degree of under-performance.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a573346">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>use [all] reasonable endeavours to meet any performance dates specified in the Contract but these dates are estimates only. Time is not of the essence for the performance of any of the Supplier's obligations in the Contract;</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a881564" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Time for performance</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000013" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a573346"><ital>clause 3.2(b)</ital></internal.reference> seeks to limit the customer's remedies if performance dates are not met. It provides that:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Time is not of the essence in respect of performance dates. If time were of the essence for a deadline, the customer would have a right to terminate if the deadline was missed. If there is no statement that time is of the essence, a party might argue that this term should be implied. Including the statement that time is not of the essence in <internal.reference refid="a573346"><ital>clause 3.2(b)</ital></internal.reference> should defeat that argument. For more information on time of the essence obligations, see <link href="3-107-3819" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Time of the essence</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>The supplier need only use reasonable (or all reasonable) endeavours to meet performance dates, which in any case are just estimates.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Where the time for performance is not fixed in the contract or by the parties' course of dealing, <link href="0-508-2613" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 14</ital></link> of the SGSA requires the supplier to carry out the services within a reasonable time.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a310855">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>comply with:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a998830">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all Applicable Laws[; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a799504">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Policies][,</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <para>
                  <paratext>provided that the Supplier shall not be liable under the Contract if, as a result of this compliance, it is in breach of any of its other obligations under the Contract]; and</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a764545" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Compliance with laws and policies</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000014" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a310855"><ital>Clause 3.2(c)</ital></internal.reference> is a general compliance clause requiring the supplier to comply with all applicable laws and, optionally, certain business policies which can be listed in optional <internal.reference refid="a381794"><ital>Schedule 3</ital></internal.reference>. For more information, see <internal.reference refid="a325889"><ital>Drafting note, Policies (optional definition)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <division id="a735658" level="2">
                      <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                        <headtext>Cost of compliance</headtext>
                      </head>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>This clause obliges the supplier to bear the costs of complying with the law and policies.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier may want to suggest that some costs caused by changes to the law should be borne by the customer. For drafting requiring the customer to agree to changes to the services and charges where necessary to comply with changes in law, see <link anchor="a153357" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 9.6</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a780290">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[use reasonable endeavours to] ensure its staff observe all reasonable health and safety and security requirements that apply at any of the Customer's premises they access and have been communicated to the Supplier in advance in writing. The Supplier shall not be liable under the Contract if, as a result of observing these requirements, it is in breach of any of its other obligations under the Contract.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a600997" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Compliance with health and safety and security requirements (optional clause)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000015" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This optional <internal.reference refid="a780290"><ital>clause 3.2(d)</ital></internal.reference> is unlikely to be necessary if supplier personnel will have negligible access to customer premises. In any event, the supplier may not want to offer any obligations to comply with health and safety or security requirements at customer premises in a first draft.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a587350">
            <identifier>4.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Customer's obligations</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a273888" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Customer's obligations</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000016" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a587350"><ital>clause 4</ital></internal.reference> sets out some general obligations on the customer. However, if the customer has significant responsibilities, or there are specific obligations which the customer must carry out before the supplier can perform the contracted services ("customer dependencies"), it may be best to set them out in a schedule to avoid future disputes and to ensure it is clear that the supplier's ability to deliver is dependent on the customer first meeting those dependencies. For an example, see <link anchor="a248038" href="5-213-3958" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Outsourcing agreement: shorter form: Schedule 7, Customer's Responsibilities</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a807447">
              <identifier>4.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a972323">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>co-operate with the Supplier in all matters relating to the Services [and ensure that its other suppliers co-operate with the Supplier where reasonably necessary];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a400737">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>provide the Supplier and its subcontractors, in a timely manner, with access to the Customer's premises and other facilities as [reasonably] required by the Supplier for the performance of the Services;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a253462">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>provide the Supplier, in a timely manner, with all information and materials as the Supplier may [reasonably] require to provide the Services and ensure that they are accurate and complete [in all material respects]; [and]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a141092">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>comply with all Applicable Laws in its performance of the Contract[; and <bold>OR</bold> .]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a240515">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[ANY OTHER OBLIGATIONS.]</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a855395" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Other customer obligations (optional clause)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000017" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For other customer obligations to consider including, see <link anchor="a166487" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 5.1</ital></link>. For example, the supplier may want to include drafting requiring the customer to provide prompt feedback on draft deliverables submitted for approval.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a288262">
              <identifier>4.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>To the extent that the Supplier's performance of its obligations under the Contract is prevented or delayed by any act or omission of the Customer or any of its agents, consultants or other suppliers (<defn.term>Excusing Cause</defn.term>), the Supplier shall not be in breach of the Contract nor liable for any Losses incurred by the Customer as a result of its performance being prevented or delayed. Without prejudice to any other right or remedy it may have, the Supplier shall be:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a718256">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>allowed an extension of time to perform its obligations equal to the delay caused by the Excusing Cause;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a468015">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>entitled to payment of the Charges despite its performance being prevented or delayed; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a254606">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>entitled to recover any Losses, including additional costs, incurred as a result of the Excusing Cause.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a287042" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Customer's non-compliance with its obligations</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000018" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a288262"><ital>clause 4.2</ital></internal.reference> seeks to ensure that if the customer's action (or inaction) results in delay or non-performance by the supplier, the supplier incurs no liability, still gets paid and can recover any additional costs it incurs.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>While it may be possible to claim this relief under the common law without this drafting, some suppliers prefer to include specific provisions in their services agreements for certainty. Suppliers should be wary of customers introducing drafting that restricts the remedies that the supplier would otherwise have at common law, for example by:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Restricting the compensation which the supplier may claim.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Making the supplier's right to claim subject to the supplier giving the customer notice of the delay and taking specified steps to mitigate its effects.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Omitting the "without prejudice to any other right or remedy" wording.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause condition="optional" id="a145480">
            <identifier>5.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Data protection</headtext>
            </head>
            <subclause1 id="a752714">
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party shall comply with its data protection obligations set out in <internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a773794" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Data protection (optional clause)</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000019" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This is an optional clause for inclusion if the supplier will be processing <link href="8-200-3413" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>personal data</ital></link> pursuant to the <link href="w-026-8528" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>UK GDPR</ital></link> in connection with the performance of the services.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The UK GDPR defines processing widely to include, among other things, collection, recording, storage and exchange of personal data. For a start, the parties should consider the context and purpose in which personal data is being processed. For example:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>The personal data is processed as part of the service offering.</bold> An example would be where the supplier is engaged to provide an online survey to the customer's employees or end-users. Here, the supplier would be processing the personal data (of the employees or end-users) on the customer's behalf as its <link href="3-107-5724" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>processor</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>The personal data is processed for general contract management or communication purposes as opposed to being part of the service offering.</bold> For example, the agreement is for the provision of office cleaning services which, in itself, does not require the processing of any personal data. However, each party may provide the names and email addresses of employees who are responsible for managing the contract and dealing with the other party for that purpose. Each party processes this data as independent <link href="5-107-5723" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>controllers</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For a list of issues to consider when determining the parties' relationship, see <link href="w-019-8440" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Checklist, Controller or processor? (UK and EU)</ital></link>. Having ascertained the type of relationship, the parties can then insert the appropriate data protection provisions to reflect that relationship:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Controller-processor relationship. </bold>In a controller-processor relationship, the UK GDPR requires certain contractual terms to be documented in a binding written processing agreement.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Controller-controller relationship.</bold> Unlike in a controller-processor relationship, there is no obligation on businesses to document their relationship or their respective responsibilities where each is acting as an independent controller in respect of the same personal data. However, businesses sharing personal data sometimes want to include drafting to protect themselves from legal risks and demonstrate that they are taking their responsibilities as a controller seriously.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <division id="a282472" level="2">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Approach in this document</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>In <internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>, there are:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Controller-processor clauses required by the UK GDPR. As this is a supplier-friendly agreement, the drafting does not go beyond the minimum necessary to comply with the UK GDPR and gives the supplier as much flexibility as possible in the way in which it processes customer data. For example, the customer gives prior general authorisation for the supplier to appoint sub-processors and transfer personal data outside the UK.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Basic compliance with law commitments that would apply to data sharing as independent controllers. Again, as this is a pro-supplier agreement, the commitments are light. If the only processing of personal data is as independent controllers, the supplier could choose to omit the schedule altogether.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                  </division>
                  <division id="a588867" level="2">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Further drafting options</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The drafting in <internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference> is partly based on the following standard clauses which provide background information and further drafting if necessary:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><link href="w-027-8411" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Data processing clauses (UK)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><link href="w-026-6854" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Personal data processing clauses for IT agreements (UK) (pro-supplier)</ital></link> (while this is drafted with an IT focus, the general principles and drafting approach are just as applicable to a non-IT-based agreement).</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><link href="w-011-7560" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Personal data sharing clauses (controller to controller, short-form) (UK)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                  </division>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a443100">
            <identifier>6.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Intellectual property</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a155429" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Intellectual property rights (IPRs)</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000020" level="1">
                <division id="a412547" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>When IPRs are relevant in services agreements</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>IPRs are relevant in contracts for services wherever:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The customer is providing the supplier with something in which IPRs subsist to enable the supplier to perform the services (for example, its branding or information about its products). In this agreement, these things are defined as "Customer Materials".</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier is, as part of the services, providing the customer with something in which IPRs subsist. These might include materials (such as instructions or software) which the supplier or a third party has already developed or materials developed as part of the services (such as bespoke reports or advertising creative). The supplier may:</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <list type="bulleted">
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext>licence the customer to use materials where the supplier wants to continue using the materials itself. This is usually the case with materials developed before the services start and is sometimes the case with materials developed as part of the services; or</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext>assign ownership of materials to the customer. This is often what the customer wants in relation to materials developed as part of the services. But if the supplier's business model is that materials developed under one client contract can be used in its services generally, including with other clients, it will only want to license these materials on a non-exclusive basis.</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                      </list>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
                <division id="a948669" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Approach in this document</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This agreement takes the following approach:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The customer licenses the supplier to use customer materials to provide the services.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier retains ownership of all intellectual property rights in the deliverables (excluding any customer materials, ownership of which is retained by the customer).</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier grants the customer a non-exclusive licence to use the deliverables. Options for the duration of the licence and whether sub-licensing is permitted are included in square brackets.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>If the supplier wants to include third party-owned materials in the deliverables and those materials cannot be licensed on the same terms as the deliverables (for example, because they are only licensed on the third party's standard terms), the supplier will either obtain the customer's consent to include them or, in a more supplier-friendly version, simply inform the customer of the licensing terms.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the supplier will be assigning ownership of the deliverables, rather than licensing them, see <link anchor="a812379" href="3-623-0753" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-customer): clause 10</ital></link> for suggested wording. As well as an assignment, this drafting includes:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>A carve-out from the assignment for any of the supplier's proprietary materials included in the deliverables. The supplier continues to own these materials and licenses the customer to use them instead of assigning them.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>A licence from the customer to the supplier to use the deliverables that are assigned to the customer. The supplier needs to continue to use those materials to service the customer.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a421827">
              <identifier>6.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier and its licensors shall retain ownership of all Intellectual Property Rights in the Deliverables, excluding any Customer Materials contained within them.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a837580">
              <identifier>6.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[Subject [to <internal.reference refid="a738015"><ital>clause 6.4</ital></internal.reference> and] to the Supplier receiving payment of all Charges attributable to the Deliverables,] the Supplier grants to the Customer a non-exclusive, royalty-free, non-transferable (except in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a228377"><ital>clause 10.2</ital></internal.reference>), [perpetual [and irrevocable] licence <bold>OR</bold> licence during the term of the Contract] [(with the right to grant sublicences)] to use, copy and modify the Deliverables for the purpose of receiving and using the Services and Deliverables in the Customer's business.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a501909" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Scope of licence</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000021" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the customer accepts a licence (rather than an assignment) of the deliverables, it will want the licence to be perpetual and ideally irrevocable. If there are any elements of the deliverables that the supplier cannot license perpetually (for example, because they are proprietary tools that can only be used by existing customers), those items could be carved out from a perpetual licence to the customer and, instead, licensed for the term of the agreement (or a different period).</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><internal.reference refid="a837580"><ital>Clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference> includes optional, supplier-friendly wording so that the licence is subject to the customer paying for the deliverables. Some customers may object to this and argue that the supplier has remedies if the customer fails to pay or is late making payments. From the supplier's perspective, making the customer's usage of the deliverables contingent on payment is useful leverage to ensure payments are made on time.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <division id="a917729" level="2">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Sublicensing</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Include the optional wording about having the right to grant sublicences if the customer is free to sublicense use of the deliverables. Alternatively, delete this optional wording and use optional <internal.reference refid="a985467"><ital>clause 6.3</ital></internal.reference> which includes a complete or partial restriction on sublicensing without consent.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a985467">
              <identifier>6.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer [shall not sublicense the rights granted in <internal.reference refid="a837580"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference> without the Supplier's prior written consent <bold>OR</bold> may sublicense the rights granted in <internal.reference refid="a837580"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference>:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a664363">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>to its Affiliates [and customers]; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a245047">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>other third parties with the Supplier's prior written consent].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a738015">
              <identifier>6.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[The Customer acknowledges that the Supplier may need to include materials belonging to third parties which cannot be licensed on the terms of <internal.reference refid="a837580"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference> (<defn.term>Third Party Materials</defn.term>) within the Deliverables <bold>OR</bold> The Supplier shall not include in the Deliverables any materials belonging to third parties that cannot be licensed to the Customer on the terms of <internal.reference refid="a837580"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference> (<defn.term>Third Party Materials</defn.term>) unless their inclusion and licence terms are approved in writing in advance by the Customer]. The Supplier shall grant to the Customer a licence (at the Customer's cost) to use any Third Party Materials [included in <bold>OR</bold> approved by the Customer for inclusion in] the Deliverables on the terms [permitted by the third party <bold>OR</bold> approved by the Customer]. The Customer shall comply with the terms (including any usage restrictions) that apply to the Third Party Materials and which have been [provided to the Customer <bold>OR</bold> approved by the Customer] in writing. [The Supplier's liability in relation to Third Party Materials shall be limited to the liability accepted by the third party under the relevant licence agreement.]</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a169789" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Third party materials (optional clause)</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000022" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a738015"><ital>clause 6.4</ital></internal.reference> includes two options for the licensing of third party materials that cannot be licensed on the same terms as <internal.reference refid="a837580"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference>:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Option 1.</bold> The supplier is able to include third party materials in the deliverables without the customer's prior approval of the materials or their licence terms. The customer must comply with any usage restrictions made known to the customer in writing. Use the first set of wording in each square bracket if using this option. This is the most supplier-friendly option.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Option 2.</bold> The supplier is only able to include third party materials in the deliverables with the customer's prior approval of the materials and their licence terms. The customer must comply with any usage restrictions approved by the customer in writing. Use the second set of wording in each square bracket if using this option.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The final sentence is optional wording to limit the supplier's liability for third party materials to the liability that the third party accepts.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a457806">
              <identifier>6.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer and its licensors shall retain ownership of all Intellectual Property Rights in the Customer Materials. The Customer grants the Supplier a non-exclusive, royalty-free licence to use, copy and modify the Customer Materials during the term of the Contract for the purpose of providing the Services to the Customer. The Supplier may grant sublicences of the Customer Materials to its subcontractors and other suppliers where necessary for the performance of the Services.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a409792">
              <identifier>6.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall indemnify the Customer against all [Losses incurred by the Customer <bold>OR</bold> sums awarded against the Customer by a court] as a result of any claim that the supply, receipt or use of any of the Deliverables infringes the Intellectual Property Rights of any third party. The Supplier shall not be liable under this indemnity to the extent that the actual or alleged infringement arises from:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a721332">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any changes made to the Deliverables without the Supplier's prior written consent (not to be unreasonably withheld);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a708499">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>instructions, information or materials provided by the Customer for the development of the Deliverables; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a554978">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the use of the Deliverables for a purpose or in a manner not authorised by the Supplier or the failure of the Customer to adhere to the Supplier's [reasonable] instructions for the use of the Deliverables.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a394464">
              <identifier>6.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall indemnify the Supplier against all [Losses incurred by the Supplier <bold>OR</bold> sums awarded against the Supplier by a court] as a result of any claim that the supply, receipt or use of the Customer Materials infringes the Intellectual Property Rights of any third party. The Customer shall not be liable under this indemnity to the extent that the actual or alleged infringement arises from the use of the Customer Materials for a purpose or in a manner not authorised by the Customer.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a840580" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>IPR indemnities</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000023" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>There is a risk that both the deliverables and the customer materials may infringe third party intellectual property rights. If the risk that the deliverables infringe third party rights is greater, it may be preferable to omit any indemnities altogether. However, if the risk of the customer materials infringing third party rights is high or if the customer insists on an indemnity in respect of the deliverables infringing third party rights, then the supplier may need to include an appropriate clause.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Use the second set of optional wording in each indemnity to limit recovery to sums awarded by a court and not other costs (for example, costs in relation to settled claims). It is more typical for an indemnity to be comprehensive, covering "all losses". Many customers expect full indemnity protection from suppliers creating materials for them. Use the first option in each indemnity for that drafting.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Unless the indemnity from the supplier at <internal.reference refid="a409792"><ital>clause 6.6</ital></internal.reference> is stated to be outside the general cap on the supplier's liability in <internal.reference refid="a335731"><ital>clause 8</ital></internal.reference>, it will be within it. There is optional wording in <internal.reference refid="a335731"><ital>clause 8</ital></internal.reference> to exclude indemnities from the limitations on liability or to include a separate liability cap for them.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the customer's liability is uncapped in this agreement, the customer's IPR indemnity would also be uncapped.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier may want to include drafting giving it the right to avoid any third party infringement claim by procuring a licence to use the infringing deliverables or modifying them so that they cease to infringe. For this drafting, see <link anchor="a653879" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 11.7</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier may also want to consider including conduct of claims wording, for example, requiring the customer to let the supplier control the defence of any third party claim that the deliverables infringe IPRs. For more information and drafting, see <link href="1-107-3797" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Indemnity</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a834748">
            <identifier>7.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Charges and payment</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a667957" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Charges and payment</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000024" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>There are a number of different mechanisms for pricing arrangements. These can be on a time and materials basis, a fixed fee basis or a combination of the two.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A time and materials fee approach can benefit the supplier because it allows the supplier to charge for all the work it actually does. With a fixed price for services and a demanding customer, the supplier may risk providing more services than the customer has actually paid for.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on charging methods, see <link anchor="a460226" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): Drafting note: Charges and payment</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This short form agreement does not include a clause allowing the supplier to increase the charges during the contract term. This type of drafting is unlikely to be necessary if the services are provided only for a short period of time. If this drafting is required, see <link anchor="a602830" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 10.4</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a428036">
              <identifier>7.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>In consideration for the provision of the Services, the Customer shall pay the Supplier the Charges in accordance with this <internal.reference refid="a834748"><ital>clause 7</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a866844">
              <identifier>7.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall reimburse the Supplier for the following expenses and costs which are excluded from the Charges:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a771509">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the cost of hotel, subsistence, travelling and any other ancillary expenses reasonably incurred by the Supplier's personnel in connection with the Services (<defn.term>Expenses</defn.term>)[, provided that the Supplier obtains the Customer's prior written approval before incurring [any individual expense item exceeding [AMOUNT] <bold>OR</bold> any expenses over [AMOUNT] in any calendar month]]; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a945575">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the cost to the Supplier of any materials or services procured by the Supplier from third parties for the provision of the Services (<defn.term>Third Party Costs</defn.term>)[, provided that the Supplier obtains the Customer's prior written approval before incurring [any individual Third Party Cost exceeding [AMOUNT] <bold>OR</bold> any Third Party Costs over [AMOUNT] in any calendar month]].</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a205331" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Costs and expenses</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000025" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a866844"><ital>Clause 7.2</ital></internal.reference> provides for certain expenses and third party costs to be payable in addition to the charges.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>There is optional wording requiring the supplier to obtain the customer's approval for any individual expense or cost or aggregated expenses or costs over a certain amount.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a726957">
              <identifier>7.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>All sums payable by the Customer exclude amounts in respect of value added tax (<defn.term>VAT</defn.term>). The Customer shall, on receipt of a valid VAT invoice from the Supplier, pay to the Supplier any additional amounts in respect of VAT as are chargeable on those sums.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a126404" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>VAT</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000026" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Unless the contract provides otherwise, the price of the services will be deemed to be inclusive of VAT (<link href="0-507-3468" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 19(2)</ital></link><ital>, Value Added Tax Act 1994</ital>). In b2b contracts, prices typically exclude VAT because businesses can generally recover all or part of the amounts paid in respect of VAT as input tax.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a265374">
              <identifier>7.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall invoice the Customer for the Charges [at the [start <bold>OR</bold> end] of each month for Services [performed in that month <bold>OR</bold> to be performed in the following month] <bold>OR </bold>at the intervals specified in <internal.reference refid="a598248"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>].</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a346115" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Invoicing schedule for charges</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000027" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext><internal.reference refid="a265374"><ital>Clause 7.4</ital></internal.reference> includes drafting for different invoicing options, including:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Monthly in advance.</bold> Invoices issued at the start of the month for the next month's activity. This way, the supplier is paid before it starts providing the next month's services. If the supplier's charges are variable (for example, where it charges on a time and materials basis), invoicing in advance is unlikely to work. If the customer objects to invoicing in the month before activity, the supplier could suggest invoicing at the start of the month in which the work takes place, meaning it will be paid at the end of that month (assuming 30-day payment terms).</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Monthly in arrears.</bold> Invoices are issued at the end of the month in which activity takes place. The downside of this approach for the supplier is that it has to wait to be paid for a month after work is completed.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a125709">
              <identifier>7.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall invoice the Customer monthly in arrears for Expenses and Third Party Costs. [The Supplier shall provide invoices or receipts for Expenses and Third Party Costs if requested by the Customer.]</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a582073" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Invoicing schedule for expenses and third party costs</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000028" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The default position is that the supplier invoices the customer in arrears for expenses and third party costs. This approach is usually acceptable for a supplier where the volume of expenses and third party costs is relatively low.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the supplier will be incurring significant third party costs for the customer's benefit but does not want to pay for those costs out of its own funds, it could include a clause allowing it to invoice earlier so that it receives funds from the customer before it has to pay the third party. For drafting, see <link anchor="a336845" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 10.8</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a437190">
              <identifier>7.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall pay each invoice submitted to it by the Supplier within [30] days of [the invoice date <bold>OR</bold> receipt] to a bank account nominated in writing by the Supplier.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a545567">
              <identifier>7.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Without prejudice to any other right or remedy that the Supplier may have, if the Customer fails to pay any sum due to the Supplier under the Contract by the due date:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a274802">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer shall pay interest on the overdue sum from the due date until payment of the overdue sum, whether before or after judgment. Interest under this clause will accrue each day at [4]% a year above the [Bank of England's] base rate from time to time, but at [4]% a year for any period when that base rate is below 0%; and</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a325217" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Interest on late payments</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000029" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on interest clauses, see the drafting notes to <link href="3-107-3800" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Interest</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a485619">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier may suspend all or part of the Services until payment has been made in full.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a234742">
              <identifier>7.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>All amounts due under the Contract from the Customer to the Supplier shall be paid in full without any set-off, counterclaim, deduction or withholding (other than any deduction or withholding of tax as required by law).</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a898826" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Set-off</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000030" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The parties will each have set-off rights under common law. This clause excludes the customer's right of set-off. If the Conditions constitute written standard terms, this may give rise to UCTA issues. For information on set-off clauses, see the drafting notes to <link href="9-107-3802" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Set-off</ital></link>. For optional wording requiring the customer to gross up any payments subject to withholding tax so that the supplier receives the full amount, see <link anchor="a335789" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 10.10(b)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a335731">
            <identifier>8.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Limitation of liability</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a155623" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Limitation of liability</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000031" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>Limitation of liability is always a key issue in a services contract and is likely to be heavily negotiated between the parties. Tailor this <internal.reference refid="a335731"><ital>clause 8</ital></internal.reference> for your particular transaction.</paratext>
                </para>
                <division id="a576151" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Approach in this clause</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This clause sets out a typical structure for a limitation of liability clause which is commonly found in services agreements. It is divided into the following sections:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Unlimited liabilities.</bold> Neither party limits those liabilities which cannot be limited as a matter of law. There is also the option to leave other potential liabilities unlimited, such as those arising from failure to pay amounts due.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Treatment of certain categories of loss.</bold> The clause provides wording to exclude certain categories of loss, such as indirect and consequential loss. In some agreements, the clause may then make exceptions to this exclusion, so that certain types of loss or specific losses are recoverable. For example, the agreement could specify that wasted expenditure in general is excluded but that certain specific costs are not. Or that loss of business in general is excluded but loss of a particular client or contract is not. As this is a pro-supplier agreement, there is no clause specifying losses that are not excluded (and therefore definitely recoverable) as this is usually for the customer's benefit. For this drafting, see <link anchor="a819714" href="w-010-2114" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Limitation of liability: clause 1.7</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Capped liabilities.</bold> Each party limits all other liabilities which might arise to a capped amount.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information on limitations of liability and alternative drafting, see <link href="w-010-2114" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Limitation of liability</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a710348">
              <identifier>8.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The following definitions apply in this <internal.reference refid="a335731"><ital>clause 8</ital></internal.reference>:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a550245">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><defn.term>contract year</defn.term>: each 12-month period starting on the Effective Date or an anniversary of it;</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a994572" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Contract year (optional clause)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000032" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Delete <internal.reference refid="a550245"><ital>clause 8.1(a)</ital></internal.reference> if there is no annual liability cap (see <internal.reference refid="a255942"><ital>Drafting note, Liability cap</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a125933">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><defn.term>default</defn.term>: any act or omission resulting in one party incurring liability to the other; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a110208">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><defn.term>liability</defn.term>: every kind of liability arising under or in connection with the Contract including liability in contract, tort (including negligence) or otherwise.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a844812" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Scope of limitations</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000033" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a110208"><ital>Clause 8.1(c)</ital></internal.reference> is designed to ensure that the caps and exclusions capture not just liability for breach of contract but also other liabilities "in connection with" the contract. These could include liability for breach of confidence, misrepresentation, undue influence, or torts such as negligence, conversion and breach of statutory duty. For more information about this clause, see <link anchor="a828907" href="w-010-2114" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Limitation of liability: Drafting note: Scope of this clause (long form)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a565708">
              <identifier>8.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Nothing in the Contract limits or excludes:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a436980">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>liability for deliberate default;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a297736">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>liability for death or personal injury caused by negligence to the extent preserved by section 2(1) of the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a479329">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>liability for fraud or fraudulent misrepresentation;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a441891">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>liability for breach of the terms implied by section 2 of the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a754117">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any liability that cannot legally be limited; [or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a775141">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[the Customer's <bold>OR</bold> either party's] liability for its payment obligations under the Contract; [or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a727392">
                <identifier>(g)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>either party's liability under the indemnities in <internal.reference refid="a443100"><ital>clause 6</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a545701" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Unlimited liabilities</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000034" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a565708"><ital>Clause 8.2</ital></internal.reference> sets out exceptions to the limitations of liability.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <division id="a102823" level="2">
                      <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                        <headtext>Deliberate default</headtext>
                      </head>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Where a party's liability is limited, there is a risk that it will decide that it is cheaper to walk away from a contract, or simply not perform part of it, and incur the limited liability rather than the costs of complying with the contract. Optional <internal.reference refid="a436980"><ital>clause 8.2(a)</ital></internal.reference> is intended to deter a party from doing this by disapplying the limits and exclusions where liability arises from deliberate default.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Alternatively, if the supplier would like to make certain that liability for deliberate default falls within the limits and exclusions of liability, it should delete <internal.reference refid="a436980"><ital>clause 8.2(a)</ital></internal.reference> and add "deliberate default" to the definition of liability in <internal.reference refid="a110208"><ital>clause 8.1(c)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                    <division id="a102391" level="2">
                      <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                        <headtext>Liabilities which parties cannot legally limit</headtext>
                      </head>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Statute prohibits the limitation or exclusion of the claims listed in <internal.reference refid="a297736"><ital>clause 8.2(b)</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a441891"><ital>clause 8.2(d)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Case law establishes that, as a matter of public policy, a party cannot exclude liability for its own fraudulent misrepresentation inducing contract formation. It is not entirely clear whether a party can exclude its liability for other types of fraud (particularly by a party's agents). However, in practice, parties generally want losses resulting from fraud to be uncapped and <internal.reference refid="a479329"><ital>clause 8.2(c)</ital></internal.reference> aims to achieve this.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                    <division id="a671696" level="2">
                      <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                        <headtext>Payment obligations</headtext>
                      </head>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The intention of a limitation clause is to cap liability for breach of the parties' non-financial obligations such as breach of confidentiality or wrongful termination of the agreement. A supplier will not want to cap the customer's duties to make agreed payments such as the price and interest on late payments.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><internal.reference refid="a775141"><ital>Clause 8.2(f)</ital></internal.reference> therefore removes the cap from the customer's payment obligations arising under the agreement. The drafting also has the effect that the customer's payment obligations cannot fall within any of the categories of excluded loss in <internal.reference refid="a120615"><ital>clause 8.4</ital></internal.reference>. The supplier may choose to make the clause mutual, presenting it as balanced although the bulk of the payment obligations are likely to rest with the customer.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                    <division id="a831154" level="2">
                      <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                        <headtext>IPR indemnities</headtext>
                      </head>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Under <internal.reference refid="a727392"><ital>clause 8.2(g)</ital></internal.reference>, the IPR indemnities in <internal.reference refid="a443100"><ital>clause 6</ital></internal.reference> can optionally be excluded from the limitations of liability. This is often the case in services agreement, although the supplier may instead want to propose that the IPR indemnities are capped, either under the general cap or at a higher level than the general liability cap (see <internal.reference refid="a820093"><ital>clause 8.3(a)</ital></internal.reference>). If the supplier is more likely to be the indemnifying party under the IPR indemnities, it is in its interests to cap liability under them.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>In a particularly pro-supplier agreement, the supplier could propose that the customer's liabilities under its IPR indemnity are unlimited, while the supplier's liabilities under the IPR indemnity it gives are limited. However, it is likely to be more acceptable to customers and smoother to negotiate if the approach is mutual.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a824217">
              <identifier>8.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Subject to <internal.reference refid="a565708"><ital>clause 8.2</ital></internal.reference>, [the Supplier's <bold>OR</bold> each party's] total liability:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a820093">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>under the indemnity it gives in <internal.reference refid="a443100"><ital>clause 6</ital></internal.reference> shall not exceed [AMOUNT];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a418247">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[for breaches occurring in any contract year] under <internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference> shall not exceed [AMOUNT]; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a375410">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>for all [other] loss or damage [arising from defaults occurring within any contract year] shall not exceed [[AMOUNT] <bold>OR</bold> the greater of [AMOUNT] and [100]% of the Charges paid [or payable] to the Supplier under the Contract] [in that contract year].</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a255942" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Liability cap</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000035" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>There are various ways to structure a liability cap (see <link anchor="a1037329" href="2-520-5359" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Limiting liability: drafting and negotiating: Ways to structure a cap</ital></link>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a824217"><ital>clause 8.3</ital></internal.reference> allows the supplier or each party to have separate liability caps for:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><bold>Intellectual property infringement.</bold> There is optional wording to cap liability for breach of the IPR indemnities in <internal.reference refid="a443100"><ital>clause 6</ital></internal.reference> at an amount that is separate to, and likely greater than, the general liability cap. This is a compromise between unlimited liability and liability being limited under the general cap. If using this option, delete the optional wording in <internal.reference refid="a727392"><ital>clause 8.2(g)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><bold>Losses arising from breaches of data protection obligations</bold>. If the supplier will be processing personal data on the customer's behalf, then the parties may want to include a separate cap for losses arising from data processing breaches. Given the potentially high fines under the UK GDPR, the supplier is likely to want a financial cap on its liability to the customer for data processing breaches. A customer that agrees to this is likely to want this cap to be separate from, and in addition to, the contract's overall liability cap. This avoids the risk that a data processing liability claim might exhaust all or most of a general cap, so that there is none left for other liabilities that are subsequently incurred. A separate cap for data protection breaches has become fairly common in services agreement. The supplier may need to offer it to prevent the customer insisting on unlimited liability instead.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><bold>Other losses.</bold> This general cap is drafted as either:</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <list type="bulleted">
                          <list.item>
                            <para>
                              <paratext><bold>a fixed amount.</bold> This may be most appropriate where the value of the contract is clear from the start. The fixed amount could simply be a multiple of the total sums payable over the full term of the agreement; or</paratext>
                            </para>
                          </list.item>
                          <list.item>
                            <para>
                              <paratext><bold>the greater of a fixed amount and a percentage of charges.</bold> This may be most appropriate where the parties are uncertain of what the charges will be and also want to ensure that a minimum amount is recoverable in the early days of the contract, where few services have been supplied and so the charges are low.</paratext>
                            </para>
                          </list.item>
                        </list>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The data protection and general caps provide two options:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><bold>A single cap for the duration of the contract.</bold> This option is likely to be best where the contract is short term.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><bold>An annual cap.</bold> This option is often used where services are provided over several years. For the customer, an annual cap avoids a situation in which the supplier, having paid out compensation once, has little or no liability for the remainder of the contract term. For the supplier, an annual cap prevents a situation in which the supplier's liability, if linked to the charges, increases year on year in a long term contract.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Use the "contract year" wording for an annual cap and remove it for a single cap.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a824217"><ital>clause 8.3</ital></internal.reference> can provide a mutual cap on each party's liability. Alternatively, it can just cap the supplier's liability leaving the customer's liability as uncapped.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For other drafting options, including separate liability caps for the customer and supplier, see <link href="w-010-2114" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Limitation of liability</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a120615">
              <identifier>8.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Subject to <internal.reference refid="a565708"><ital>clause 8.2</ital></internal.reference>, neither party shall have any liability for:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a864224">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of profits (including loss of anticipated savings);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a938620">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of business or business opportunity;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a670516">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of use or corruption of software, data or information;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a195455">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of or damage to goodwill; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a859651">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>indirect or consequential loss.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a941752" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Specific heads of excluded loss</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000036" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a120615"><ital>clause 8.4</ital></internal.reference> sets out the types of losses that a supplier may want to exclude.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Before deciding which losses to exclude, the supplier should identify the risks it faces and the legal constraints on excluding liability. If the supplier's drafting leaves the customer without a meaningful remedy for breach, the clause risks being ineffective (see <link anchor="a644068" href="w-006-5549" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Limiting liability: interpretation: Interpreting a total exclusion</ital></link>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Each party should also bear in mind that a more moderate position is easier to negotiate. A supplier will expect to see some exclusions from liability, while a customer will not expect to see a long list of excluded losses.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For more information about drafting and negotiating this clause, see <link anchor="a634896" href="w-010-2114" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Limitation of liability: Drafting note: Losses that are excluded</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For supplier-friendly drafting that relieves the supplier of liability where the customer uses draft deliverables as finished work without the supplier's consent, see <link anchor="a791155" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 5.2</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a599017">
              <identifier>8.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Subject to <internal.reference refid="a565708"><ital>clause 8.2</ital></internal.reference>, all conditions, warranties, representations or other terms that might otherwise be implied into this agreement by statute, common law or otherwise are excluded from the Contract.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a612333" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Exclusion of statutory implied terms (optional)</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000037" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="4-508-2593" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Sections 3 to 5</ital></link> of the SGSA (in respect of goods transferred under a services contract) imply terms that goods:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Will match their description (<ital>section 3, SGSA</ital>).</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Are of satisfactory quality and fit for their purpose (<ital>section 4, SGSA</ital>).</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Conform to any sample and be free from defects (<ital>section 5, SGSA</ital>).</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="2-507-0628" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Section 13</ital></link> of the SGSA implies a term that services will be provided with reasonable skill and care.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="7-505-7728" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>UCTA</ital></link> permits the exclusion of these terms, subject to the reasonableness test (see <link anchor="a325598" href="9-617-5230" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Limiting liability: statutory and common law controls on limitation clauses: UCTA: statutory implied terms as to quality in supply of goods</ital></link> and <link anchor="a760097" href="9-617-5230" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>UCTA: statutory implied duty of skill and care in supply of services</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier's argument for excluding these provisions and all other implied terms is that the description of the services and the deliverables sets out the full quality requirements to which it is committing. These express commitments should influence whether the exclusion of implied terms is reasonable.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a851883">
              <identifier>8.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Unless a party notifies the other party that it intends to make a claim within the notice period, the other party shall have no liability for that claim. The <defn.term>notice period</defn.term> shall start on the day on which the party wishing to make a claim became[, or ought reasonably to have become,] aware of its having grounds to make a claim and shall expire [NUMBER] months from that date. The notice must be in writing and must identify the grounds for the claim in reasonable detail.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a256496" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>No liability for claims not notified within a specified time (optional clause)</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000038" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The parties may wish to consider agreeing time limits for notifying claims or beginning litigation (reducing the usual six-year statutory limitation period for contract claims). This type of clause is more likely to benefit the supplier, as claims are more likely to be made by the customer.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>In a particularly supplier-friendly agreement, the supplier could rework this clause so that it is just the customer who is barred from bringing claims that are not notified within a specific period, although a mutual clause may be more likely to survive the UCTA reasonableness test.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information, see <link anchor="a910674" href="w-010-2114" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Limitation of liability: Drafting note: No liability for claims not notified within [NUMBER] months (optional clause)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a321263">
            <identifier>9.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Termination</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a397108" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Termination</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000039" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a321263"><ital>clause 9</ital></internal.reference> provides two sets of termination rights:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a195122"><ital>Clause 9.1</ital></internal.reference> provides mutual termination rights for material breach or insolvency-related events. A supplier's right to terminate for a customer's insolvency is severely restricted due to the effects of the <link href="w-026-3565" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Corporate Insolvency and Governance Act 2020</ital></link> (CIGA 2020), which is discussed in <internal.reference refid="a492672"><ital>Drafting note, Termination for customer's insolvency: effects of CIGA 2020</ital></internal.reference>. We have therefore included a clause allowing either party to terminate pre-insolvency where the other party's financial position deteriorates.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a109368"><ital>Clause 9.2</ital></internal.reference> is a one-way termination clause where the supplier can terminate for the customer's failure to make payments within a certain period or for repeated late payment.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This agreement does not include a right to terminate for the change of control of either party. This is on the assumption that it is the customer who is generally more likely to want to use that termination right. If the supplier does want to include a right to terminate on a change of control, see <link anchor="a335832" href="3-107-4673" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Termination: 1.1(q)</ital></link> for drafting.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For information on termination issues and longer form drafting options, see the following standard clauses and their drafting notes:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="3-107-4673" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Termination</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="3-203-1593" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Survival</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a195122">
              <identifier>9.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Without affecting any other right or remedy available to it, either party to the Contract may terminate it with immediate effect by notifying the other party if:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a853026">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party commits a material breach of any term of the Contract which :</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a475582">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>is not capable of remedy; or</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a176286">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>if capable of remedy, is not remedied within a period of [NUMBER] days by the other party after being notified to do so;</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <drafting.note id="a148379" jurisdiction="">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Material breach</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <division id="a000040" level="1">
                      <para>
                        <paratext>For drafting to specify that a breach of certain clauses constitutes a material breach, see <link anchor="a72352" href="3-107-4673" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Termination: clause 1.2</ital></link>. This drafting is more likely to favour the customer and therefore we have not included it in this agreement.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </drafting.note>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a646378">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party takes or has taken against it (other than in relation to a solvent restructuring) any step or action towards its entering bankruptcy, administration, provisional liquidation or any composition or arrangement with its creditors, applying to court for or obtaining a moratorium under Part A1 of the Insolvency Act 1986, being wound up (whether voluntarily or by order of the court), being struck off the register of companies, having a receiver appointed to any of its assets or its entering a procedure in any jurisdiction with a similar effect to a procedure listed in this <internal.reference refid="a646378"><ital>clause 9.1(b)</ital></internal.reference>];</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a240181" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Termination for insolvency</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000041" level="1">
                    <division id="a492672" level="2">
                      <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                        <headtext>Termination for customer's insolvency: effects of CIGA 2020</headtext>
                      </head>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>From 26 June 2020, CIGA 2020 introduced a new <link href="w-026-3710" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 233B</ital></link> to the Insolvency Act 1986 (IA 1986). Broadly, this section makes it difficult or impossible for a supplier to terminate many contracts for the supply of goods or (non-financial) services on the grounds that the customer has entered a formal corporate insolvency procedure. At this point:</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <list type="bulleted">
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext>Termination rights arising before the start of the insolvency period cannot be exercised (<ital>section 233B(4)</ital>).</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext>A termination provision triggered by entry into the insolvency process has no effect (<ital>section 233B(3)</ital>).</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                      </list>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>To terminate the contract unilaterally, a supplier needs one of the following:</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <list type="bulleted">
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext>A new termination right, arising after the start of the insolvency process and not triggered by the process.</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext>Consent from the officer appointed to run the company or the insolvency process, such as an administrator.</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext>Court permission, granted due to the financial hardship caused to the supplier.</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                      </list>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>It is still common to include termination for insolvency clauses in services agreements, partly because customers expect them and are not prevented by CIGA 2020 from using them.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>A supplier affected by these rules should consider including a clause that would allow it to terminate at an early stage in a customer's financial problems (that is, before the customer enters insolvency), see <internal.reference refid="a729100"><ital>clause 9.1(d)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>For a detailed discussion about the effects of CIGA 2020 on termination of contracts, see <link anchor="a317331" href="w-025-9457" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Restrictions on terminating supply contracts in insolvency proceedings: Section 233B: no termination of supplies of goods and services generally</ital></link> and in particular the section entitled <link anchor="co_anchor_a742070" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-025-9457?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Options for a supplier</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                    <division id="a662047" level="2">
                      <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                        <headtext>Shorter form termination for insolvency clause</headtext>
                      </head>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>In <internal.reference refid="a646378"><ital>clause 9.1(b)</ital></internal.reference>, "any step towards a specified insolvency process triggers termination. In a longer form agreement, the parties sometimes specify each step that triggers the termination right to ensure that the right arises at the earliest possible point. Assuming a low commercial risk of insolvency is envisaged, adopting a slightly more ambiguous form of words may be an acceptable trade-off for a more easily digestible contract.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a818174">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party suspends or ceases, or threatens to suspend or cease, carrying on all or a substantial part of its business; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a729100">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party's financial position deteriorates so far as to reasonably justify the opinion that its ability to give effect to the terms of the Contract is in jeopardy.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a148057" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Termination for financial difficulties</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000042" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This clause allows either party to terminate at an early stage in a party's financial problems, before any steps towards an insolvency process or even before any default in performing the contract has occurred. This could be particularly attractive for suppliers, who have very limited abilities to terminate a supply contract when the customer has entered insolvency (see <internal.reference refid="a492672"><ital>Drafting note, Termination for customer's insolvency: effects of CIGA 2020</ital></internal.reference>). For more information about this clause, see <link anchor="a477738" href="3-107-4673" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Termination: Drafting note: Financial difficulties</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a109368">
              <identifier>9.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Without affecting any other right or remedy available to it, the Supplier may terminate the Contract with immediate effect by notifying the Customer if the Customer fails to pay:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a502492">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any amount due under the Contract on the due date for payment and remains in default not less than [NUMBER] days after being notified to make that payment; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a223876">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any amounts due under the Contract by the due date for payment on [NUMBER] or more occasions in any [NUMBER]-month period.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a444405" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Termination for late payment</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000043" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a109368"><ital>clause 9.2</ital></internal.reference> gives the supplier the right to terminate if the customer is:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Late making a payment and fails to fix the issue within a further cure period.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Repeatedly late with making payments, regardless of whether it cures the issue or not.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The customer may argue that the supplier has a right to terminate for material breach and therefore this termination right is not necessary. The supplier usually wants a less ambiguous right to terminate for late payment rather than trying to prove that late payment amounts to a material or repudiatory breach. For more information, see <link anchor="a870980" href="5-559-4767" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: termination: Termination for non-payment</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>If a customer agrees to a right to terminate for late payment, it may want to:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Include an opportunity for the customer to fix the late payments before the termination right applies. We have included this in <internal.reference refid="a502492"><ital>clause 9.2(a)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>State that the right only applies if invoices over a certain amount are overdue.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Make the right mutual. This way, if the supplier owes money to the customer (for example, liquidated damages for delay), the customer can terminate if the supplier is late paying.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a335529">
              <identifier>9.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>On termination of the Contract for whatever reason, the Customer shall immediately pay to the Supplier all of the Supplier's outstanding unpaid invoices and interest and, where no invoice has been submitted for Services supplied, the Supplier may submit an invoice, which shall be payable [immediately on receipt <bold>OR</bold> in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a437190"><ital>clause 7.6</ital></internal.reference>].</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a591010" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Obligations on termination</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000044" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Depending on the services, the customer may require:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Materials returning to the customer. For this drafting, see <link anchor="a201422" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 18.1(b)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Assistance to help the customer transition the services either to a replacement supplier or itself. We have not included transitional assistance in this pro-supplier agreement. For a sample clause, see <link anchor="a587954" href="3-623-0753" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-customer): clause 20.2</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a394303">
              <identifier>9.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Any provision of the Contract that expressly or by implication is intended to come into or continue in force on or after termination of the Contract shall remain in full force and effect.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a725468">
              <identifier>9.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Termination of the Contract shall not affect any of the rights, remedies, obligations or liabilities of the parties that have accrued up to the date of termination, including the right to claim damages in respect of any breach of the Contract which existed at or before the date of termination.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a989592">
            <identifier>10.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>General</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a980587" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>General</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000045" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause sets out essential boilerplate provisions. For additional boilerplate clauses, see <link href="9-107-3656" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Boilerplate agreement</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a119178">
              <identifier>10.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Force majeure</bold>. Neither party shall be liable for any delay or failure in performing any of its obligations for so long as and to the extent that the delay or failure results from events, circumstances or causes beyond its reasonable control.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a953697" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Force majeure</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000046" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Because the supplier is responsible for the bulk of the obligations under the contract, the customer may want to include a provision allowing it to terminate the contract if a force majeure event continues for more than a certain length of time. We have omitted this provision from this agreement because it is pro-supplier.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This short form force majeure clause also does not specify specific events that may amount to force majeure.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information on force majeure clauses, and a longer form clause that includes a detailed list of force majeure events and a termination provision, see <link href="6-107-3808" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Force majeure</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a228377">
              <identifier>10.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Assignment and other dealings</bold>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a319607">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Subject to <internal.reference refid="a500138"><ital>clause 10.2(b)</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a875507"><ital>clause 10.2(c)</ital></internal.reference>, neither party shall <bold>OR</bold> The Customer shall not] assign, novate, transfer, mortgage, charge, subcontract, delegate, declare a trust over or deal in any other manner with any or all of its rights and obligations under the Contract without the prior written consent of the [other party <bold>OR</bold> Supplier] [(consent not to be unreasonably withheld or delayed)].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a500138">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Either party may, after giving prior notice to the other party, assign, novate or transfer any of its rights and obligations under the Contract to:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a255100">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>an Affiliate of that party from time to time; or</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a262808">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any person to which it transfers [its business <bold>OR </bold>that part of its business to which the Contract relates].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a875507">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[The Supplier may subcontract or delegate any or all of its obligations under the Contract to any third party[, provided that it:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 condition="optional" id="a389204">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>notifies the Customer in advance of the subcontracting or delegation;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a955895">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>only subcontracts or delegates obligations to reputable third parties; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a179142">
                  <identifier>(iii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>remains responsible for the performance of the Contract and liable for all acts and omissions of third parties to which it subcontracts or delegates obligations as if they were its own].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>OR</bold></paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Supplier may at any time assign, novate, transfer, mortgage, charge, subcontract, delegate, declare a trust over or deal in any other manner with any or all of its rights and obligations under the Contract[, provided that it gives prior written notice to the Customer].</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a637125" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Assignment and other dealings</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000047" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a228377"><ital>clause 10.2</ital></internal.reference> contains two options for assignment and other dealings:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><bold>Option 1.</bold> Each party needs the other party's consent to assign and deal with this agreement, subject to exceptions. If choosing this option:</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <list type="bulleted">
                          <list.item>
                            <para>
                              <paratext>use the first set of optional wording in each place in <internal.reference refid="a319607"><ital>clause 10.2(a)</ital></internal.reference> and delete the second set;</paratext>
                            </para>
                          </list.item>
                          <list.item>
                            <para>
                              <paratext>consider using the optional exception in <internal.reference refid="a500138"><ital>clause 10.2(b)</ital></internal.reference> for assignment and other dealings with affiliates and in connection with a business sale; and</paratext>
                            </para>
                          </list.item>
                          <list.item>
                            <para>
                              <paratext>use the first option in <internal.reference refid="a875507"><ital>clause 10.2(c)</ital></internal.reference> so that the supplier can subcontract provided it uses reputable subcontractors and remains liable for their performance. Delete the second option in <internal.reference refid="a875507"><ital>clause 10.2(c)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                            </para>
                          </list.item>
                        </list>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><bold>Option 2.</bold> The customer cannot assign or deal with this agreement without the supplier's consent. The supplier is expressly permitted to assign or deal with this agreement. If choosing this option:</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <list type="bulleted">
                          <list.item>
                            <para>
                              <paratext>use the second set of optional wording in each place in <internal.reference refid="a319607"><ital>clause 10.2(a)</ital></internal.reference> and delete the first set; and</paratext>
                            </para>
                          </list.item>
                          <list.item>
                            <para>
                              <paratext>delete <internal.reference refid="a500138"><ital>clause 10.2(b)</ital></internal.reference> and the first option in <internal.reference refid="a875507"><ital>clause 10.2(c)</ital></internal.reference>. Use the second option in <internal.reference refid="a875507"><ital>clause 10.2(c)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                            </para>
                          </list.item>
                        </list>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Option 1 is relatively balanced. Choosing option 1 is likely to be easier to negotiate than option 2 which is more one-sided in the supplier's favour.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>With subcontracting, other options are to:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Ensure that there are no restrictions on subcontracting in the agreement (for example, by removing references to subcontracting or delegation in <internal.reference refid="a319607"><ital>clause 10.2(a)</ital></internal.reference>). This is more likely to benefit the supplier as the party more likely to subcontract.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>State that neither party can subcontract without consent (not to be unreasonably withheld) but to include a list of permitted subcontractors in a schedule to the agreement.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For further information on issues relating to assignment and other dealings, and alternative drafting options, see <link href="5-107-3823" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Assignment and other dealings</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a892805">
              <identifier>10.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Confidentiality.</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a430630">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Each party undertakes that it shall not [at any time <bold>OR</bold> , at any time during the Contract and for a period of [two] years after termination of the Contract,] disclose to any person any Confidential Information of the other party, except as permitted by <internal.reference refid="a991699"><ital>clause 10.3(b)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a991699">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Each party may disclose the other party's Confidential Information:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a369867">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>to [those of] its [and its Affiliates'] employees, officers, representatives, contractors, subcontractors or advisers who need to know that information for the purposes of exercising its rights or carrying out its obligations under the Contract (<defn.term>Representatives</defn.term>). Each party shall ensure that its Representatives comply with confidentiality obligations which are substantially equivalent to those set out in this <internal.reference refid="a892805"><ital>clause 10.3</ital></internal.reference>; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a572958">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>as may be required by law, a court of competent jurisdiction or any governmental or regulatory authority.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a115761">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Neither party may use the other party's Confidential Information for any purpose other than to exercise its rights and perform its obligations under the Contract.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a530324" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Confidentiality</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000048" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on confidentiality clauses and longer form drafting options, see <link href="2-107-3829" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Confidentiality</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For drafting that restricts the customer from sharing supplier confidential information with competitors, see <link anchor="a706219" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 15.3</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a458567">
              <identifier>10.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Entire agreement.</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a480517">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Contract constitutes the entire agreement between the parties and supersedes and extinguishes all previous agreements, promises, assurances and understandings between them, whether written or oral, relating to its subject matter.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a131005">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Each party acknowledges that in entering into the Contract it does not rely on and shall have no remedies in respect of any statement, representation, assurance or warranty (whether made innocently or negligently) that is not set out in the Contract. Each party agrees that it shall have no claim for innocent or negligent misrepresentation [or negligent misstatement] based on any statement in the Contract.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a957090" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Entire agreement</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000049" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on entire agreement clauses and alternative drafting, see <link href="2-107-3834" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Entire agreement</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a124232">
              <identifier>10.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Variation.</bold> No variation of the Contract shall be effective unless it is in writing and signed by the parties (or their authorised representatives).</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a757228" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Variation</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000050" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For information on variation clauses and longer form drafting, see <link href="3-107-3838" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Variation</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a817875">
              <identifier>10.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Waiver. </bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a254611">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A waiver of any right or remedy is only effective if given in writing and shall not be deemed a waiver of any subsequent right or remedy.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a376804">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A delay or failure to exercise, or the single or partial exercise of, any right or remedy does not waive that or any other right or remedy, nor does it prevent or restrict the further exercise of that or any other right or remedy.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a649347" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Waiver</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000051" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on waiver clauses and longer form drafting, see <link href="0-107-3806" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Waiver</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a665484">
              <identifier>10.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Severance.</bold> If any provision or part-provision of the Contract is or becomes invalid, illegal or unenforceable, it shall be deemed deleted, but that shall not affect the validity and enforceability of the rest of the Contract.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a926959" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Severance</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000052" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This short form clause does not include an obligation on the parties to negotiate in good faith to amend the clause to make it enforceable.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For drafting to that effect and information on severance clauses generally, see <link href="9-107-3840" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Severance</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a860784">
              <identifier>10.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Notices.</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a205529">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Any notice given to a party under or in connection with the Contract shall be in writing and shall be:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a901555">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>delivered by hand or by pre-paid first-class post or other next working day delivery service to its address specified in the Contract Details; or</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a541516">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>sent by email to the email address specified in the Contract Details,</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>or to any other address as it may have notified to the other party in accordance with this <internal.reference refid="a860784"><ital>clause 10.8</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a874694">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Any notice shall be deemed to have been received:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a920001">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>if delivered by hand, at the time the notice is left at the proper address;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a426771">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>if sent by [pre-paid first-class post or other] next working day delivery service, at [9.00 am] on the [second] Business Day after posting; or</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a740041">
                  <identifier>(iii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>if sent by email, at the time of transmission, or, if this time falls outside business hours in the place of receipt, when business hours resume. In this <internal.reference refid="a740041"><ital>clause 10.8(b)(iii)</ital></internal.reference>,<ital> </ital>business hours means 9.00am to 5.00pm Monday to Friday on a day that is not a public holiday in the place of receipt.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <drafting.note id="a337572" jurisdiction="">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Notices</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <division id="a000053" level="1">
                      <para>
                        <paratext>For information on notice clauses and longer form drafting, see <link href="5-107-3842" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Notices</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </drafting.note>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a499239">
              <identifier>10.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Third party rights.</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a942665">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Unless it expressly states otherwise,] the Contract does not give rise to any rights under the Contracts (Rights of Third Parties) Act 1999 to enforce any term of the Contract.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a439895">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The rights of the parties to rescind or vary the Contract are not subject to the consent of any other person.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a192161" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Third party rights</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000054" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Use the optional opening words in <internal.reference refid="a942665"><ital>clause 10.9(a)</ital></internal.reference> if a third party is given rights under the <link href="9-505-5610" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Contracts (Rights of Third Parties) Act 1999</ital></link> (CROTPA) to enforce any terms in this agreement. If no third party is meant to benefit from any right or defence in the agreement, delete the optional opening words.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a439895"><ital>Clause 10.9(b)</ital></internal.reference> should only be used if third party rights have been granted. Delete it if all rights under CROTPA have been excluded.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on third party rights clauses, see <link href="6-107-3846" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Third party rights</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a930224">
              <identifier>10.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Governing law. </bold>The Contract, and any dispute or claim (including non-contractual disputes or claims) arising out of or in connection with it or its subject matter or formation, shall be governed by and construed in accordance with the law of England and Wales.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a865366" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Governing law</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000055" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For information on governing law clauses, see <link href="8-107-3850" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Governing law</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a331069">
              <identifier>10.11</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Jurisdiction.</bold> Each party irrevocably agrees that the courts of England and Wales shall have [exclusive <bold>OR</bold> non-exclusive] jurisdiction to settle any dispute or claim (including non-contractual disputes or claims) arising out of or in connection with the Contract or its subject matter or formation.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a113775" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Jurisdiction</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000056" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For information on jurisdiction clauses, see <link href="9-522-6848" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Jurisdiction</ital></link> and its drafting notes.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
        </operative>
        <disclosure.schedule>
          <schedule condition="optional" id="a343828">
            <identifier>Schedule 1</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Services</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a888035" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Services (optional schedule)</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000057" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a343828"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference> can be used to set out the full services specification and full details of any deliverables (as identified in the Contract Details cover sheet). Delete this schedule if the services and deliverables can be set out solely in the cover sheet.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>It is in the interests of the supplier as well as the customer to include a sufficiently detailed and well drafted service description. This will reduce the risk of disputes over what is and is not included in the services. Tips for drafting a service description for the supplier include:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Consider the services to be provided in detail from end to end, step by step. Also consider how the supplier should respond to unusual events which occur periodically (for example, in the context of delivery services, the provision by the customer of an incorrect address).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The supplier's own description of its services, as used in its marketing, may be a good starting point but usually requires some editing to make it clearer and more precise. The supplier should check to ensure that the description of its services does not over-promise and that any deadlines are realistic. The service description should be focused on what the supplier will actually do on a day-to-day basis, rather than the benefits that this will have for the customer (such as anticipated savings).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Obtain input from the individuals involved in the operational aspects of the services so that the drafting reflects the realities of the provision of the services.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Consider the division of responsibilities between the supplier and the customer. Be clear on any areas where the supplier's performance is dependent on something the customer must do first. Specific customer duties should be included where possible so that the supplier can invoke <internal.reference refid="a288262"><ital>clause 4.2</ital></internal.reference> if its performance is delayed by the customer's acts or omissions. For a discussion of how to deal with the customer's responsibilities, see <internal.reference refid="a273888"><ital>Drafting note, Customer's obligations</ital></internal.reference><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Avoid subjective descriptions such as "good" or "satisfactorily" where possible as these may result in disputes as to whether the standard has been met. Instead define the standards by measurable criteria. If it has been agreed that something will be done to the customer's satisfaction, make sure the customer is required to act reasonably.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Avoid leaving matters to be agreed by both parties as this will cause problems if the parties cannot subsequently agree. If something cannot be agreed upfront, try to include a mechanism for working out the relevant issue.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <division id="a118052" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Varying the service description</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>After contract signature, additional services or variations to existing services agreed by the parties should be documented in writing to avoid any future dispute. In this short form agreement, <internal.reference refid="a124232"><ital>clause 10.5</ital></internal.reference> provides that any variations to any part of the agreement must be in writing and signed by both parties. When considering changes to the services, suppliers should consider whether the price needs revising as well. For a formal change control mechanism for agreeing and pricing changes to the services, see <link anchor="a950521" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 9</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <clause id="a378541">
              <identifier>1.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Services</headtext>
              </head>
            </clause>
            <para>
              <paratext>[SERVICES TO BE PROVIDED]</paratext>
            </para>
            <clause id="a295143">
              <identifier>2.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Deliverables</headtext>
              </head>
            </clause>
            <para>
              <paratext>[DELIVERABLES TO BE PROVIDED]</paratext>
            </para>
          </schedule>
          <schedule condition="optional" id="a598248">
            <identifier>Schedule 2</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Charges</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a934537" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Charges (optional schedule)</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000058" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>Specify whether the charges for the services will be fixed price, time and materials, or mixed. See <internal.reference refid="a667957"><ital>Drafting note, Charges and payment</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The sums inserted for the charges should be exclusive of VAT.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a265374"><ital>Clause 7.4</ital></internal.reference> provides different drafting options for the invoicing schedule or, alternatively, allows the details to be set out in this <internal.reference refid="a598248"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Delete this schedule if the charges can be set out solely in the Contract Details cover sheet and the invoicing arrangement are described in <internal.reference refid="a265374"><ital>clause 7.4</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <clause id="a301750">
              <identifier>1.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Charges</headtext>
              </head>
              <subclause1 id="a618473">
                <identifier>1.1</identifier>
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Fixed price</headtext>
                </head>
                <subclause2 id="a168386">
                  <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The total charges for the [Services <bold>OR</bold> [PART OF THE SERVICES CHARGED ON A FIXED PRICE BASIS]] are [AMOUNT].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a562378">
                  <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The[se] charges are calculated as follows: [CALCULATION METHOD].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a682261">
                <identifier>1.2</identifier>
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Time and materials</headtext>
                </head>
                <subclause2 id="a100488">
                  <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The [Services <bold>OR</bold> [RELEVANT PART OF THE SERVICES]] shall be charged on a time and materials basis as follows:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <subclause3 id="a886002">
                    <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The [daily <bold>OR</bold> hourly] rates for the Supplier are: [SPECIFY].</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </subclause3>
                  <subclause3 id="a281527">
                    <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The weekend and overtime rates for work outside normal business hours are: [SPECIFY].</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </subclause3>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a723718">
                  <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The Supplier's normal business hours are [9.00] am to [5.00] pm on a Business Day.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a128936">
                  <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The Supplier's daily rates are calculated on the basis of an [eight]-hour day worked during normal business hours. The Supplier may charge on a pro rata basis for part days worked during normal business hours.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
              </subclause1>
            </clause>
            <clause id="a507501">
              <identifier>2.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Invoicing schedule</headtext>
              </head>
              <subclause1 id="a531595">
                <identifier>2.1</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Supplier shall invoice the Customer for the Charges on the following schedule: [SPECIFY].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
            </clause>
          </schedule>
          <schedule condition="optional" id="a381794">
            <identifier>Schedule 3</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Policies</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a889113" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Policies (optional schedule)</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000059" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For the background to this schedule, see <internal.reference refid="a113535"><ital>Drafting note, Document structure</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a325889"><ital>Drafting note, Policies (optional definition)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>If there are no business polices that the supplier must adhere to, delete this schedule and the references in the main body of the agreement to "Policies".</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <para>
              <paratext>[LIST [AND INSERT COPIES OF OR LINKS TO] THE POLICIES].</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Policies are:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Code of Conduct].</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Modern Slavery and Human Trafficking Policy].</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Environmental, Social and Governance Policy].</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Ethics and Anti-bribery Policy].</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </schedule>
          <schedule condition="optional" id="a217005">
            <identifier>Schedule 4</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Data protection</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a449865" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Data protection (optional schedule)</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000060" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For the background to this <internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>, see <internal.reference refid="a773794"><ital>Drafting note, Data protection (optional clause)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <clause id="a246187">
              <identifier>1.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Definitions</headtext>
              </head>
              <subclause1 id="a375718">
                <identifier>1.1</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><defn.term>Applicable Data Protection Laws</defn.term>: all Applicable Laws relating to the protection of personal data and the privacy of individuals, including the UK GDPR, the Data Protection Act 2018 and the Privacy and Electronic Communications Regulations 2003 (<ital>SI 2003/2426</ital>).</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a292752">
                <identifier>1.2</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Commissioner, controller, data subject, personal data, personal data breach, processor </bold>and<bold> processing</bold>: as defined in Applicable Data Protection Law.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a959327">
                <identifier>1.3</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><defn.term>Customer Personal Data</defn.term>: any personal data which the Supplier processes in connection with the Contract on behalf of the Customer in the capacity of a processor.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a203383">
                <identifier>1.4</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><defn.term>Shared Personal Data</defn.term>: any personal data which the Supplier receives from the Customer, or otherwise collects, in connection with the Contract and processes in the capacity of a controller.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a477532">
                <identifier>1.5</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><defn.term>UK GDPR</defn.term>: has the meaning given in section 3(10) (as supplemented by section 205(4)) of the Data Protection Act 2018.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
            </clause>
            <clause id="a343062">
              <identifier>2.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Terms</headtext>
              </head>
              <subclause1 id="a229764">
                <identifier>2.1</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Each party shall comply with all Applicable Data Protection Laws in its processing of personal data under or in connection with the Contract. This <internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference> is in addition to, and does not relieve, remove or replace, a party's obligations or rights under Applicable Data Protection Laws.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a891861">
                <identifier>2.2</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Without prejudice to <internal.reference refid="a229764"><ital>paragraph 2.1</ital></internal.reference>, the Customer shall ensure that it has all necessary consents and notices in place to enable the Shared Personal Data and Customer Personal Data to be lawfully transferred to or collected by the Supplier[, and further processed by the Supplier,] in connection with the performance of the Contract.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a586805">
                <identifier>2.3</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Supplier and Customer shall act as independent controllers in respect of the following personal data and processing activities:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause2 id="a240836">
                  <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The names and contact details of staff which are shared by the parties and processed for the purposes of contract management and maintaining a business relationship between them.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a132975">
                  <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>[OTHER].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a805943">
                <identifier>2.4</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>In relation to the Customer Personal Data, the scope, nature, purpose and duration of processing by the Supplier and the types of personal data and categories of data subject are as follows:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause2 id="a647432">
                  <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Scope:</bold> [SUBJECT MATTER OF THE PROCESSING. FOR EXAMPLE, NAME OF THE SPECIFIC SERVICE THAT INVOLVES PROCESSING.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a648417">
                  <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Nature:</bold> [DESCRIPTION OF THE TYPE OF PROCESSING, FOR EXAMPLE, DATA COLLECTION, STORAGE, SHARING AND SO ON.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a476496">
                  <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Purpose of processing:</bold> [DESCRPTION OF THE PURPOSES OF THE PROCESSING. FOR EXAMPLE, RECRUITMENT, DIRECT MARKETING AND SO ON.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a574504">
                  <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Duration of processing:</bold> [PERIODS FOR WHICH THE DATA WILL BE PROCESSED. THIS IS LIKELY TO BE THE DURATION OF THE SERVICES.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a967016">
                  <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Types of personal data:</bold> [TYPES OF PERSONAL DATA TO BE PROCESSED SUCH AS NAMES, CONTACT DETAILS AND SO ON.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a339765">
                  <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Categories of data subject:</bold> [FOR EXAMPLE, EMPLOYEES, CUSTOMERS AND SO ON.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a356220">
                <identifier>2.5</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Without prejudice to <internal.reference refid="a229764"><ital>paragraph 2.1</ital></internal.reference>, the Supplier shall, in relation to Customer Personal Data:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause2 id="a851615">
                  <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>process that Customer Personal Data only on the documented instructions of the Customer, which are set out in [<internal.reference refid="a805943"><ital>paragraph 2.4</ital></internal.reference> <bold>OR</bold> [DOCUMENT]] (<bold>Purpose</bold>), unless the Supplier is required by Applicable Laws to otherwise process that Customer Personal Data. Where the Supplier is relying on Applicable Laws as the basis for processing Customer Personal Data, the Supplier shall notify the Customer of this before performing the processing unless prohibited from doing so by those Applicable Laws. [If the Supplier believes that any instruction received from the Customer is likely to infringe Applicable Data Protection Laws, the Supplier shall inform the Customer and may suspend the provision of the Services until the parties have agreed revised instructions which are not infringing];</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a864391">
                  <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>ensure that it has in place appropriate technical and organisational measures to protect against unauthorised or unlawful processing of Customer Personal Data and against accidental loss or destruction of, or damage to, Customer Personal Data[. The Customer acknowledges that it has reviewed the technical and organisational measures set out in [DOCUMENT] and confirms they are appropriate to the harm that might result from the unauthorised or unlawful processing or accidental loss or destruction of, or damage to, the Customer Personal Data, taking into account the state of the art, the costs of implementation and the nature, scope, context and purposes of the processing of Customer Personal Data as well as the risks to individuals];</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a157780">
                  <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>ensure that any personnel engaged and authorised by the Supplier to process Customer Personal Data are obliged to keep that personal data confidential;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a337083">
                  <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>assist the Customer insofar as this is possible (taking into account the nature of the processing and the information available to the Supplier), and at the Customer's cost and written request, in responding to any request from a data subject and in ensuring the Customer's compliance with its obligations under Applicable Data Protection Laws with respect to security, breach notifications, impact assessments and consultations with the Commissioner or other regulators;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a613235">
                  <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>notify the Customer without undue delay on becoming aware of a personal data breach;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a761138">
                  <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>at the written direction of the Customer, delete or return to the Customer all Customer Personal Data on termination of the Contract unless the Supplier is required by Applicable Law to continue to process that Customer Personal Data. For the purposes of this <internal.reference refid="a761138"><ital>paragraph 2.5(f)</ital></internal.reference>, Customer Personal Data shall be considered deleted where it is put beyond further use by the Supplier; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a716175">
                  <identifier>(g)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>make available information to the Customer to demonstrate its compliance with this <internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>, and allow for audits by the Customer (or its designated professional auditors) for this purpose on [reasonable <bold>OR</bold> not less than [14] days'] notice[, provided that the Supplier is not obliged to allow more than one audit in any Contract Year or make available any information that concerns any other customer of the Supplier [(or any of its Affiliates)] or could compromise the security of the Supplier's systems or cause it to breach any legal obligation. The Supplier is not obliged to grant access to any third party auditor until that auditor signs a confidentiality agreement with the Supplier on terms reasonably satisfactory to the Supplier].</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <drafting.note id="a163224" jurisdiction="">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Audits</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <division id="a000061" level="1">
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The UK GDPR requires the processor to allow for and contribute to audits by the controller or an auditor mandated by the controller. The optional wording in this <internal.reference refid="a716175"><ital>paragraph 2.5(g)</ital></internal.reference> puts some parameters around the frequency of audits and the information that can be viewed.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </drafting.note>
                </subclause2>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a522723">
                <identifier>2.6</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Customer provides its prior, general authorisation for the Supplier to:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause2 id="a433770">
                  <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>appoint processors to process the Customer Personal Data, provided that the Supplier:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <subclause3 id="a339819">
                    <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>ensures that the terms on which it appoints any processor comply with Applicable Data Protection Laws, and are consistent with the obligations imposed on the Supplier in this <internal.reference refid="a217005"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </subclause3>
                  <subclause3 id="a224661">
                    <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>remains responsible for the acts and omissions of any processor as if they were the acts and omissions of the Supplier; and</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </subclause3>
                  <subclause3 id="a226823">
                    <identifier>(iii)</identifier>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>informs the Customer of any intended changes concerning the addition or replacement of processors after the Effective Date, giving the Customer the opportunity to object to changes provided that if the Customer objects to a change and cannot demonstrate, to the Supplier's reasonable satisfaction, that the objection is due to an actual or likely breach of Applicable Data Protection Law, the Customer shall indemnify the Supplier for any Losses incurred by the Supplier in accommodating the objection.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </subclause3>
                </subclause2>
                <subclause2 id="a538170">
                  <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>transfer Customer Personal Data outside of the UK as required for the Purpose, provided that the Supplier shall ensure that all transfers are effected in accordance with Applicable Data Protection Laws. For these purposes, the Customer shall promptly comply with any reasonable request of the Supplier, including any request to enter into standard data protection clauses adopted by the Commissioner (where the UK GDPR applies to the transfer) or any other applicable data protection regulator.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause2>
              </subclause1>
              <subclause1 id="a641690">
                <identifier>2.7</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The processors engaged by the Supplier at the Effective Date are [[DETAILS] <bold>OR</bold> set out at [LINK]].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
            </clause>
          </schedule>
        </disclosure.schedule>
      </body>
      <rev.history>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>General update (May 2025)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20250430</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law Commercial</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000001" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have significantly updated this agreement to reflect changes to Practical Law boilerplate terms and to provide additional drafting, such as personal data processing terms.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
      </rev.history>
    </standard.doc>
  </n-docbody>
</n-document>