<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><n-document xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" guid="0" synced="true" validated="true">
  <n-docbody>
    <standard.doc precedenttype="agreement">
      <prelim>
        <product.name>product.name0</product.name>
        <title>Hardware maintenance agreement</title>
        <author><link href="https://www.pinsentmasons.com/people/edwin-baker" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Edwin Baker</ital></link> and Stephen Reeves, Pinsent Masons</author>
        <resource.type>Standard documents</resource.type>
        <juris>juris0</juris>
        <juris>juris1</juris>
      </prelim>
      <abstract>
        <para>
          <paratext>An agreement drafted from the supplier’s point of view, in which the supplier agrees to provide support and maintenance for certain hardware supplied by the supplier.</paratext>
        </para>
      </abstract>
      <toc.identifier hasToc="true"/>
      <body>
        <drafting.note id="a771242" jurisdiction="">
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>About this document</headtext>
          </head>
          <division id="a000009" level="1">
            <para>
              <paratext>An agreement drafted from the Supplier’s point of view, in which the Supplier agrees to provide support and maintenance for certain hardware supplied by the Supplier. Although primarily a hardware maintenance agreement, the agreement also covers updates to software where these are provided with the hardware, see <internal.reference refid="a772513"><ital>Drafting note, Software maintenance services (optional)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
            </para>
            <division id="a848370" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Assumptions</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>It is assumed for the purpose of this standard document that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier and the customer are UK limited companies, and the customer is a business user.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The agreement has been drafted in consideration of, and is subject to, English law.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Any goods or services to be provided under the agreement, are to be provided in the UK exclusively. (If goods or services are to be provided in jurisdictions outside the UK, the laws of those jurisdictions will need to be considered, separately, by each party).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>No specific cybersecurity standards apply to the parties, or to any goods or services that are to be provided under this agreement, under English law (or the law of any other jurisdiction). For more information, see <internal.reference refid="a779169"><ital>Drafting note, Cybersecurity</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
            </division>
            <division id="a779169" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Cybersecurity</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>Cybersecurity obligations are becoming more prominent in IT agreements, including as statutory controls and obligations in relation to network and information system, and data, security are increasing, see:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="9-617-7682" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity: overview (UK)</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="5-616-1485" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, UK cybersecurity law</ital></link>:</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>Specific UK cybersecurity legal standards may apply in particular circumstances, including in relation to:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Certain regulated activities and sectors, see <link href="2-616-1566" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity in regulated sectors, cybersecurity guidance and standards</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Certain operators of essential services and relevant digital service providers, see <internal.reference refid="a480584"><ital>Drafting note, Operators of essential services and relevant digital service providers</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Certain consumer connectable products, see <internal.reference refid="a356861"><ital>Drafting note, Consumer connectable products</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Personal data, see <internal.reference refid="a549452"><ital>Drafting note, Data protection</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>Cyber laws in other jurisdictions may also apply extraterritorially to organisations in the UK, depending on where goods and services are being provided. By way of example, see <link href="7-628-0350" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, EU cybersecurity framework</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement is drafted on the assumption that no specific cybersecurity laws or legal standards apply to the parties, or to the goods or services which are the subject matter of this agreement, in the UK or elsewhere, see <internal.reference refid="a848370"><ital>Drafting note, Assumptions</ital></internal.reference>. If they do, then this may necessitate the inclusion of certain provisions into the agreement, or the party subject to the requirements may wish to flow them down to their counterparty.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>To determine whether a legal requirement applies, a cybersecurity risk assessment may be necessary or helpful. For more information on conducting cybersecurity risk assessments, see <link href="w-034-5348" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity risk assessments and reporting (UK)</ital></link><ital>. </ital>For more information about managing cyber risk in an organisation's supply chain, see <link href="w-038-4171" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Managing cybersecurity risk in supplier relationships (UK)</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <division id="a480584" level="3">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Operators of essential services and relevant digital service providers</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The <link href="w-014-4419" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Network and Information Systems Regulations 2018 (SI 2018/506)</ital></link> (NIS Regulations) which came into effect on 10 May 2018 pursuant to the <link href="w-010-2436" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Cybersecurity Directive ((EU) 2016/1148)</ital></link> (also known as the NIS Directive). They have potential impact on:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Any operator of essential services (OES) that relies on IT systems in the following sectors: energy, transport, health, drinking water supply and distribution, digital infrastructure.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Relevant providers of online marketplaces, online search engines and cloud computing services (Relevant Digital Service Providers (RDSPs)).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Like the <link href="6-631-1875" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>General Data Protection Regulation ((EU) 2016/679) (GDPR)</ital></link>, the NIS Regulations impose security and incident reporting requirements and provide for high penalties (up to £17 million in the case of the NIS Regulations), but their focus is on security of IT systems, rather than security of the personal data processed by those systems; in practice the two regimes are inextricably linked.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The banking and financial market infrastructures sectors were omitted from the NIS Regulations although they fall within the Cybersecurity Directive. The UK government stated in its consultation on implementation of the Directive that competent authorities for these sectors would not be identified. Firms and financial market infrastructure within these sectors must continue to adhere to requirements and standards as set by the Bank of England and/or the Financial Conduct Authority.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For a definition of an OES see <link anchor="a873370" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity Directive: UK implementation: Identification or Designation as an OES</ital></link>, and for a definition of an RDSP see <link anchor="a375008" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity Directive: UK implementation: Identification as an RDSP</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>OESs and RDSPs have obligations to maintain the security of the systems on which their services rely and to report security incidents to their respective regulators (the Information Commissioner's Office (ICO) is the regulator for RDSPs and Schedule 1 of the NIS Regulations lists the regulators for OESs).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This agreement is drafted on the assumption that the NIS Regulations do not apply (either directly or indirectly). Where the NIS Regulations apply to the Customer, it will need to consider whether the obligations placed on the Supplier with regard to maintenance of the Customer's hardware (and associated software) are sufficient to meet any enhanced cybersecurity requirements under the NIS Regulations. The National Cyber Security Centre has published <link href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/nis-guidance-collection" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>guidance</ital></link> for OESs which includes advice on how to pass obligations up the supply chain and what considerations should be made in different circumstances.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Customer should also refer to any specific guidance issued by the regulator for their specific OES sector (or by the ICO for RDSPs) and any applicable guidance for the banking and financial market infrastructures sectors, see <link href="2-616-1566" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity in regulated sectors, cybersecurity guidance and standards</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Hardware maintenance can be a key way of protecting the Customer's system from cybersecurity threats, and so (whether the NIS Regulations apply or not) the Customer may wish to place the Supplier under a specific obligation to maintain the security of any software which runs on the hardware, as well as its functional operation, see <internal.reference refid="a772513"><ital>Drafting note, Software maintenance services (optional)</ital></internal.reference><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>In addition, during hardware maintenance the Customer and Supplier systems may interface with each other, and so the Customer may want to impose an additional obligation on the Supplier not to introduce vulnerabilities into the Customer's network and information systems. As drafted, <internal.reference refid="a894269"><ital>clause 8.1(d)</ital></internal.reference><ital> </ital>currently only covers viruses.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For an example of additional cybersecurity requirements that could be included here (albeit in the context of software, rather than hardware, maintenance) see <link anchor="a669850" href="7-107-4807" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Software maintenance agreement (pro-customer): Security of network and information systems</ital></link>. Please note these requirements are general in nature and not aligned to any sectoral requirements, so if the NIS Regulations do apply, you should always consult the specific guidance that applies for your sector.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a356861" level="3">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Consumer connectable products</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Manufacturers, distributors and importers of certain consumer connectable in the UK (such as certain, qualifying smart products, like smart TVs, smart speakers, connected baby monitors and connected alarm systems) are subject to minimum cybersecurity requirements under Part 1 of the <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-037-9685?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=PLDocumentLink&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)&amp;amp;ppcid=6f09838bcf6542b0be5d3ff1bc314681" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Product Security and Telecommunications Infrastructure Act 2022</ital></link> (PSTIA). A party who is subject to these requirements might seek to include specific clauses in its maintenance arrangements with third parties to ensure that the cybersecurity of such products are preserved.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on the requirements of the PSTIA, see <link href="w-039-2845" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity requirements for consumer connectable products under Part 1 of Product Security and Telecommunications Infrastructure Act 2022 (UK)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </division>
            <division id="a549452" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Data protection</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>Where <link href="8-200-3413" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>personal data</ital></link> will be processed under this agreement, the parties will need to consider the impact of any applicable data protection legislation and, where appropriate, suitable data protection clauses will need to be inserted at <internal.reference refid="a74840"><ital>clause 12</ital></internal.reference>, or, alternatively, a data protection schedule will need to be annexed to this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>The clauses which are appropriate to include, in each case, will depend upon the relationship of the parties, the context of the processing, and the capacity in which each party processes the personal data.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For some specimen personal data processing clauses designed for use in an IT agreement, see:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="w-027-4499" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Personal data processing clauses for IT agreements (UK) (pro-customer version)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="w-026-6854" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Personal data processing clauses for IT agreements (UK) (pro-supplier version)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each set of clauses provide alternative options to cater for different processing scenarios.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For a note setting out the key issues to address when considering the impact of the UK and EU data protection legislation on rights and obligations commonly found in IT contracts, see <link href="w-027-2423" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Data protection issues in IT contracts</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
            <division id="a443853" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Supply chain issues: slavery and human trafficking</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The <link href="2-607-4606" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Modern Slavery Act 2015</ital></link> (MSA) is aimed at combating crimes of slavery and human trafficking. <link href="7-608-3825" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Section 54</ital></link> of the MSA requires commercial organisations having a global turnover of £36 million or more to publish an annual slavery and human trafficking statement for each financial year that ends on or after 31 March 2016. The statement must disclose what steps the organisation has taken to ensure that human trafficking is not taking place in any of its supply chains or its business; or state that it has taken no such steps. Including anti-slavery and trafficking obligations in its contracts (through business policies or otherwise) is one of the steps an organisation can take.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier should note that the Customer may want to include wording in its supply agreements that have a connection with a supply chain to prohibit the use of forced or trafficked labour. For example, by stating that the Supplier will comply with the Customer's policy on slavery (and possibly its other business policies too such as anti-bribery and corruption and data protection and security). But depending on the bargaining strengths of the parties, the Supplier may require the Customer to comply with the Supplier's business policies for reputational reasons, for example. The outcome of such negotiations would ultimately depend on the parties and how keen each of them wants to do the transaction.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For further information on the MSA including links to example clauses, see <link href="8-618-8657" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Modern Slavery Act 2015 toolkit</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </division>
          <division id="a425309" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Drafting for Brexit</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>On 31 January 2020 (<link href="w-015-8342" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>exit day</ital></link>), the UK left the EU and the UK-EU withdrawal agreement entered into force. Following the end of the <link href="w-023-9796" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><bold><ital>UK-EU transition period</ital></bold></link> at 11.00 pm UK time on 31 December 2020, <link href="w-019-6282" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><bold><ital>retained EU law</ital></bold></link> was created, the remaining withdrawal agreement provisions came into operation, and the <link href="w-029-0843" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><bold><ital>future relationship agreements</ital></bold></link> (including the UK-EU trade and co-operation agreement) started to apply on a provisional basis, eventually entering into force at 11.00 pm (UK time) on 30 April 2021. This resource has been reviewed and reflects the position from the end of the transition period.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>For general information on the withdrawal agreement, future relationship agreements, and the operation of UK law following the end of the transition period, see <link href="w-013-0603" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>UK legal change post-transition and UK-EU agreements toolkit</ital></link> and Practical Law’s <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/Browse/Home/Resources/Brexit" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Brexit page</ital></link>.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>For more information on the impact of Brexit on the specific practice areas covered by this resource, see:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-017-3813?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Brexit: implications for intellectual property rights</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link anchor="co_anchor_a871801" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/3-107-3683?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Overview: UK competition law: Brexit and competition law</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-016-7309?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Brexit: implications for data protection</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
            <para>
              <paratext>See also <link anchor="co_anchor_a470016" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-014-0890?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Impact of the General Data Protection Regulation on intellectual property licence-related obligations: General points</ital></link>.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>For guidance on the issues to consider when assessing the possible impact of Brexit when drafting an agreement, see <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-005-3555?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Drafting for Brexit: Brexit clauses</ital></link>, which includes specimen Brexit clauses.</paratext>
            </para>
          </division>
        </drafting.note>
        <cover.sheet>
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>Hardware maintenance agreement</headtext>
          </head>
          <party.name>Supplier</party.name>
          <AdditionalPartyType>
            <static.and>and</static.and>
            <party.name>Customer</party.name>
          </AdditionalPartyType>
        </cover.sheet>
        <intro default="true">
          <intro.date>This agreement is dated [DATE]</intro.date>
        </intro>
        <parties>
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>PARTIES</headtext>
          </head>
          <party executionmethod="contract" id="a854806" status="individual">
            <identifier>(1)</identifier>
            <defn.item>
              <defn>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[FULL COMPANY NAME] incorporated and registered in England and Wales with company number [NUMBER] whose registered office is at [REGISTERED OFFICE ADDRESS]</paratext>
                </para>
              </defn>
              <defn.term>Supplier</defn.term>
            </defn.item>
          </party>
          <party executionmethod="contract" id="a104081" status="individual">
            <identifier>(2)</identifier>
            <defn.item>
              <defn>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[FULL COMPANY NAME] incorporated and registered in England and Wales with company number [NUMBER] whose registered office is at [REGISTERED OFFICE ADDRESS]</paratext>
                </para>
              </defn>
              <defn.term>Customer</defn.term>
            </defn.item>
          </party>
        </parties>
        <recitals>
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>BACKGROUND</headtext>
          </head>
          <clause id="a769643">
            <identifier>(A)</identifier>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Supplier has supplied certain hardware products to the Customer and has agreed to provide support and maintenance for this hardware on the terms set out in this agreement.</paratext>
            </para>
          </clause>
        </recitals>
        <operative xrefname="clause">
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>Agreed terms</headtext>
          </head>
          <clause id="a199583">
            <identifier>1.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Interpretation</headtext>
            </head>
            <subclause1 id="a778201">
              <identifier>1.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The definitions and rules of interpretation in this clause apply in this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
              <defn.item id="a306032">
                <defn.term>Additional Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any Emergency Maintenance or Excluded Maintenance performed by the Supplier under this agreement.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a902997">
                <defn.term>Additional Services Fees</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the fees payable in consideration of the provision of any Additional Services, which shall be calculated at the Additional Services Rates.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a279158">
                <defn.term>Additional Services Rates</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the rates set out in <internal.reference refid="a439776"><ital>Part 5</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>, as those rates are amended from time to time in accordance with the terms of this agreement.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a568336">
                <defn.term>Business Day</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>a day other than a Saturday, Sunday or public holiday in England when banks in [London] are open for business.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a327740">
                <defn.term>Charges</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Maintenance Fees and the Additional Services Fees together.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a232481">
                <defn.term>Commencement Date</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the date specified in <internal.reference refid="a602587"><ital>Part 1</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a176442">
                <defn.term>Confidential Information</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>has the meaning given in <internal.reference refid="a959936"><ital>clause 10.1</ital></internal.reference> (Confidentiality).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a840208">
                <defn.term>Corrective Maintenance</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a672503"><ital>clause 2.3</ital></internal.reference>:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>making any adjustments to the Maintained Equipment; and</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>replacing any parts or components of the Maintained Equipment,</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in each case, which are required to restore the Maintained Equipment to Good Working Order.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a106036">
                <defn.term>EULA</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the end user licence agreement[s] set out in <internal.reference refid="a251354"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a959570">
                <defn.term>Excluded Causes</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext/>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>[a defect in the manufacturer's design of the Maintained Equipment;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>faulty materials or workmanship in the manufacture of the Maintained Equipment;]</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>use of the Maintained Equipment with computer equipment or materials not supplied or approved in writing by the Supplier;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>any maintenance, alteration, modification or adjustment performed by persons other than the Supplier or its employees or agents [unless approved by the Supplier in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a252658"><ital>clause 5(f)</ital></internal.reference>];</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>the Customer or a third party moving the Maintained Equipment;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>the use of the Maintained Equipment in breach of any of the provisions of the agreement under which the Maintained Equipment was supplied;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>a failure, interruption or surge in the electrical power or its related infrastructure connected to the Maintained Equipment;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>a failure or malfunction in the air conditioning or other environmental controls required for the normal operation of the Maintained Equipment, or an error or omission in the correct use of that air conditioning or other environmental controls by the Customer;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>the neglect or misuse of the Maintained Equipment; or</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>use of Unsupported Software.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a135891" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Design defects in the Maintained Equipment (optional)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000010" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>It should be considered whether parts (a) and (b) are appropriate in the circumstances, particularly where the Supplier is also the manufacturer of the Maintained Equipment, or where the Customer simply wants the hardware fixed, as part of the standard maintenance fees, notwithstanding that the error may be a result of an original design defect. The Customer may want the Supplier to address any defect that is detected, subject to it being compensated for the price of any spare parts in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a628498"><ital>clause 4.1</ital></internal.reference>. The Supplier may very well resist this, however.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a917559">
                <defn.term>Excluded Maintenance</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any maintenance services required to restore any malfunctioning or failed Maintained Equipment [or Supported Software] to Good Working Order where the malfunction or failure results from or is caused by any of the Excluded Causes.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a791944">
                <defn.term>Emergency Maintenance</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext/>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>making any adjustments to the Maintained Equipment; and</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>replacing any parts or components of the Maintained Equipment, in each case, which are required to restore the Maintained Equipment to Good Working Order.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a997173">
                <defn.term>Fix Time</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the applicable fix times as set out in <internal.reference refid="a1015113"><ital>Part 2</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a741444"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a240524">
                <defn.term>Good Industry Practice</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in relation to any undertaking and any circumstances, the exercise of skill, diligence, prudence, foresight and judgement and the making of any expenditure that would reasonably be expected from a skilled person engaged in the same type of undertaking under the same or similar circumstances.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a247922">
                <defn.term>Good Working Order</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Maintained Equipment operates in accordance with the Operating Manuals.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a494090">
                <defn.term>Initial Period</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>a period of [12] months commencing on the Commencement Date.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a537548">
                <defn.term>Location</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the location of the Maintained Equipment as specified in <internal.reference refid="a239422"><ital>Part 3</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>, or any other location as may be agreed by the parties in writing from time to time.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a986143" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Location</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000011" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>A key concept within any hardware maintenance contract, is the location where the Supplier needs to attend to perform the Maintenance Services. This may be as simple as a certain specified address. However in more complex arrangements, such as Edge Computing deployments (see <link anchor="a850791" href="4-619-6070" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Demystifying IT for lawyers: The cloud</ital></link>), the Maintained Equipment may be spread across a number of locations, and potentially some difficult to access locations. Consideration should be given to whether the provisions referencing Location and associated response times are appropriate for these Locations.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a771758">
                <defn.term>Maintained Equipment</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the equipment specified <internal.reference refid="a784170"><ital>Part 2</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a791828">
                <defn.term>Maintenance Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Preventative Maintenance, Corrective Maintenance and Emergency Maintenance of the Maintained Equipment [together with the Software Maintenance Services].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a240959" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Maintenance services</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000012" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>If the scope of the maintenance services will also cover supporting any software that is installed on the maintained equipment than the optional wording should also be included, see <internal.reference refid="a772513"><ital>Drafting note, Software maintenance services (optional)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a786263">
                <defn.term>Mandatory Policies</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the [Customer's <bold>OR</bold> Supplier's] business policies [and codes] [attached <bold>OR</bold> listed] in <internal.reference refid="a985480"><ital>Schedule 3</ital></internal.reference>, as amended by notification to the [Supplier <bold>OR</bold> Customer] from time to time.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a379762" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Mandatory Policies (optional)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000013" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This definition relates to the optional compliance requirement at <internal.reference refid="a305119"><ital>clause 10.10</ital></internal.reference>.which offers two drafting options. The first is a requirement on the Customer to comply with the Supplier's policies, and the second is a requirement on the Supplier to comply with the Customer's policies. Ensure that this definition is consistent with the approach taken in <internal.reference refid="a305119"><ital>clause 10.10</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>See further the integrated drafting notes at <internal.reference refid="a927892"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference> and also <link href="8-618-8657" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Drafting note, Supply chain issues: slavery and human trafficking</ital></link> above.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a278488">
                <defn.term>Normal Business Hours</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>[8.30] am to [6.00] pm GMT on a Business Day.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a963963">
                <defn.term>Operating Manuals</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all operating manuals and specifications relating to the Maintained Equipment which are provided to the Customer by the Supplier.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a462003">
                <defn.term>Preventative Maintenance</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>means:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>testing that the Maintained Equipment is functional; and</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>making any adjustments as may be required to ensure the Maintained Equipment remains in Good Working Order,</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a473603"><ital>clause 2.2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a844700">
                <defn.term>Renewal Period</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>each successive 12-month period after the Initial Period for which this agreement is renewed.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a580568">
                <defn.term>Representatives</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>has the meaning given to it in <internal.reference refid="a959936"><ital>clause 10.1</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a920929">
                <defn.term>Response Time</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the applicable response times as set out in <internal.reference refid="a858939"><ital>Part 1</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a741444"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a152439">
                <defn.term>Service Credits</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the service credits specified in <internal.reference refid="a421005"><ital>Part 4</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a741444"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a156249">
                <defn.term>Service Levels</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the levels to which the Supplier must perform the Maintenance Services, as set out in <internal.reference refid="a812168"><ital>Part 3</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a741444"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a515718">
                <defn.term>Software</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any software which is made available by Supplier to Customer, including the firmware installed on the Hardware, ]and any updates to such software provided from time to time.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a311188">
                <defn.term>Software Maintenance Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the software maintenance services to be provided by the Supplier in respect of the Supported Software as set out in <internal.reference refid="a462774"><ital>Part 6</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a772513" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Software maintenance services (optional)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000014" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>It is becoming increasing likely that hardware will come with some form of software (including certain pre-installed software (often referred to as firmware)).</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The support offered for software will depend on the hardware being maintained, whether the Supplier is the manufacturer of the hardware, and the other support obligations.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Manufacturers will generally provide patches (minor updates to fix bugs) for free and may provider other major updates for free or for a fee. There may also be urgent security patches where a critical vulnerability is identified.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Software within hardware will often not be supported forever, but will come with an advertised shelf life, or will be maintained subject to an “end of life” notice being provided by the manufacturer.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The availability of patches or updates without charge does not mean the Supplier will install them for free. So, in the context of this agreement, the parties should consider who is responsible for all activities to do with the maintenance and support of the software and the commercial impact of those being provided, including the following:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Support services (support desk, response and resolution).</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Monitoring the availability of patches, updates and security issues;</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Notifying the other party of the availability of patches, updates and security issues;</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Applying and installing patches and updates from time to time; and</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Applying and installing urgent security patches from time to time.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>If the Supplier is to take on any of these tasks, then the definition of "software maintenance services" should be retained, and the scope, and detail, of the services should be set out in <internal.reference refid="a462774"><ital>Part 6</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>If the Customer retains any of these responsibilities but fails, then consider if that should be an excluded cause (see <internal.reference refid="a959570"><ital>Excluded Causes</ital></internal.reference>) or otherwise limit Supplier’s liability (for example if any form of hardware warranty is provided, would that be subject to damage caused by a failure to patch (for example due to overheating).</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>If the hardware does not contain any software then all references to software, and software maintenance services, in this agreement can be removed.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For example software maintenance agreements, see <link href="7-107-4807" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Software maintenance agreement (pro-customer)</ital></link> and <link href="1-107-4810" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Software maintenance agreement (pro-supplier)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a888227">
                <defn.term>Standard Maintenance Fees</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the fees set out in <internal.reference refid="a873665"><ital>Part 4</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>, as these fees are varied from time to time in accordance with the terms of this agreement.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a576817">
                <defn.term>Supported Software</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Software that is both:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Specified in <internal.reference refid="a462774"><ital>Part 6</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference> as Supported Software.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Currently supported by [Supplier <bold>OR</bold> the manufacture of the Maintained Equipment] [as detailed in <internal.reference refid="a462774"><ital>Part 6</ital></internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>].</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a841808">
                <defn.term>Term</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Initial Period together with all Renewal Periods.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a577130">
                <defn.term>Unsupported Software</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Software that is not Supported Software.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a230010">
                <defn.term>VAT</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>value added tax imposed by the Value Added Tax Act 1994 [or any similar tax] chargeable in the UK [or elsewhere].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a254794" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>VAT</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000015" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Unless the parties are confident there will be no UK VAT or equivalent sales tax, it is recommended they retain the wording "or elsewhere" in the document.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a753327">
                <defn.term>Virus</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any program which contains malicious code or infiltrates or damages a computer system without the owner's informed consent or is designed to do so or which is hostile, intrusive or annoying to the owner or user and has no legitimate purpose.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a603090">
              <identifier>1.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Clause, Schedule and paragraph headings shall not affect the interpretation of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a1015616">
              <identifier>1.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A <bold>person</bold> includes a natural person, corporate or unincorporated body (whether or not having separate legal personality).</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a1043615">
              <identifier>1.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Schedules form part of this agreement and shall have effect as if set out in full in the body of this agreement. Any reference to this agreement includes the Schedules.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a225199">
              <identifier>1.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to a <bold>company</bold> shall include any company, corporation or other body corporate, wherever and however incorporated or established.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a414871">
              <identifier>1.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Unless the context otherwise requires, words in the singular shall include the plural and in the plural shall include the singular.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a314694">
              <identifier>1.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Unless the context otherwise requires, a reference to one gender shall include a reference to the other genders.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a880804">
              <identifier>1.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to a statute or statutory provision is a reference to it as amended, extended or re-enacted from time to time.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a182473">
              <identifier>1.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to a statute or statutory provision shall include all subordinate legislation made from time to time under that statute or statutory provision.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a543047">
              <identifier>1.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to writing or written excludes faxes [and email <bold>OR</bold> but not e-mail].</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a672245" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Reference to writing</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000016" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Care should be taken to ensure the approach in this <internal.reference refid="a543047"><ital>clause 1.10</ital></internal.reference> aligns with the approach taken in <internal.reference refid="a606956"><ital>clause 16</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a930166">
              <identifier>1.11</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>References to clauses and Schedules are to the clauses and Schedules of this agreement and references to paragraphs are to paragraphs of the relevant Schedule.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a299968">
              <identifier>1.12</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Any words following the terms <bold>including</bold>, <bold>include</bold>, <bold>in particular</bold>, <bold>for example</bold> or any similar expression shall be interpreted as illustrative and shall not limit the sense of the words, description, definition, phrase or term preceding those terms.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a120646">
              <identifier>1.13</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If there is an inconsistency between any of the provisions in the main body of this agreement and the Schedules, the provisions in the main body of this agreement shall prevail.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a190564">
            <identifier>2.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Maintenance Services</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a987618" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Maintenance Services</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000017" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause sets out the three main types of Maintenance Services being provided by the Supplier under this agreement. These are:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Preventative Maintenance. This is where the Supplier attends the Customer's premises to assess the Maintained Equipment with the objective of pre-empting any potential problems with it, and also repairing any Maintained Equipment which has failed and gone unnoticed or which is not operating as it should. Consider how frequently the Supplier will be required to carry out these pre-emptive visits.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Corrective Maintenance. This is where the Supplier attends the Customer's premises to repair the Maintained Equipment in response to a Customer's request. The key distinction between Corrective Maintenance and Emergency Maintenance is that Corrective Maintenance is performed during Normal Business Hours and (subject to <internal.reference refid="a628498"><ital>clause 4.1</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a795354"><ital>clause 6</ital></internal.reference>) is included in the fixed Standard Maintenance Fee. The parties will need to consider and agree the level of commitment that the Supplier will give in relation to any Response Time and Fix Time Service Levels. Will these be firm commitments, or will they be given on a reasonable endeavours basis only?</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Emergency Maintenance. This is where the Supplier attends the Customer's premises outside Normal Business Hours and, as such, is charged at the Additional Services Rates.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <division id="a760285" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Software support</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the Supplier is providing any software support services then consider what will be done as part of the above elements of the maintenance services (such as who is responsible for regular patching and installing updates and whether this forms part of the Supplier’s services or should be a Customer responsibility and therefore an Excluded Cause), see <internal.reference refid="a772513"><ital>Drafting note, Software maintenance services (optional)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a769946">
              <identifier>2.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>During the Term, the Supplier shall provide the Customer with the Maintenance Services.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a473603">
              <identifier>2.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall [every [NUMBER] weeks <bold>OR</bold> at a frequency as is reasonably determined by the Supplier] perform Preventative Maintenance of the Maintained Equipment. Where the Supplier wishes to attend the Location in order to perform Preventative Maintenance, it shall do so during Normal Business Hours.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a672503">
              <identifier>2.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>On the Customer informing the Supplier that the Maintained Equipment is malfunctioning or has failed or is otherwise not in Good Working Order, the Supplier shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a341382">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[use all reasonable endeavours to] perform Corrective Maintenance of the Maintained Equipment within the relevant Fix Time; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a849955">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>where, in the Supplier's opinion, it cannot reasonably perform Corrective Maintenance remotely, [use all reasonable endeavours to] attend at the Location during Normal Business Hours within the relevant Response Time.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a366762">
              <identifier>2.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>On the Customer informing the Supplier outside of Normal Business Hours that the Maintained Equipment is malfunctioning, has failed or is not in Good Working Order, the Supplier shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a566373">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[use all reasonable endeavours to] perform Emergency Maintenance of the Maintained Equipment within the relevant Fix Time; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a826087">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>where, in the Supplier's opinion, it cannot reasonably perform Emergency Maintenance remotely, [use all reasonable endeavours to] attend at the Location within the relevant Response Time.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a779316">
              <identifier>2.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Emergency Maintenance shall be charged at the Additional Services Rates for each of the Supplier's personnel involved in the performance of Emergency Maintenance. Any additional charges shall be calculated, in the case of Emergency Maintenance that is performed remotely, from the time at which the relevant Supplier personnel commence performance of Emergency Maintenance, and in the case of Emergency Maintenance that is performed at the Location, from when the personnel arrive at the Location until they leave the Location.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a421508">
              <identifier>2.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>In performing any Maintenance Services, the Supplier shall [use all reasonable endeavours to] restore any malfunctioning or failed Maintained Equipment to Good Working Order either remotely or while in attendance at the Location. Where this is not reasonably practicable, or not reasonably practicable within Normal Business Hours (in the case of Preventative Maintenance and Corrective Maintenance), the Supplier shall either arrange for a further visit to the Location within Normal Business Hours to complete the repair, or remove the Maintained Equipment or part of the Maintained Equipment for repair off-site.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a560365">
              <identifier>2.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall procure that its personnel shall, while on site at the Location, comply with the Customer's reasonable health and safety and security policies provided that these policies have been brought to the attention of its personnel [in writing in advance].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a451790">
              <identifier>2.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall not be required to perform any maintenance or support in relation to either:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a195727">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Unsupported Software.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a672611">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Supported Software where Customer is in breach of [this agreement or ]the relevant EULA.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause condition="optional" id="a143793">
            <identifier>3.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Service Levels</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a393509" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Service Levels</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000018" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The parties may wish to include a Service Level regime to measure the Supplier's performance under the agreement. In a hardware maintenance agreement, the Service Level measurements most commonly used are the Response Times and the Fix Times. The target response and resolution times will typically vary, depending on the severity of the problem. Severity categories, together with the applicable Response Times and Fix Times, should be documented in <internal.reference refid="a741444"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Where Service Levels apply, the Customer will normally expect these to be backed by some form of Service Credit regime, under which the Customer is entitled to a partial refund of maintenance charges if the Supplier fails to meet the Service Levels in any given measurement period (normally monthly or quarterly).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Take care to ensure that any Service Credits are not set at a punitive level to avoid the risk of unenforceability. For more information, see <link anchor="a574254" href="9-582-2885" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: agreed remedies: The rule against penalties</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Consider if and to the extent software should be covered in, or excluded from, the service level regime, see <internal.reference refid="a772513"><ital>Drafting note, Software maintenance services (optional)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a688541">
              <identifier>3.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall [use reasonable endeavours to] perform the Maintenance Services in accordance with the Service Levels.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a759265">
              <identifier>3.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall provide the Customer with a report, on a monthly basis [and in a form to be agreed with the Customer], setting out the Supplier's performance against the Service Levels in the immediately preceding month.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a812671">
              <identifier>3.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If the Supplier fails to perform the Maintenance Services in accordance with the Service Levels, the Supplier shall, without prejudice to the Customer's other rights and remedies:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a652452">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>arrange all additional resources necessary to perform the Maintenance Services in accordance with the Service Levels as soon as possible and at no additional charge to the Customer; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a133112">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>credit the Customer with the Service Credits, which shall take effect as an adjustment to the Standard Maintenance Fee.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a422609">
              <identifier>3.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The parties agree that the value of the Service Credits is proportionate when considering the Customer's legitimate interest to avoid any delay or deficiency in the maintenance of the Maintained Equipment.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a425553">
            <identifier>4.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Replacements and spare parts</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a282650" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Replacements and spare parts</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000019" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>It may not always be possible or economically viable for the Supplier to repair hardware that has failed. The agreement therefore needs to address the financial consequences of hardware failures which require spare or replacement parts. For example, are the costs of replacement/spare parts included within the Standard Maintenance Fees or are they subject to an additional charge?</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Some Customers will prefer to include these costs in the Standard Maintenance Fees on the basis that this will give greater budgetary certainty as to overall hardware maintenance costs, although this will be reflected in a higher maintenance charge. Fixing the fees in this way may also encourage the Supplier to maintain the Maintained Equipment to a higher standard than might otherwise be the case (as they cannot levy an additional charge for replacement hardware).</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a628498">
              <identifier>4.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>In performing the Preventative Maintenance, Corrective Maintenance and the Additional Services, the Supplier shall [use all reasonable endeavours to] source spare parts required to restore the Maintained Equipment to Good Working Order. Where the Supplier can reasonably source individual spare parts for less than £[AMOUNT] excluding VAT, the Supplier shall not charge the Customer for the spare parts. Where the Supplier is unable to source individual spare parts for less than this amount, the Supplier shall have the right to charge the Customer for the spare parts.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a673814">
              <identifier>4.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>All spare parts and/or replacements provided by the Supplier to the Customer shall become part of the Maintained Equipment [and the property of the Customer. The Supplier will assign to the Customer, with full title guarantee and free from all third-party rights, all spare parts and/or replacements provided by the Supplier]. All parts and components removed from the Maintained Equipment by the Supplier in the course of performing the Preventative Maintenance, Corrective Maintenance and/or the Additional Services shall no longer constitute part of the Maintained Equipment [and will be the property of the Supplier. The Customer will assign to the Supplier, with full title guarantee and free from all third-party rights, all parts and components removed from the Maintained Equipment by the Supplier in accordance with this <internal.reference refid="a673814"><ital>clause 4.2</ital></internal.reference>]. [For the purposes of this sub-clause, 'assign' includes 'transfer ownership of'.]</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a69024">
            <identifier>5.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Customer's obligations</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a617817" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Customer's obligations</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000020" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause contains a number of obligations on the Customer which, from the Supplier's standpoint, are intended to reduce the amount of Corrective Maintenance or Emergency Maintenance required. Many of these are relatively standard Customer obligations. However, the implications of each will need to be carefully considered.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>In particular, <internal.reference refid="a252658"><ital>clause 5(f)</ital></internal.reference> (which prevents anyone other than the Supplier maintaining or making changes to the Maintained Equipment), <internal.reference refid="a451558"><ital>clause 5(g)</ital></internal.reference> (which prevents the Customer from moving the equipment without the Supplier's prior written consent), and <internal.reference refid="a113801"><ital>clause 5(i)</ital></internal.reference> (which requires the Customer to use only materials that have been supplied or approved by the Supplier) each require careful consideration, particularly in the context of any outsourcing arrangements that the Customer has entered into (or is planning to enter into). They will not be appropriate in many cases.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a256703">
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a173843">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>ensure that the Maintained Equipment is installed and kept at the Location, under suitable conditions, as specified in [the agreement under which the Maintained Equipment was supplied <bold>OR</bold> the Operating Manuals], and permit only trained and competent personnel to use it and follow any operating instructions as the Supplier may give from time to time;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a953580">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>notify the Supplier promptly if the Maintained Equipment is discovered to be operating incorrectly.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a348790">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>at all reasonable times permit full and free access to the Location and to the Maintained Equipment to the Supplier, its employees, contractors and agents, and provide them with adequate and safe working space, and any telecommunications facilities as are reasonably required to enable the Supplier to perform the Maintenance Services and the Additional Services while at the Location;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a163162">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>provide the Supplier with any information that is reasonably requested in the performance of the Maintenance Services and the Additional Services;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a985624">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>take any steps reasonably necessary to ensure the safety of the Supplier's personnel when attending the Location;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a252658">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>not allow any person other than the Supplier to maintain, alter, modify or adjust the Maintained Equipment without the prior written approval of the Supplier;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a451558">
                <identifier>(g)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>not move the Maintained Equipment from the Location without the prior written approval of the Supplier (such approval not to be unreasonably withheld or delayed);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a120437">
                <identifier>(h)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>store any reserve equipment only in conditions approved by the Supplier, and make this equipment available for periodic maintenance, as with all other Maintained Equipment; [and]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a113801">
                <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>only use supplies or materials supplied or approved by the Supplier (such approval not to be unreasonably withheld or delayed)[; and]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a679275">
                <identifier>(j)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>only use the Software in accordance with the terms and conditions set out in the EULA.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a795354">
            <identifier>6.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Excluded Maintenance</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a438825" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Excluded Maintenance</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000021" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause needs careful review by both parties as it effectively defines the scope of the hardware Maintenance Services (and the circumstances in which those Maintenance Services will be provided) as part of the Standard Maintenance Fees.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>From the Supplier's point of view, it protects them from having to provide Maintenance Services in relation to failures or malfunctions which are the fault of the Customer (for example, damage caused by moving equipment or a failure to use required environmental controls). From the Customer's point of view, careful attention needs to be paid to ensure that the exclusions are not too broad, in turn significantly reducing the circumstances in which maintenance will be provided as part of the Standard Maintenance Fees.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>As drafted, where maintenance is required for any of the reasons set out in the definition of<ital> </ital><internal.reference refid="a959570"><ital>Excluded Causes</ital></internal.reference>, additional charges will be applied.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a502913">
              <identifier>6.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier is not obliged to perform any Excluded Maintenance.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a310649">
              <identifier>6.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Where the Supplier is performing or has performed the Maintenance Services in circumstances where it is established that the Maintained Equipment was not in Good Working Order due to any of the Excluded Causes, the Supplier may charge, and the Customer shall pay, the Additional Services Fees in respect of that work.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a158520">
            <identifier>7.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Charges</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a83750" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Charges</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000022" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>There are three types of fees payable under this agreement:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Standard Maintenance Fees. These are payable in respect of Preventative Maintenance and Corrective Maintenance (and, where applicable, the Software Maintenance Services) performed during Normal Business Hours. The applicable payment terms (that is, when the fees will be payable and at what intervals) need to be agreed and documented in <internal.reference refid="a94432"><ital>clause 7.4</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Additional Services Fees. These are payable in respect of any Emergency Maintenance and any Excluded Maintenance. Additional Services Fees are calculated in accordance with the rates set out in <internal.reference refid="a143290"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference> and, as currently drafted, are payable in arrear on a monthly basis.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Fees for spare parts. These charges are payable where the threshold set out in <internal.reference refid="a628498"><ital>clause 4.1</ital></internal.reference> is exceeded.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a635134">
              <identifier>7.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>For the performance of Corrective Maintenance and Preventative Maintenance [and Software Maintenance Services], the Customer shall pay to the Supplier the Standard Maintenance Fees.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a919485">
              <identifier>7.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>For the performance of any Additional Services, the Customer shall pay to the Supplier the Additional Services Fees.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a332012">
              <identifier>7.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Standard Maintenance Fees and the Additional Services Fees shall be inclusive of all expenses, other than those recoverable in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a628498"><ital>clause 4.1</ital></internal.reference>, and the Supplier shall be responsible for all costs and expenses incurred in providing the Maintenance Services (other than those recoverable in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a628498"><ital>clause 4.1</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a94432">
              <identifier>7.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Standard Maintenance Fees shall be due and payable in full to the Supplier [annually in advance], within [30] days of receipt of a valid invoice from the Supplier. Any Additional Services Fees shall be due and payable monthly, within [30] days of receipt of a valid invoice from the Supplier. Any charges for spare parts recoverable in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a628498"><ital>clause 4.1</ital></internal.reference> shall be due within [30] days of receipt of a valid invoice from the Supplier.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a276014">
              <identifier>7.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If the Customer fails to make any payment due to the Supplier under this agreement by the due date for payment, then[, without limiting the Supplier's remedies under <internal.reference refid="a839850"><ital>clause 11</ital></internal.reference>, the Customer shall pay interest on the overdue amount at the rate of [4]% per annum above [FULL NAME OF BANK]'s base rate from time to time. Such interest shall accrue on a daily basis from the due date until actual payment of the overdue amount, whether before or after judgment. The Customer shall pay the interest together with the overdue amount.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a731266">
              <identifier>7.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>All payments made by the Customer under this agreement are exclusive of VAT, which shall be paid by the Customer at the rate and in the manner for the time being prescribed by law. The Supplier shall provide the Customer with a valid VAT invoice.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a110853">
              <identifier>7.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall pay any stamp duties or similar transfer taxes imposed on the supplies made under this agreement and shall reimburse the Supplier for any such stamp duties or similar transfer taxes paid by the Supplier. If the Customer is required to make any deduction for or on account of tax from any payment due under this agreement (<bold>Tax Deduction</bold>):</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a634762">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Customer shall account to the relevant tax authority for such Tax Deduction and shall provide evidence to the Supplier that it has so accounted.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a420774">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The amount of the payment due under this Agreement shall be increased so that the Supplier receives an amount equal to the amount that would have been received by it, had the Customer not been required to make any Tax Deduction.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer and the Supplier shall co-operate to minimise the amount of any Tax Deduction. If following the making of a Tax Deduction, the Supplier determines [in its sole discretion <bold>OR</bold> acting in good faith] that it (or any member of the Supplier's group) has received and retained any credit, relief or other benefit as a result of the Tax Deduction, the Supplier shall pay such amount to the Customer as the Supplier determines [in its sole discretion <bold>OR</bold> acting in good faith] would leave the Supplier in the same position as if the Customer had not been required to make any Tax Deduction.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a921228" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Tax deductions and withholding (optional)</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000023" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>In international supply agreements, for example where the customer and supplier are located in different countries, consideration should be given as to whether the short provision in <internal.reference refid="a731266"><ital>clause 7.6</ital></internal.reference> is sufficient by itself, or whether it may be necessary to have additional wording to deal with taxation issues that only arise in international contexts, (such as transfer taxes and tax withholding). <internal.reference refid="a110853"><ital>Clause 7.7</ital></internal.reference> is an optional clause that can be used for tax withholding where required. It is always advisable to obtain expert tax advice on the structuring of payments before any agreement is entered into. For further guidance on tax deductions and withholding, see <link href="5-201-9175" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Withholding tax</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a631089">
              <identifier>7.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier may, at any time after the [first] anniversary of the Commencement Date, increase the Standard Maintenance Fees and the Additional Services Rates by giving to the Customer not less than [three] months written notice, provided that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a197200">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the increase shall not exceed a percentage equal to the percentage increase in [the Consumer Prices Index (All Items) <bold>OR </bold>SPECIFY INDEX] published by the Office for National Statistics (or its successor from time to time) for the period from the Commencement Date (in the case of the first increase) or the date on which the immediately preceding increase came into effect pursuant to this clause (in the case of the second or any subsequent increase) up to the date of this notice; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a233289">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the increases shall be no more frequent than once in any 12-month period.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a230869" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Increasing the standard maintenance fees</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000024" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a631089"><ital>Clause 7.8</ital></internal.reference> sets out a mechanism under which the Supplier can increase the Standard Maintenance Fees and the Additional Services Rates during the Term of the Agreement. The clause envisages that there will be an Initial Period following the Commencement Date in which those charges may not be increased. Thereafter, the Supplier is entitled to increase the Charges once in any 12-month period in line with any increases to the consumer price indexes in the preceding 12-month period.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For other indices you might use for annual increases, see <link href="w-038-1950" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Choosing a price index for a price variation clause</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a859442">
            <identifier>8.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Supplier warranties</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a246561" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Supplier warranties</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000025" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause sets out fairly standard supplier warranties, exclusions and obligations. Specifically, the Supplier undertakes that:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The services will be performed substantially in accordance with reasonable skill and care and/or in accordance with Good Industry Practice.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Appropriate skilled and qualified personnel of sufficient number will perform the services in accordance with applicable laws.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Any equipment supplied will operate in accordance with their technical specifications.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a607135"><ital>Clause 8.2</ital></internal.reference> is included to negate all other terms which may otherwise be implied by law (such as those implied terms set out in the <link href="1-507-2816" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Sale of Goods Act 1979</ital></link> and the <link href="3-507-0623" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982</ital></link>) so as to limit the extent and scope of the Supplier's warranties to those set out in this <internal.reference refid="a859442"><ital>clause 8</ital></internal.reference> and elsewhere in the agreement.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a506958">
              <identifier>8.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier represents and warrants to the Customer that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a304013">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Maintenance Services and the Additional Services shall be performed:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a912848">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>by an appropriate number of suitably qualified and experienced personnel;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a86342">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>using all reasonable skill and care [and in accordance with Good Industry Practice]; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a97023">
                  <identifier>(iii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in accordance with all laws and regulations in force from time to time which are applicable to the Supplier.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <drafting.note id="a332620" jurisdiction="">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Compliance with applicable laws</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <division id="a000026" level="1">
                      <para>
                        <paratext>When acting for the Supplier, you should be careful to ensure that any obligation to comply with applicable laws, is limited to those laws that are applicable to the Supplier and not the Customer.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>This will be particularly important where the Customer is subject to the NIS Regulations, and is required to maintain a higher standard of cybersecurity, and business continuity, than would otherwise apply to other business sectors, see <internal.reference refid="a480584"><ital>Drafting note, Operators of essential services and relevant digital service providers</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>A supplier may want to make it clear that any such heightened cybersecurity requirements do not apply to it (for an example of such a disclaimer, in the context of a software licence, see <link anchor="a540626" href="3-107-4814" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Software licence agreement (pro-supplier): Drafting note: Exclusion of cybersecurity warranties</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>On the other hand, the Customer may well want to flow down any such heightened cybersecurity requirements to its supplier who is responsible for maintaining its hardware (a failure of which may have serious security consequences for the Customer). In such case, the Supplier is likely to require clear and precise obligations to be set out in this agreement rather than to be forced to interpret what these standards might be by virtue of agreeing to a broad compliance with law clause.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </drafting.note>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a64979">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>all components and equipment supplied or used in the course of the provision of the Maintenance Services and the Additional Services shall operate materially in accordance with their technical specifications;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a161111">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier has the full capacity and authority and all necessary permissions, licences and consents necessary to enter into, and perform its obligations under, this agreement;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a894269">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier shall [take reasonable steps to] not introduce any Viruses into the Maintained Equipment, or the Customer's network and information systems, by way of the Maintenance Services or the Additional Services or otherwise.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a607135">
              <identifier>8.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Except as expressly stated in this agreement, all warranties, conditions and terms, whether express or implied by statute, common law or otherwise (including satisfactory quality, fitness for purpose and suitability) are hereby excluded to the fullest extent permitted by law.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a737902">
            <identifier>9.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Liability</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a876759" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Liability</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000027" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For further discussion on negotiating limits of liability in maintenance agreements (although focused on software maintenance), see <link anchor="co_anchor_a241821" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/7-107-4789?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note: overview, Main issues in software licensing and maintenance contracts: Limitation of liability</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more general information, see the following practice notes relating to limiting liability in B2B contracts:</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link anchor="co_anchor_a668968" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/2-107-4777?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Main issues in systems integration contracts: Exclusions and limitation of liability</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/2-520-5359?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Limiting liability: drafting and negotiating</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/9-617-5230?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Limiting liability: statutory and common law controls on limitation clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-006-5549?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Limiting liability: interpretation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The provisions relating to liability have been drafted on the basis that the parties are both commercial entities.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a647586"><ital>Clause 9.1</ital></internal.reference> states that death or personal injury arising from negligence cannot be excluded (<link href="4-506-5560" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 2(1)</ital></link><ital>, </ital><link href="7-505-7728" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977</ital></link><ital> </ital>(UCTA 1977)), nor can liability for fraud or fraudulent misrepresentation (<link href="D-008-7730" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Thomas Witter v TBP Industries [1996] 2 All ER 573</ital></link>). <internal.reference refid="a647586"><ital>clause 9.1</ital></internal.reference> also states that the obligations implied by <link href="7-508-2520" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 12</ital></link> of the Sale of Goods Act 1979 and <link href="9-507-2935" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 2</ital></link> of the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982 relating to title of property also are not excluded (<link href="8-507-2870" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>sections 6(1)</ital></link><ital> and </ital><link href="6-507-2871" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>7(3A)</ital></link><ital>, UCTA 1977</ital>).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a66750"><ital>Clause 9.2</ital></internal.reference> then seeks to exclude all loss that:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Constitutes loss of profits, business revenue or goodwill (whether direct or indirect).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Is loss or corruption of data or information (whether direct or indirect).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Is special, indirect or consequential.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The distinction between direct and indirect loss is not clear cut, and there is no easy formulation to determine on which side of the line a particular category or type of loss falls in any specific case. A particular difficulty arises when deciding whether loss of profits is direct or indirect. Recent case law has tended to hold that loss of profits can be a direct loss. In a limitation of liability clause such as this, if it is the parties' intention to exclude all loss of profit, this needs to be done in a way that does not link lost profit with indirect loss. Otherwise, direct loss of profit is unlikely to be excluded, since exclusion clauses are interpreted by the courts <ital>contra proferentem</ital>, that is, against the person seeking to rely upon it.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Finally, <internal.reference refid="a536728"><ital>clause 9.3</ital></internal.reference> seeks to limit both parties' aggregate liability under the contract to a pre-set sum, by reference to the greater of a multiple of the contract price or a fixed amount. As a general rule, if this is a contract to which <link href="5-505-8743" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 3</ital></link> of UCTA 1977 potentially applies (that is, if it is, or could be considered to be, effectively on one party's standard terms) then there is a risk that if the liability cap is significantly below the contract price, it could be held by the courts to be unreasonable (under the test laid down by UCTA 1977) and therefore unenforceable.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The charges multiple set out in <internal.reference refid="a882575"><ital>clause 9.3(b)</ital></internal.reference> may conceivably produce a low sum and run the risk of being viewed as unreasonable and therefore unenforceable. To reduce this risk, <internal.reference refid="a536728"><ital>clause 9.3</ital></internal.reference> caps liability at the greater of the charges multiple and a fixed sum to be inserted into <internal.reference refid="a231015"><ital>clause 9.3(a)</ital></internal.reference>. The latter should be determined in accordance with established principles of what is a reasonable sum in the particular circumstances. If this provision is held to be unreasonable under UCTA 1977, damages would be recoverable without limitation, on the basis of the ordinary contract law rules of remoteness.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Depending on which formulation is chosen, these rules say that recoverable loss is either:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Loss which arises naturally from a breach or which may reasonably be supposed to have been in the parties' contemplation when they made the contract as the probable result of a breach (the classic formulation in <link href="D-000-1778" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Hadley v Baxendale (1854) 9 Ex 341</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>All loss which, at the time the contract was made, was reasonably foreseeable as liable to result from the breach (<link href="D-016-1528" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Victoria Laundry (Windsor) v Newman Industries [1949] 2 KB 528</ital></link>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>It may be agreed that the Supplier's liability will be unlimited in specific circumstances. Common exceptions include breach of confidentiality (<internal.reference refid="a927892"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference>), The Supplier's attitude is likely to depend on the nature of the services to be provided, and the types of confidential information it may have access to in the course of its maintenance.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Customer might want to state that the Supplier's liability in relation to compliance with any cybersecurity obligations (including where these place the Customer in breach of the NIS Regulations, if applicable, see <internal.reference refid="a779169"><ital>Drafting note, Cybersecurity</ital></internal.reference>) or data protection obligations (see <internal.reference refid="a549452"><ital>Drafting note, Data protection</ital></internal.reference>) should not be subject to the Supplier's liability cap. At the very least, the parties should consider, when setting the cap, that a fine for breaches of this legislation could be very substantial. For further discussion on this topic, see <link anchor="a207698" href="w-027-2423" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Data protection issues in IT contracts: Liability for data protection compliance in IT contracts</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Where software is provided you will also want to consider whether an IP indemnity should be included, and whether that should be uncapped (and subject to a conduct of claims provision), see <link anchor="a735753" href="7-107-4789" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note: overview, Main issues in software licensing and maintenance contracts: Intellectual property and indemnities</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a647586">
              <identifier>9.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Neither party excludes or limits liability to the other party for:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a632860">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>fraud or fraudulent misrepresentation;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a942618">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>death or personal injury caused by negligence; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a1013342">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a breach of any obligations implied by section 12 of the Sale of Goods Act 1979 or section 2 of the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a66750">
              <identifier>9.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Subject always to <internal.reference refid="a647586"><ital>clause 9.1</ital></internal.reference>, neither party shall be liable whether in contract, tort (including for negligence or breach of statutory duty), misrepresentation (whether innocent or negligent), restitution or otherwise, for:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a906529">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any loss (whether direct or indirect) of profits, business, revenue, or goodwill;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a387190">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss or corruption (whether direct or indirect) of data or information; or</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a850515" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Excluding the Supplier's liability for loss or corruption of data</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000028" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The Customer may wish to resist such an exclusion, particularly where the Supplier will be responsible for maintaining hardware which stores business critical information, or personal data (see <internal.reference refid="a549452"><ital>Drafting note, Data protection</ital></internal.reference>) or where the Customer is subject to the NIS Regulations (see <internal.reference refid="a779169"><ital>Drafting note, Cybersecurity</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a679630">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any special, indirect or consequential loss, costs, damages, charges or expenses,</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext>in each case, however arising under this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a536728">
              <identifier>9.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Subject always to <internal.reference refid="a647586"><ital>clause 9.1</ital></internal.reference>, each party's total aggregate liability in contract, tort (including negligence and breach of statutory duty), misrepresentation (whether innocent or negligent), restitution or otherwise, arising in connection with the performance,  contemplated performance, or non-performance of this agreement shall be limited to the greater of:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a231015">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>£[AMOUNT]; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a882575">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[PERCENTAGE]% of the total Charges paid by the Customer to the Supplier [during the [12-]month period immediately preceding the date on which the first cause of action under this agreement first arose].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a927892">
            <identifier>10.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Confidentiality [and compliance with policies]</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a323102" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Confidentiality</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000029" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="2-107-3829" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Confidentiality</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <division id="a780600" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Compliance with policies</headtext>
                  </head>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a959936">
              <identifier>10.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><defn.term>Confidential Information</defn.term> means all confidential information (however recorded or preserved) disclosed by a party or its Representatives (as defined below) to the other party and that party's Representatives [whether before or] [after the date of this agreement] in connection with this agreement or the Maintenance Services including but not limited to:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a432058">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the [existence and] terms of this agreement [or any agreement entered into in connection with this agreement];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a159289">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any information that would be regarded as confidential by a reasonable business person relating to:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a941556">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the business, assets, affairs, customers, clients, suppliers, [or] plans [, intentions, or market opportunities] of the disclosing party [(or of any member of the group of companies to which the disclosing party belongs)]; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a854244">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the operations, processes, product information, know-how, designs, trade secrets or software of the disclosing party [(or of any member of the group of companies to which the disclosing party belongs)];</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a383352">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any information developed by the parties in the course of carrying out this agreement; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a458681">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any information detailed in Schedule [NUMBER].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Representatives</bold> means, in relation to a party, its employees, officers, contractors, subcontractors, representatives and advisers.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a122818">
              <identifier>10.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The provisions of this clause shall not apply to any Confidential Information that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a107351">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>is or becomes generally available to the public (other than as a result of its disclosure by the receiving party or its Representatives in breach of this clause);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a965454">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>was available to the receiving party on a non-confidential basis before disclosure by the disclosing party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a646690">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>was, is or becomes available to the receiving party on a non-confidential basis from a person who, to the receiving party's knowledge, is not bound by a confidentiality agreement with the disclosing party or otherwise prohibited from disclosing the information to the receiving party; [or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a675566">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the parties agree in writing is not confidential or may be disclosed[; or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a271172">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>is developed by or for the receiving party independently of the information disclosed by the disclosing party.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a895067">
              <identifier>10.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party shall keep the other party's Confidential Information secret and confidential and shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a267104">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>not use any Confidential Information except [for the purpose of exercising or performing its rights and obligations under or in connection with this agreement  <bold>OR </bold>[SPECIFY PURPOSE]] (<defn.term>Permitted Purpose</defn.term>); or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a508729">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>not disclose such Confidential Information in whole or in part to any third party, except as expressly permitted by this <internal.reference refid="a927892"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a458763">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>not process the Confidential Information in any way using machine learning or artificial intelligence (“AI”) models <bold>OR</bold> only process the Confidential Information using machine learning or artificial intelligence (“AI”) models where those models will not be:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a322715">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>trained on the Confidential Information; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a742322">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>lawfully available to or accessible for use by any person or entity except for a party or its Representatives.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <drafting.note id="a959623" jurisdiction="">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>AI and machine learning (optional)</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <division id="a000030" level="1">
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The specific requirements of a confidentiality clause can vary with the type of information being shared and its intended purpose. However, with AI use becoming ever more prevalent in a commercial context, practitioners should expressly address the parties' potential use of AI and machine learning, including how this interfaces with the need to protect the confidential information disclosed.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Choose from the following two drafting options:</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <list type="bulleted">
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext><bold>Option 1.</bold> Unless there is a transaction-specific reason to permit it, a confidentiality clause should prohibit the use of the other party's confidential information by AI or machine learning models (whether private or public facing). This broad prohibition also prevents use of the disclosed confidential information to train such models. Particularly with a public facing AI model (for example, Chat GPT), this helps address the risk that a party's confidential information may be used to train the model to respond to future queries by members of the public, and so lead to potential data leakage (unauthorised disclosure to third parties). The first drafting option at <internal.reference refid="a458763"><ital>clause 10.3(a)</ital></internal.reference> reflects this approach.</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                        <list.item>
                          <para>
                            <paratext><bold>Option 2</bold>. If either or both parties are unable to agree to a blanket prohibition on disclosure of the confidential information to AI or machine learning models, for example because the proposed commercial transaction envisages use of AI, the confidentiality clause should expressly provide for that. In these circumstances, practitioners should also consider imposing a condition on the recipient of the discloser's confidential information that any such information fed into the AI model will not be used to train it, and that the AI model is not accessible to or available for use by anyone that is not already allowed to access the confidential information under the agreement. Choose the second drafting option at <internal.reference refid="a458763"><ital>clause 10.3(a)</ital></internal.reference> if taking this approach.</paratext>
                          </para>
                        </list.item>
                      </list>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>It should be noted that <internal.reference refid="a458763"><ital>clause 10.3(a)</ital></internal.reference> may not favour IT suppliers (who may, typically, be the most likely to want to use customer information to train AI models) so this clause has been made optional.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>For further information on AI and confidentiality, see <link anchor="a402318" href="8-384-4456" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Protecting confidential information: overview: Artificial intelligence (AI) and confidentiality</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </drafting.note>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a1049431">
              <identifier>10.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A party may disclose the other party's Confidential Information to those of its Representatives who need to know that Confidential Information for the Permitted Purpose, provided that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a427324">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>it informs such Representatives of the confidential nature of the Confidential Information before disclosure; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a1028069">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>at all times, it is responsible for the Representatives' compliance with the confidentiality obligations set out in this <internal.reference refid="a927892"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a491412">
              <identifier>10.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A party may disclose Confidential Information to the extent such Confidential Information is required to be disclosed by law, by any governmental or other regulatory authority [(including, without limitation, [ANY RELEVANT SECURITIES EXCHANGES])] or by a court or other authority of competent jurisdiction provided that, to the extent it is legally permitted to do so, it gives the other party as much notice of such disclosure as possible [and, where notice of disclosure is not prohibited and is given in accordance with this <internal.reference refid="a491412"><ital>clause 10.5</ital></internal.reference>, it takes into account the reasonable requests of the other party in relation to the content of such disclosure].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a835805">
              <identifier>10.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party reserves all rights in its Confidential Information. No rights or obligations in respect of a party's Confidential Information, other than those expressly stated in this agreement, are granted to the other party, or are to be implied from this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a333783">
              <identifier>10.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The provisions of this <internal.reference refid="a927892"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference> shall [continue to apply after termination [or expiry] of this agreement <bold>OR</bold> survive for a period of [five] years from termination [or expiry] of this agreement].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a253506">
              <identifier>10.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Except as expressly stated in this agreement, no party makes any express or implied warranty or representation concerning its Confidential Information.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a727298">
              <identifier>10.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A party may, provided that it has reasonable grounds to believe that the other party is involved in activity that may constitute a criminal offence under the Bribery Act 2010, disclose Confidential Information to the Serious Fraud Office without first informing the other party of such disclosure.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a305119">
              <identifier>10.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[In performing its obligations under this agreement the [Supplier <bold>OR</bold> Customer] shall comply with the Mandatory Policies.]</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a855735" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Compliance with policies</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000031" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext><internal.reference refid="a305119"><ital>Clause 10.10</ital></internal.reference> can be used where the Customer or Supplier has specific business policies and wants to ensure that the other party complies with them. The policies might reflect a party's legal obligations, for instance, its obligations under instruments such as the Modern Slavery Act 2015 (see <internal.reference refid="a443853"><ital>Drafting note, Supply chain issues: slavery and human trafficking</ital></internal.reference>) the Bribery Act 2010, or data protection legislation (see <internal.reference refid="a549452"><ital>Drafting note, Data protection</ital></internal.reference>). Alternatively, a party may have adopted business social responsibility policies voluntarily.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>In most goods or services agreements, the obligation is usually on the supplier to comply with the customer's policies. But this may not always be the case: depending on the bargaining strengths of the parties, a supplier may well require the customer to comply with the supplier's policies instead. As this is a pro-supplier agreement, the Supplier may want to omit this clause altogether from the first draft provided to the Customer.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the Supplier does choose to include this clause, there are two drafting options:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The first is a requirement on the Customer to comply with the Supplier's policies. This is slightly unusual (the usual position is that a supplier agrees to comply with its customer's policies), but a supplier who is concerned about its reputation may well want to ensure that it is only supplying goods or services to customers who are willing to comply with the supplier's policies on issues such as anti-bribery, modern slavery and ethics, or cybersecurity.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The second option is a requirement on the Supplier to comply with the Customer's policies. This is the more usual approach in a goods or services agreement. A supplier may include this option if, for instance, it has already agreed in principle that it is able to comply with its customer's policies, or the parties already have an ongoing relationship where the supplier is comfortable with complying with the customer's policies.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Whatever approach is taken, check that the definition of <internal.reference refid="a379762"><ital>Drafting note, Mandatory Policies (optional)</ital></internal.reference> above is consistent with the approach in this clause.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Note also that if the Customer agrees to comply with the Supplier's policies, the Supplier may want a subsequent right to terminate the agreement if the Customer breaches those policies. If this is desired, the Supplier could include this additional right to terminate at <internal.reference refid="a839850"><ital>clause 11</ital></internal.reference>. For an example of this, see <link href="0-350-9991#a1028636" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Simple framework services agreement (pro-customer): clause 15.4(a)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information on general compliance clauses, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-618-9498" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Compliance with laws and policies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a839850">
            <identifier>11.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Term and termination</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a56069" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Term and termination</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000032" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a291058"><ital>Clause 11.1</ital></internal.reference> provides for the agreement to last for the Initial Period, and after that for successive Renewal Periods, unless either party notifies the other of its intention to terminate the agreement at least 60 days before the end of the Initial Period or any subsequent Renewal Period. The Supplier and Customer should both consider whether 60 days is a sufficient period of time.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Each party has the right to terminate the contract in the event of the other's insolvency or default (<internal.reference refid="a470318"><ital>clause 11.2</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a487367"><ital>Clause 11.6</ital></internal.reference> sets out fairly standard provisions for the consequences of termination in this kind of agreement (that is, return of the other party's property and documentation and payment of outstanding amounts). <internal.reference refid="a761036"><ital>clause 11.6(b)</ital></internal.reference> obliges the Supplier to provide a degree of transitional assistance upon termination. Customers may want to consider making these obligations more defined and extensive. Suppliers may wish to remove this provision completely or make it optional at the request of the Customer but subject to additional charges.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For further information, see <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/3-107-4673?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Standard clause, Termination</ital></link> and associated drafting notes, including information on the <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-026-2452?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Corporate Insolvency and Governance Act 2020</ital></link>, which came into force on 26 June 2020. See also <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-025-9457?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Restrictions on terminating supply contracts in insolvency proceedings</ital></link> and, in particular, <link anchor="co_anchor_a557921" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-025-9457?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>What is a contract for the supply of goods and services?</ital></link> and the commentary around <link anchor="co_anchor_a387269" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-025-9457?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Software licence agreements</ital></link> and <link anchor="co_anchor_a776693" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-025-9457?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Intellectual property licence agreements</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a291058">
              <identifier>11.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement shall commence on the Commencement Date. Unless terminated earlier in accordance with this <internal.reference refid="a839850"><ital>clause 11</ital></internal.reference>, this agreement shall continue for the Initial Period and shall automatically extend for a Renewal Period at the end of the Initial Period and at the end of each Renewal Period. Either party may give written notice to the other party, not later than [60 days] before the end of the Initial Period or the relevant Renewal Period, to terminate this agreement at the end of the Initial Period or the relevant Renewal Period, as the case may be.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a470318">
              <identifier>11.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Without affecting any other right or remedy available to it, either party may terminate this agreement with immediate effect by giving [written] notice to the other party if:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a979610">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party fails to pay any amount due under this agreement on the due date for payment and remains in default not less than [NUMBER] days after being notified [in writing] to make such payment;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a926452">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party commits a material breach of any [other] term of this agreement and (if such breach is remediable) fails to remedy that breach within a period of [NUMBER] days after being notified [in writing] to do so;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a324585">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party repeatedly breaches any of the terms of this agreement in such a manner as to reasonably justify the opinion that its conduct is inconsistent with it having the intention or ability to give effect to the terms of this agreement;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a112466">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party suspends, or threatens to suspend, payment of its debts or is unable to pay its debts as they fall due or admits inability to pay its debts or [(being a company or limited liability partnership) is deemed unable to pay its debts within the meaning of section 123 of the Insolvency Act 1986 (<bold>IA 1986</bold>) as if the words "it is proved to the satisfaction of the court" did not appear in sections 123(1)(e) or 123(2) of the IA 1986 <bold>OR</bold> (being an individual) is deemed either unable to pay its debts or as having no reasonable prospect of so doing, in either case, within the meaning of section 268 of the IA 1986 <bold>OR</bold> (being a partnership) has any partner to whom any of the foregoing apply];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a528662">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party commences negotiations with all or any class of its creditors with a view to rescheduling any of its debts, or makes a proposal for or enters into any compromise or arrangement with any of its creditors [other than (being a company) for the sole purpose of a scheme for a solvent amalgamation of that other party with one or more other companies or the solvent reconstruction of that other party];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a272614">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party applies to court for, or obtains, a moratorium under Part A1 of the Insolvency Act 1986;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a278486">
                <identifier>(g)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a petition is filed, a notice is given, a resolution is passed, or an order is made, for or in connection with the winding up of the other party (being a company, limited liability partnership or partnership) [other than for the sole purpose of a scheme for a solvent amalgamation of that other party with one or more other companies or the solvent reconstruction of that other party];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a457739">
                <identifier>(h)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>an application is made to court, or an order is made, for the appointment of an administrator, or a notice of intention to appoint an administrator is given or an administrator is appointed, over the other party (being a company, partnership or limited liability partnership);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a367541">
                <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the holder of a qualifying floating charge over the assets of that other party (being a company or limited liability partnership) has become entitled to appoint or has appointed an administrative receiver;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a968485">
                <identifier>(j)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a person becomes entitled to appoint a receiver over all or any of the assets of the other party or a receiver is appointed over all or any of the assets of the other party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a331492">
                <identifier>(k)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a creditor or encumbrancer of the other party attaches or takes possession of, or a distress, execution, sequestration or other such process is levied or enforced on or sued against, the whole or any part of the other party's assets and such attachment or process is not discharged within [14] days;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a923515">
                <identifier>(l)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any event occurs, or proceeding is taken, with respect to the other party in any jurisdiction to which it is subject that has an effect equivalent or similar to any of the events mentioned in <internal.reference refid="a112466"><ital>clause 11.2(d)</ital></internal.reference> to <internal.reference refid="a331492"><ital>clause 11.2(k)</ital></internal.reference> (inclusive);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a818865">
                <identifier>(m)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party suspends or ceases, or threatens to suspend or cease, carrying on all or a substantial part of its business[; or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a827680">
                <identifier>(n)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party's financial position deteriorates so far as to reasonably justify the opinion that its ability to give effect to the terms of this agreement is in jeopardy[; or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a275449">
                <identifier>(o)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>there is a change of control of the other party [(within the meaning of section 1124 of the Corporation Tax Act 2010)][; or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a541466">
                <identifier>(p)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any warranty given by the other party in clause [NUMBER] of this agreement is found to be untrue or misleading.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a251118">
              <identifier>11.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>For the purposes of <internal.reference refid="a926452"><ital>clause 11.2(b)</ital></internal.reference> a material breach [means <bold>OR </bold>includes]:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a513620">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a breach of any of the obligations set out in clauses [NUMBERS]; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a862437">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a breach that has a serious effect on the benefit the terminating party would otherwise derive from this agreement [over any [NUMBER]-month period during its term].</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a433153" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Defining material breach (optional)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000033" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Consider carefully whether the agreement should include a definition for material breach, how that is defined, and whether that definition should be exhaustive. A definition which is too narrow or wide can make the termination trigger higher or lower than that which might be ordinarily expected. The definition may also not correctly anticipate the area(s) where a dispute ultimately arises. It is not unusual for English law governed contracts to leave this concept as undefined, despite this creating a degree of uncertainty as to when such a termination right may therefore arise. For further commentary on the meaning of material breach (where no definition is used) and related termination considerations, see <link anchor="a91689" href="6-370-6007" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Issues in IT contracts litigation: What is a "material" breach?</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a885167">
              <identifier>11.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Any provision of this agreement that expressly or by implication is intended to come into or continue in force on or after termination of this agreement shall remain in full force and effect.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a451278">
              <identifier>11.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Termination of this agreement, for any reason, shall not affect the accrued rights, remedies, obligations or liabilities of the parties existing at termination, including the right to claim damages in respect of any breach of the agreement which existed at or before the date of termination.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a487367">
              <identifier>11.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>On termination of this agreement for any reason;</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a498555">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>except as provided for in <internal.reference refid="a166927"><ital>clause 11.7</ital></internal.reference>, each party shall as soon as reasonably practicable:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a113520">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>return or destroy (or, in the case of electronic data, delete), as directed in writing by the other party, any documents, handbooks, CD-ROMs, DVDs, other tangible digital media or other information or data provided to it by the other party for the purposes of this agreement, including all documents and materials (and any copies) containing, reflecting, incorporating or based on the other party's Confidential Information. If required by the other party, it shall provide written evidence (in the form of a letter signed by its [RELEVANT OFFICER]) no later than [14] days after termination of this agreement that these have been destroyed or deleted and that it has not retained any copies of them, except for one copy that it may use for audit purposes only, and subject to the confidentiality obligations in <internal.reference refid="a927892"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference>;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a235060">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>delete any proprietary software belonging to the other party and all the other party's Confidential Information from its IT network and hard disks or other storage means associated with any computer equipment owned or controlled by that party. Each party shall provide written confirmation (in the form of a letter signed by its [RELEVANT OFFICER]) no later than [14] days after termination of this agreement that this software and Confidential Information has been deleted;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a604861">
                  <identifier>(iii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>return all of the other party's equipment and materials, failing which the other party may enter the relevant premises and take possession of them. Until these are returned or repossessed, the party remaining in possession shall be solely responsible for their safe-keeping;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a761036">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier shall provide all reasonable, transitional assistance to the Customer and/or any third party engaged by the Customer in connection with the maintenance and support of the Maintained Equipment; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a558091">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer shall immediately pay any outstanding amounts owed to the Supplier pursuant to this agreement.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a166927">
              <identifier>11.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If a party is required by any applicable law or regulation, or government or regulatory body of competent jurisdiction to retain any documents or materials which it would otherwise be required to return or destroy under <internal.reference refid="a487367"><ital>clause 11.6</ital></internal.reference>, it shall notify the other party in writing of that retention, giving details of the documents or materials that it must retain and the reasons for such retention, and it shall be entitled to retain such documents or materials for the period required by the relevant applicable law or regulation or government or regulatory body provided at all times that <internal.reference refid="a927892"><ital>clause 10</ital></internal.reference> shall continue to apply to any retained documents and materials.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a375431">
              <identifier>11.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Electronic data shall be considered deleted, for the purposes of <internal.reference refid="a487367"><ital>clause 11.6</ital></internal.reference>, where it has been put beyond use by the deleting party.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a185532" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Deletion of electronic data</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000034" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>It can be difficult for organisations (particularly suppliers) to agree to "delete" electronic data. The word ‘deletion’ can mean different things in relation to electronic data, and it is recognised that it is not always possible to delete or erase all traces of the data. As the ICO (the UK's data protection authority) has opined that the term "deletion", in relation to personal data, should be taken to mean ensuring that the data is beyond use, we consider this is a reasonable deletion standard to use in most circumstances. If it is appropriate to delete personal data from a live system, we recommend that a party should also be expected to delete it from any back-up of the information on that system, and the parties may prefer for this to be made explicit as part of the deletion obligation.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a74840">
            <identifier>12.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Data protection</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a778299" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Data protection</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000035" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on data protection, and the appropriate clauses to be inserted here, see <internal.reference refid="a549452"><ital>Drafting note, Data protection</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a105670">
              <identifier>12.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[INSERT APPROPRIATE DATA PROTECTION CLAUSES].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a573169">
            <identifier>13.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Force majeure</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a85522" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Force majeure</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000036" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-107-3808" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Force majeure</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a226743" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Force majeure</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a149609">
              <para>
                <paratext>Neither party shall be liable for any delay or failure in the performance of its obligations for so long as and to the extent that such delay or failure results from events, circumstances or causes beyond its reasonable control. If the period of delay or non-performance continues for [NUMBER] [days], the party not affected may terminate this agreement by giving [not less than [NUMBER] days'] written notice to the affected party.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a861213">
            <identifier>14.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Assignment</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a991980" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Assignment</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000037" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="5-107-3823" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Assignment and other dealings</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a120126" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Assignment and other dealings</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a448686">
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement is personal to the parties and neither party shall assign, transfer, mortgage, charge, subcontract, declare a trust of or deal in any other manner with any of its rights and obligations under this agreement [without the prior written consent of the other party (which is not to be unreasonably withheld or delayed)].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a949254">
            <identifier>15.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Waiver</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a259014" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Waiver</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000038" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="0-107-3806" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Waiver</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a947318" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Waiver</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a117566">
              <identifier>15.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A waiver of any right or remedy is only effective if given in writing [and shall not be deemed a waiver of any subsequent right or remedy].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a450898">
              <identifier>15.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A delay or failure to exercise, or the single or partial exercise of, any right or remedy does not waive that or any other right or remedy, nor does it prevent or restrict the further exercise of that or any other right or remedy.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a606956">
            <identifier>16.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Notice</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a438005" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Notice</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000039" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="5-107-3842" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clauses, Notices</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>See also <link href="3-107-3843" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Notice clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Care should be taken to ensure the approach in this notice clause aligns with the approach taken in <internal.reference refid="a543047"><ital>clause 1.10</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a587544">
              <identifier>16.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Any notice given to a party under or in connection with this agreement shall be in writing and shall be:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a133975">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>delivered by hand or by pre-paid first-class post or other next working day delivery service at its registered office (if a company) or its principal place of business (in any other case)[; or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a362879">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>sent by email to the following addresses (or an address substituted in writing by the party to be served):</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a327095">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Party 1: [ADDRESS].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a372392">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Party 2: [ADDRESS].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a547409">
              <identifier>16.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Any notice shall be deemed to have been received:</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a198971">
              <identifier>16.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>This <internal.reference refid="a606956"><ital>clause 16</ital></internal.reference> does not apply to the service of any proceedings or other documents in any legal action or, where applicable, any arbitration or other method of dispute resolution.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a978707">
            <identifier>17.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Entire agreement</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a373917" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Entire agreement</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000040" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to See also <link href="2-107-3834" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Entire agreement</ital></link>:</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a102696" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Entire agreement</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a809434">
              <identifier>17.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement constitutes the entire agreement between the parties and supersedes and extinguishes all previous and contemporaneous agreements, promises, assurances and understandings between them, whether written or oral, relating to its subject matter.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a589171">
              <identifier>17.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party acknowledges that in entering into this agreement it does not rely on[, and shall have no remedies in respect of,] any statement, representation, assurance or warranty (whether made innocently or negligently) that is not set out in this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a52557">
              <identifier>17.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party agrees that it shall have no claim for innocent or negligent misrepresentation [or negligent misstatement] based on any statement in this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a145564">
            <identifier>18.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Variation</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a138928" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Variation</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000041" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="3-107-3838" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Variation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a436667" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Variation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a895848">
              <para>
                <paratext>No variation of this agreement shall be effective unless it is in writing and signed by the parties (or their authorised representatives).</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a419234">
            <identifier>19.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Severance</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a583499" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Severance</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000042" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="9-107-3840" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Severance</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a117161" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Severance</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a656170">
              <identifier>19.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If any provision or part-provision of this agreement is or becomes invalid, illegal or unenforceable, it shall be deemed deleted, but that shall not affect the validity and enforceability of the rest of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a1051379">
              <identifier>19.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If any provision or part-provision of this agreement is deemed deleted under <internal.reference refid="a656170"><ital>clause 19.1</ital></internal.reference> the parties shall negotiate in good faith to agree a replacement provision that, to the greatest extent possible, achieves the intended commercial result of the original provision.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a344464">
            <identifier>20.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>No partnership or agency</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a807806" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>No partnership or agency</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000043" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="4-107-3814" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, No partnership or agency</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a358774" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: No partnership or agency</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a803887">
              <identifier>20.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Nothing in this agreement is intended to, or shall be deemed to, establish any partnership or joint venture between any of the parties, constitute any party the agent of another party, or authorise any party to make or enter into any commitments for or on behalf of any other party [except as expressly provided in clause[s] [NUMBER(S)]].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a455448">
              <identifier>20.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party confirms it is acting on its own behalf and not for the benefit of any other person.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a156246">
            <identifier>21.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Third-party rights</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a106884" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Third-party rights</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000044" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-107-3846" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Third party rights</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a867788" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Third party rights</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a341873">
              <identifier>21.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[Unless it expressly states otherwise, this <bold>OR </bold>This] agreement does not give rise to any rights under the Contracts (Rights of Third Parties) Act 1999 to enforce any term of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a740851">
              <identifier>21.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The rights of the parties to rescind or vary this agreement are not subject to the consent of any other person.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a534359">
            <identifier>22.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Rights and remedies</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a957247" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Rights and remedies</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000045" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="2-203-0725" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Rights and remedies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a778211" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Rights and remedies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a420341">
              <para>
                <paratext>[Except as expressly provided in this agreement, the <bold>OR</bold> The] rights and remedies provided under this agreement are in addition to, and not exclusive of, any rights or remedies provided by law.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a284422">
            <identifier>23.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Governing law</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a722356" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Governing law</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000046" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="8-107-3850" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Governing law</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a742310" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Governing law</ital></link></paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>See also:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="4-107-3852" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Governing law and jurisdiction clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="0-107-3646#a683835" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Supply contracts: overview: Choice of law and jurisdiction</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a728992">
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement and any dispute or claim arising out of or in connection with it or its subject matter or formation (including non-contractual disputes or claims) shall be governed by and construed in accordance with the law of England and Wales.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a959136">
            <identifier>24.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Jurisdiction</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a199245" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Jurisdiction</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000047" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For information, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="9-522-6848" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Jurisdiction</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a783056" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Jurisdiction</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a250178">
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party irrevocably agrees that the courts of England and Wales shall have [exclusive <bold>OR </bold>non-exclusive] jurisdiction to settle any dispute or claim (including non-contractual disputes or claims) arising out of or in connection with this agreement or its subject matter or formation</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
        </operative>
        <testimonium default="true" wording="contract">
          <para>
            <paratext>This agreement has been entered into on the date stated at the beginning of it.</paratext>
          </para>
        </testimonium>
        <disclosure.schedule>
          <schedule id="a143290">
            <identifier>Schedule 1</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Key details</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a162062" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Key details</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000048" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Commencement Date of the agreement, the equipment to be maintained, the Location of the Maintained Equipment, the fixed Standard Maintenance Fee, and the rates applied to the Additional Services should be set out in this Schedule.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <part id="a602587">
              <identifier>Part 1</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Commencement Date</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part id="a784170">
              <identifier>Part 2</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Maintained Equipment</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part id="a239422">
              <identifier>Part 3</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Location</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer's premises located at [INSERT].</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>OR</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <clause id="a000049">
                <para>
                  <paratext>
                    <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
                      <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="33"/>
                        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="33"/>
                        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="33"/>
                        <tbody>
                          <row>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para align="left">
                                <paratext>#</paratext>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para align="left">
                                <paratext>Maintained Equipment</paratext>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para align="left">
                                <paratext>Location</paratext>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                          </row>
                          <row>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para>
                                <paratext/>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para>
                                <paratext/>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para>
                                <paratext/>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                          </row>
                          <row>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para>
                                <paratext/>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para>
                                <paratext/>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry valign="top">
                              <para>
                                <paratext/>
                              </para>
                            </entry>
                          </row>
                        </tbody>
                      </tgroup>
                    </table>
                  </paratext>
                </para>
              </clause>
            </part>
            <part id="a873665">
              <identifier>Part 4</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Standard Maintenance Fees</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part id="a439776">
              <identifier>Part 5</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Additional Services Rates</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part condition="optional" id="a462774">
              <identifier>Part 6</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Supported Software and terms of support</headtext>
              </head>
              <drafting.note id="a928064" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Supported software and terms of support (optional)</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000050" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If software maintenance services are being provided (see <internal.reference refid="a772513"><ital>Drafting note, Software maintenance services (optional)</ital></internal.reference>) then this <internal.reference refid="a462774"><ital>Part 6</ital></internal.reference> will need to be completed with the details of such services, including any relevant support or end of life policies. Note you will need to provide, or link to, an appropriate end user licence at <internal.reference refid="a251354"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>, see <internal.reference refid="a772513"><ital>Drafting note, Software maintenance services (optional)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For example software maintenance agreements, see <link href="7-107-4807" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Software maintenance agreement (pro-customer)</ital></link> and <link href="1-107-4810" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Software maintenance agreement (pro-supplier)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </part>
          </schedule>
          <schedule id="a741444">
            <identifier>Schedule 2</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Service levels</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a367598" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Service levels</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000051" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>Where Service Levels and Service Credits are to be applied to the Supplier's performance of its obligations pursuant to this agreement, these should be included here (see <internal.reference refid="a987618"><ital>Drafting note, Maintenance Services</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a393509"><ital>Drafting note, Service Levels</ital></internal.reference>). Where not relevant, this Schedule should be removed.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <part id="a858939">
              <identifier>Part 1</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Response Times</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part id="a1015113">
              <identifier>Part 2</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Fix Times</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part condition="optional" id="a812168">
              <identifier>Part 3</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Service Levels</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part condition="optional" id="a421005">
              <identifier>Part 4</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Service Credits</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
          </schedule>
        </disclosure.schedule>
        <disclosure.schedule>
          <schedule id="a985480">
            <identifier>Schedule 3</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>MANDATORY POLICIES</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a475553" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Mandatory Policies: list and attach?</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000052" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For a discussion of whether or not the mandatory policies should also be attached to the agreement, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-618-9498" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Compliance with laws and policies: Schedule of Mandatory Policies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <para>
              <paratext>[LIST [AND ATTACH] THE MANDATORY POLICIES HERE]</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Mandatory Policies are:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Modern Slavery and Human Trafficking Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Corporate and Social Responsibility Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Data and Privacy Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Ethics and Anti-Bribery Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Expenses Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Cybersecurity Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </schedule>
          <schedule condition="optional" id="a251354">
            <identifier>Schedule 4</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>SOFTWARE EULA</headtext>
            </head>
          </schedule>
          <schedule id="a346595">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>[INCLUDE [OR LINK TO] ANY RELEVANT SOFTWARE EULA HERE].</headtext>
            </head>
          </schedule>
        </disclosure.schedule>
        <signature default="true" pagebreak="true" signaturemessage="no">
          <para>
            <paratext>
              <table frame="none" pgwide="1">
                <tgroup cols="3">
                  <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="33"/>
                  <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="33"/>
                  <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="33"/>
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Signed by [NAME OF DIRECTOR]  for and on behalf of [NAME OF SUPPLIER]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>....................</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Director</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry nameend="3" namest="1" valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Signed by [NAME OF DIRECTOR]  for and on behalf of [NAME OF CUSTOMER]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>....................</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Director</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry nameend="3" namest="1" valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
            </paratext>
          </para>
        </signature>
      </body>
      <rev.history>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Review (February 2025)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20250211</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000001" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have updated this resource following a review by our external contributors.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Review (February 2023)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20230208</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000002" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have updated this resource following a review by our external contributors.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Review (June 2022)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20220616</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000003" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have reviewed and updated this agreement generally, including in relation to the tax clause (see <internal.reference refid="a731266"><ital>clause 7.6</ital></internal.reference>) and the boilerplate provisions.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Review to add reference to software and firmware updates (August 2021)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20210805</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000004" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have updated this resource to cover software and firmware updates and have made other general updates to the boilerplate.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Review following the end of the UK-EU transition period (May 2021)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20210524</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000005" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have reviewed this resource in light of the end of the UK-EU transition period.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Network and Information Systems Regulations 2018</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20190513</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000006" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>Updated to take into account these regulations</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>New materials on Brexit and IP (March 2019)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20190314</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000007" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have added links to various materials on Brexit relevant to this resource.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Reviewed February 2014</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20140220</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Click here to enter the Resource History Author</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000008" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>This document was reviewed as part of ongoing maintenance in February 2014.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
      </rev.history>
    </standard.doc>
  </n-docbody>
</n-document>