<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><n-document xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" guid="0" synced="true" validated="true">
  <n-docbody>
    <standard.doc precedenttype="agreement">
      <prelim>
        <product.name>product.name0</product.name>
        <title>Equipment maintenance agreement</title>
        <author><link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/Browse/Home/About/OurteamCommercial" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practical Law Commercial</ital></link></author>
        <resource.type>Standard documents</resource.type>
        <juris>juris0</juris>
        <juris>juris1</juris>
      </prelim>
      <abstract>
        <para>
          <paratext>A B2B agreement in which the supplier agrees to provide a maintenance and support service for equipment. The agreement is drafted to be broadly neutral between the parties.</paratext>
        </para>
      </abstract>
      <toc.identifier hasToc="true"/>
      <body>
        <drafting.note id="a229984" jurisdiction="">
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>About this document</headtext>
          </head>
          <division id="a000001" level="1">
            <para>
              <paratext>This document is an agreement for the maintenance of equipment in a business-to-business (B2B) context. The agreement is drafted to be broadly neutral between the parties.</paratext>
            </para>
          </division>
          <division id="a207903" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Alternative agreements</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>Practical Law offers a range of services agreements. See <link href="w-003-2270" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Which Practical Law services agreement template should I use?</ital></link>.</paratext>
            </para>
          </division>
          <division id="a577318" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Legal issues</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>We have set out below some of the key legal issues that typically arise when drafting an agreement for the maintenance of equipment in the B2B context.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>For issues generally when considering drafting a services agreement, see <link href="5-201-9043" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Checklist, Preliminary considerations when entering services arrangements</ital></link>.</paratext>
            </para>
            <division id="a153881" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Relationship with hire agreement (if applicable)</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>If the supplier of the services is also hiring the equipment under the terms of a separate agreement, the drafter will need to consider the relationship between the two agreements. For example:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Are the agreements co-terminous?</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Are the parties' respective obligations under the two agreements consistent?</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Should service credits be on account of future hire fees?</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>For an equipment hire agreement in the B2B context, see standard documents:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="w-023-4533" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Equipment hire agreement (pro-lessor)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="w-023-4985" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Equipment hire agreement (pro-lessee)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
            </division>
            <division id="a788944" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Implied terms</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The <link href="3-507-0623" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982</ital></link> (SGSA) applies to B2B contracts for the supply of services or for works and materials. Part II of the SGSA implies the following three terms into such contracts:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier will carry out the service with reasonable care and skill (<link href="2-507-0628" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 13</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the time for the services is not fixed by the contract, left to be fixed in a manner agreed in the contract or determined by the parties' course of dealing, then there is an implied term that the supplier will carry out the services within a reasonable time. What is "reasonable" is a question of fact (<link href="0-508-2613" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 14</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the price of the services is not determined by the contract, left to be determined in a manner agreed in the contract or determined by the course of dealing between the parties, then there is an implied term that the customer will pay the supplier a reasonable charge. What is "reasonable" is a question of fact (<link href="7-507-2922" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 15</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>In addition, Part I of the SGSA implies the following terms in relation to goods transferred under a contract for services (for example, spare parts or materials used as part of the services, such as in contracts for work and materials):</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The seller has title, the buyer will enjoy quiet possession and the goods are free from encumbrances (<link href="9-507-2935" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 2</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The goods will correspond with their description (<link href="4-508-2593" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 3</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The goods will be of satisfactory quality and fit for purpose (<link href="3-508-2598" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 4</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The goods will correspond with their sample (<link href="7-508-2600" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 5</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>These implied terms do not apply in relation to the finished output of the services (such as any deliverables).</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>The <link href="5-107-7449" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977</ital></link> (UCTA) controls attempts to exclude these implied terms or limit liability for their breach as follows:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Exclusions or limitation in relation to the implied terms as to reasonable skill and care, correspondence with description, satisfactory quality, fitness for purpose and correspondence with sample must be reasonable (<link href="4-506-5560" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 2</ital></link> and <link href="6-507-2871" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 7(1A)</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Exclusions or limitations in relation to implied terms as to title, quiet possession and freedom from encumbrances are void (<link href="6-507-2871" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 7(3A)</ital></link>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
            </division>
            <division id="a893858" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Limiting liability</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>Like any other services agreement, the limitation of liability clause in an equipment maintenance agreement is likely to be a key area of negotiation. The clause should broadly reflect the value of the agreement and the parties needs to be comfortable with the financial exposure of the liability caps (see <internal.reference refid="a618544"><ital>clause 12</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>If the supplier intends to use this standard document as its standard terms, a clause limiting liability for breach of contract or by which it claims to be entitled to render a contractual performance substantially different from what was reasonably expected of it, or to render no performance at all, will only be valid if it is reasonable (<link href="5-505-8743" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 3</ital></link>,<ital> UCTA</ital>).</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For a more detailed discussion of limitation of liability clauses, see practice notes:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="2-520-5359" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: drafting and negotiating</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="w-006-5549" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: interpretation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="9-617-5230" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: statutory and common law controls on limitation clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
            </division>
            <division id="a729641" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Machine-generated data</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement envisages the supplier providing a regular "preventative" service and then corrective and emergency services as necessary. Increasingly, equipment support agreements are driven by machine-generated data, so that the supplier only inspects the equipment when prompted to do so by the data. This has the virtue of enabling a more focused service and reducing the number of call-outs (and therefore costs savings). However, if there is machine-generated data, the parties should address:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Ownership rights in the data.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Restrictions on the use the supplier can make of the data.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Confidentiality and security measures.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Rights to access the data.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
            </division>
            <division id="a648310" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Supply chain issues</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>Ensuring ethical practice throughout the supply chain is an issue of increasing importance to business customers. For a discussion of the key areas that could give rise to supply chain compliance requirements in the UK, including environmental, social and governance (ESG) matters, and information security and cyber security issues, see <link href="w-027-3652" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Supply chain compliance</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <division id="a604561" level="3">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Modern Slavery Act 2015</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Commercial organisations carrying on business in the UK with a global annual turnover of £36 million or more must complete a slavery and human trafficking statement for each financial year, setting out the steps they have taken to ensure that there is no slavery or human trafficking in its business or in its supply chains (<link href="7-608-3825" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 54</ital></link><ital>, Modern Slavery Act 2015</ital> (MSA)). Including anti-slavery and trafficking obligations in its contracts (through business policies or otherwise) is one of the steps an organisation can take.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on the MSA and to access materials dealing with the MSA, see <link href="8-618-8657" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Modern Slavery Act 2015 toolkit</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a844948" level="3">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Bribery Act 2010</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Of particular concern to businesses in a commercial context is the corporate offence of failure to prevent bribery by an associated person. A commercial organisation will be guilty of an offence if a person associated with it bribes another person intending to obtain or retain business for the commercial organisation, or to obtain or retain an advantage in the conduct of business for the commercial organisation (<ital>section 7</ital>, <link href="1-503-8422" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Bribery Act 2010</ital></link>). The commercial organisation has a defence if it can show that it had adequate procedures in place to prevent bribery by its associated persons.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For further information and an example of an anti-bribery clause, see <link href="6-503-5299" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Anti-bribery clause (short-form)</ital></link>. For background and all Practical Law materials on the Bribery Act, see <link href="9-503-9451" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Bribery Act 2010 toolkit</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a351418" level="3">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Network security</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The <link href="w-014-4419" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Network and Information Systems Regulations 2018 (SI 1018/506)</ital></link> (NISR) apply to "essential service providers" (electricity, water supply, gas and transport) and "relevant digital service providers" (search engines, online marketplaces and cloud computing service providers). NISR require these entities to ensure that they have appropriate technical and organisational measures in place to manage the risks to the security of the network and information systems on which their services rely, and to notify the competent authority within a specified time frame if there is an incident which significantly impacts the continuity of its services.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A customer who is subject to NISR may want to flow down the security measures as required by NISR to the supplier. For suitable wording, see <link anchor="a228443" href="0-202-4551" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Outsourcing agreement: long form: clause 37</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </division>
          </division>
          <division id="a879287" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Drafting assumptions</headtext>
            </head>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Hire agreement</bold>. The supplier is not also hiring the equipment to the customer.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Data protection</bold>. The agreement does not involve the processing or sharing of personal data.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Machine-generated data. </bold>There is no machine-generated data.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Intellectual property rights</bold>. The agreement does not involve the transfer of any intellectual property rights.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>TUPE</bold>. TUPE does not apply either on entry to or exit from the agreement. See <link href="8-204-4041" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, TUPE (3): service provision changes</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>UK companies</bold>. The customer and the supplier are companies incorporated in England and Wales. The customer is not a public body, so the UK rules relating to public procurement will not apply. See <link href="9-386-0686" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Procurement Act 2023: overview</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Business-to-business (B2B)</bold>. The parties are dealing with each other in the course of their respective businesses (meaning that the UK rules protecting consumers will not apply).</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>Governing law</bold>. The agreement is subject to the law of England Wales</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </division>
        </drafting.note>
        <intro default="true">
          <intro.date>This agreement is dated [DATE]</intro.date>
        </intro>
        <parties>
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>PARTIES</headtext>
          </head>
          <party executionmethod="contract" id="a149737" status="company">
            <identifier>(1)</identifier>
            <defn.item>
              <defn>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[FULL COMPANY NAME] incorporated and registered in England and Wales with company number [NUMBER] whose registered office is at [REGISTERED OFFICE ADDRESS]</paratext>
                </para>
              </defn>
              <defn.term>Supplier</defn.term>
            </defn.item>
          </party>
          <party executionmethod="contract" id="a181991" status="company">
            <identifier>(2)</identifier>
            <defn.item>
              <defn>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[FULL COMPANY NAME] incorporated and registered in England and Wales with company number [NUMBER] whose registered office is at [REGISTERED OFFICE ADDRESS]</paratext>
                </para>
              </defn>
              <defn.term>Customer</defn.term>
            </defn.item>
          </party>
        </parties>
        <recitals>
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>BACKGROUND</headtext>
          </head>
          <drafting.note id="a749909" jurisdiction="">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Background</headtext>
            </head>
            <division id="a000002" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>Also known as recitals, the background section does not form part of the operative provisions. In cases of dispute, it may be used as an interpretative guide where a clause is considered obscure or ambiguous. For more information, see <link anchor="a41966" href="0-107-4877" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: structure and terms of commercial contracts: Background, recitals, or preamble</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>Amend or supplement this section as appropriate to reflect the purpose and background of the agreement, or alternatively omit the background section if the agreement is simple and its purpose obvious.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </drafting.note>
          <clause id="a468907">
            <identifier>(A)</identifier>
            <para>
              <paratext>[The Supplier has supplied certain equipment to the Customer. <bold>OR </bold>The Customer has purchased certain equipment which will require specialist maintenance.]</paratext>
            </para>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a838348">
            <identifier>(B)</identifier>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Customer wishes the Supplier to provide a maintenance and support service in relation to the equipment and the Supplier is willing to supply the services on the terms set out in agreement.</paratext>
            </para>
          </clause>
        </recitals>
        <operative xrefname="clause">
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>AGREED TERMS</headtext>
          </head>
          <clause id="a238331">
            <identifier>1.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Interpretation</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a416942" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Interpretation</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000003" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For information on definitions and interpretation, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="5-107-3795" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Interpretation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <para>
              <paratext>The following definitions and rules of interpretation apply in this agreement.</paratext>
            </para>
            <subclause1 id="a563144">
              <identifier>1.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Definitions:</paratext>
              </para>
              <defn.item id="a827200">
                <defn.term>Additional Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any Emergency Maintenance or Excluded Maintenance performed by the Supplier under this agreement.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a145022">
                <defn.term>Additional Services Charges</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the charges payable in consideration of the provision of any Additional Services, to be calculated in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a344459"><ital>Part 2</ital></internal.reference> of Schedule 4.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a934142">
                <defn.term>Applicable Laws</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the laws of England and Wales and any other laws or regulations, regulatory policies, guidelines or industry codes which apply to the provision of the Services.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a849677">
                <defn.term>Business Day</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>a day, other than a Saturday, Sunday or public holiday in England, when banks in London are open for business.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a349177">
                <defn.term>Business Hours</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold> </bold><defn.term>t</defn.term>he period from [9.00 am to 5.00 pm] on any Business Day.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a309318" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Business Hours</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000004" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Check that these suggested hours are suitable.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a596294">
                <defn.term>Charges</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The charges to be paid for the Services under <internal.reference refid="a386761"><ital>clause 9</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a585593">
                <defn.term>Commencement Date</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>[[DATE] <bold>OR</bold> the date of this agreement].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a295377">
                <defn.term>Consultancy Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the advisory services<defn.term> </defn.term>to be provided pursuant to<defn.term> </defn.term><internal.reference refid="a557319"><ital>clause 4.8</ital></internal.reference><defn.term>.</defn.term></paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a421565">
                <defn.term>Consultancy Services Charges</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the charges to be paid in consideration of the provision of any Consultancy Services, to be calculated in accordance with<defn.term> </defn.term><internal.reference refid="a336351"><ital>Part 3</ital></internal.reference><defn.term> </defn.term>of Schedule 4.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a975240">
                <defn.term>Consumables</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>non-durable items used in the operation of the Equipment[ including those items listed in Schedule [SCHEDULE NUMBER];]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a851065" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Consumables</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000005" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>List the consumables if possible, if necessary in a separate schedule. For example, for a printer, the consumables may be toner and ink.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a865054">
                <defn.term>Contract Year</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>a 12-month period starting on the Commencement Date and on each anniversary of the Commencement Date.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a429760" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Contract Year</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000006" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The term "Contract Year" is used in <internal.reference refid="a591461"><ital>clause 12.3</ital></internal.reference> (cap on supplier's liability) and <internal.reference refid="a418877"><ital>clause 12.5</ital></internal.reference> (cap on customer's liability).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a160610">
                <defn.term>control</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>has the meaning given in section 1124 of the Corporation Tax Act 2010, and the expression <bold>change of control</bold> shall be interpreted accordingly.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a629926">
                <defn.term>Corrective Maintenance</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a124288"><ital>clause 4.4</ital></internal.reference>:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>making any adjustments to the Equipment; or</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>replacing any parts or components of the Equipment,</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in each case, as required to restore the Equipment to Good Working Order.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a975780">
                <defn.term>Critical Service Failure</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>an event where the Supplier's performance of any of the Services falls to, or below, any of the Critical Service Levels for that Service.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a862930">
                <defn.term>Critical Service Levels</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>has the meaning given in <internal.reference refid="a870479"><ital>Part 4</ital></internal.reference> of Schedule 3.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a924152" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Critical Service Levels (optional definition)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000007" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The definition of Critical Service Levels refers to the point at which the supplier's failure to provide an aspect of the service in accordance with the required service level becomes critical. If the supplier's performance of the services falls to this level, the customer may wish to have the ability to exercise its termination rights (see <internal.reference refid="a305128"><ital>clause 14.4(a)</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The Critical Service Levels must be appropriate to the equipment in question and the customer requirements.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a796214">
                <defn.term>Emergency Maintenance</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a639714"><ital>clause 4.5</ital></internal.reference>:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>making any adjustments to the Equipment; or</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>replacing any parts or components of the Equipment,</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in each case, as required to restore the Equipment to Good Working Order.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a160136">
                <defn.term>Equipment</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the equipment specified in <internal.reference refid="a187097"><ital>Schedule 1</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a586109">
                <defn.term>Excluded Causes</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext/>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>a defect in the design of the Equipment;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>faulty materials or workmanship in the manufacture of the Equipment;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>the use of the Equipment with equipment or materials not supplied or approved [in writing] by the Supplier [or the manufacturer];</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>any maintenance, alteration, modification or adjustment performed by persons other than the Supplier or its employees or agents unless approved [in writing] by the Supplier;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>the Customer or third party moving the Equipment unless approved [in writing] by the Supplier;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>the use of the Equipment in breach of any of the provisions of the agreement under which the Equipment was supplied;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>a failure, interruption or surge in the electrical power or its related infrastructure connected to the Equipment;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>a failure or malfunctioning of the air conditioning or other environmental controls required for the normal operation of the Equipment, or an error or omission in the correct use of that air conditioning or other environmental controls by the Customer; or</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>the Customer's neglect or misuse of the Equipment.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a535206" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Excluded causes</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000008" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>If the supplier has manufactured the equipment then the first two exclusions may be inappropriate.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Consider also whether each exclusion is applicable to the particular equipment. For example, the restriction on moving the equipment may be inappropriate for other than large items of equipment.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a730370">
                <defn.term>Excluded Maintenance</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any Maintenance Services required to restore any defect or malfunctioning or failure in the Equipment to Good Working Order where the defect or malfunctioning or failure results from or is caused by any of the Excluded Causes.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a192460">
                <defn.term>Extended Term</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>has the meaning given in <internal.reference refid="a824363"><ital>clause 2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a912801">
                <defn.term>Fix Time</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the applicable fix time set out in <internal.reference refid="a1015113"><ital>Part 2</ital></internal.reference> of Schedule 3.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a438304">
                <defn.term>Good Industry Practice</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold> </bold>the exercise of that degree of skill, care, prudence, efficiency, foresight and timeliness as would be expected from a leading company within the relevant industry or business sector.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a333006" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Good Industry Practice</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000009" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The customer may seek the higher standard of "Best Industry Practice", defined in <link href="0-202-4551" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Outsourcing agreement: long form</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a482182">
                <defn.term>Good Working Order</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>[operating in accordance with the applicable specification of the manufacturer of the Equipment <bold>OR </bold>operating in accordance with the Operating Manual.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a578961">
                <defn.term>Group</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in relation to a company, that company, any subsidiary or holding company [from time to time <bold>OR</bold> at the date of this agreement] of that company[, and any subsidiary [from time to time <bold>OR</bold> at the date of this agreement] of a holding company of that company].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a507073">
                <defn.term>Initial Term</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>has the meaning given in <internal.reference refid="a824363"><ital>clause 2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a782719">
                <defn.term>Inspection Fee</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold> </bold>the sum set out in <internal.reference refid="a551145"><ital>Part 4</ital></internal.reference> of Schedule 4 for the Supplier's initial inspection of the Equipment pursuant to <internal.reference refid="a552125"><ital>clause 3.1</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a599941">
                <defn.term>Location</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold> </bold>the location of the Equipment as specified in <internal.reference refid="a296072"><ital>Schedule 2</ital></internal.reference>, or any other location as may be agreed by the parties in writing from time to time.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a667792">
                <defn.term>Maintenance Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold> </bold>Routine Maintenance, Corrective Maintenance and Emergency Maintenance.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a273178">
                <defn.term>Mandatory Policies</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Customer's business policies [and codes] [attached <bold>OR</bold> listed] in <internal.reference refid="a660852"><ital>Schedule 5</ital></internal.reference>, as amended by notification to the Supplier from time to time<defn.term>.</defn.term></paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a417063" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Mandatory Policies (optional definition)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000010" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a257869"><ital>Clause 11</ital></internal.reference> obliges the supplier to comply with the customer's mandatory policies (see <internal.reference refid="a327275"><ital>Drafting note, Compliance with laws and policies (optional wording)</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a839623">
                <defn.term>Response Time</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the applicable response time set out in <internal.reference refid="a745564"><ital>Part 1</ital></internal.reference> of Schedule 3.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><bold>Routine Maintenance</bold>:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="loweralpha">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>testing that the Equipment is functional;</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>making any adjustments as may be required to ensure the Equipment remains in Good Working Order; and</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>replacing any Consumables that require replacing,</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a976016"><ital>clause 4.2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a783731">
                <defn.term>Service Credits</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the sums attributable to a Service Failure as specified in <internal.reference refid="a421005"><ital>Part 5</ital></internal.reference><defn.term> </defn.term>of Schedule 3.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a697939">
                <defn.term>Service Failure</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>a failure by the Supplier to deliver any part of the Services in accordance with the Service Levels.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a640906" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Service Failure</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000011" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Service Failures are defined as applying to a failure by the supplier to perform a service in accordance with an applicable service level. The service level is the level of performance which must be achieved for the supplier to avoid paying any service credits. If the supplier's performance in relation to any element of the services falls below an applicable service level, service credits become payable. Service credits usually accrue on a graduated basis up to a minimum threshold. If the supplier's performance fails to meet that threshold, the customer may recover additional damages.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a302102">
                <defn.term>Service Levels</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the service levels to which the Services are to be provided, as set out in <internal.reference refid="a812168"><ital>Part 3</ital></internal.reference> of Schedule 3.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a545020" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Service Levels</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000012" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The service levels/service credits regime should focus on the key aspects of the service and reflect the customer's needs. For example, a service interruption during peak hours may have more serious consequences than an interruption occurring outside peak hours. See also <internal.reference refid="a625351"><ital>Drafting note, Service levels</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The agreement also includes an optional defined term "Critical Service Levels". If the supplier fails to meet the Critical Service Level an agreed number of times, the customer has the right to terminate (see <internal.reference refid="a305128"><ital>clause 14.4(a)</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a639169">
                <defn.term>Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Maintenance Services and the Consultancy Services.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a808515">
                <defn.term>Services Managers</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the managers appointed by the parties in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a925936"><ital>clause 4.10</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a505666"><ital>clause 7.6</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a699867">
                <defn.term>Spare Parts</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all spare components and subassemblies of the Equipment supplied for installation in the Equipment as part of the provision of the Services.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a800002" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Spare Parts</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000013" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>As with the definition of Equipment, consider whether this definition is wide enough. For example, should it cover parts that will be connected to the equipment but not actually installed in it? The definition deliberately says "supplied for installation" rather than "supplied and installed" so that the provisions of <internal.reference refid="a494885"><ital>clause 6.1</ital></internal.reference> (regarding payment for the spare parts) will apply in respect of parts supplied but not (yet, if ever) installed.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a990397">
                <defn.term>Standard Maintenance Charges</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the charges payable in consideration of the provision of the Routine Maintenance and Corrective Maintenance, to be calculated in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a292235"><ital>Part 1</ital></internal.reference> of Schedule 4, as varied from time in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a980636"><ital>clause 9.6</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a858903">
                <defn.term>Term</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Initial Term together with all Extended Terms.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a634972">
                <defn.term>VAT</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>value added tax [or any equivalent tax] chargeable in the UK [or elsewhere].]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a865121">
              <identifier>1.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Clause, Schedule and paragraph headings shall not affect the interpretation of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a671064">
              <identifier>1.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A <bold>person</bold> includes a natural person, corporate or unincorporated body (whether or not having separate legal personality.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a688812">
              <identifier>1.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Schedules form part of this agreement and shall have effect as if set out in full in the body of this agreement. Any reference to this agreement includes the Schedules.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a266870">
              <identifier>1.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to a <bold>company</bold> includes any company, corporation or other body corporate, wherever and however incorporated or established.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a738535">
              <identifier>1.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to a <bold>holding company</bold> or a <bold>subsidiary</bold> means a holding company or a subsidiary (as the case may be) as defined in section 1159 of the Companies Act 2006 [and a company shall be treated, for the purposes only of the membership requirement contained in sections 1159(1)(b) and (c), as a member of another company even if its shares in that other company are registered in the name of:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a226012">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>another person (or its nominee) by way of security or in connection with the taking of security; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a858323">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>its nominee].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext>[For the purposes of determining whether a limited liability partnership is a subsidiary of a company or another limited liability partnership, section 1159 of the Companies Act 2006 shall be interpreted so that: (a) references in sections 1159(1)(a) and (c) to voting rights are to the members' rights to vote on all or substantially all matters which are decided by a vote of the members of the limited liability partnership; and (b) the reference in section 1159(1)(b) to the right to appoint or remove a majority of its board of directors is to the right to appoint or remove members holding a majority of the voting rights.]</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a913327">
              <identifier>1.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Unless the context otherwise requires, words in the singular include the plural and in the plural include the singular.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a189061">
              <identifier>1.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Unless the context otherwise requires, a reference to one gender includes a reference to the other genders.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a577940">
              <identifier>1.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[Unless expressly provided otherwise in this agreement, a <bold>OR </bold>A] reference to legislation or a legislative provision is a reference to it as [amended, extended or re-enacted from time to time <bold>OR</bold> it is in force as at the date of this agreement].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a473037">
              <identifier>1.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[Unless expressly provided otherwise in this agreement, a <bold>OR </bold>A] reference to legislation or a legislative provision includes all subordinate legislation made [from time to time <bold>OR </bold>as at the date of this agreement] under that legislation or legislative provisions.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a865262">
              <identifier>1.11</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to <bold>writing</bold> or <bold>written</bold> excludes fax [and email <bold>OR</bold> but not email].</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a659590" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>In writing</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000014" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>On the meaning of "in writing" in commercial contracts, see <link anchor="a674860" href="w-014-8695" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, What does "in writing" mean?: Contractual requirements for communications in writing</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The parties will need to decide if email will constitute a form of writing. Check that the drafting relating to email notices in <internal.reference refid="a133341"><ital>clause 18.10(b)(iii)</ital></internal.reference> is consistent with the position in <internal.reference refid="a865262"><ital>clause 1.11</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a939038">
              <identifier>1.12</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>References to clauses and Schedules are to the clauses and Schedules of this agreement and references to paragraphs are to paragraphs of the relevant Schedule.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a456849">
              <identifier>1.13</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Any words following the terms <bold>including</bold>, <bold>include</bold>, <bold>in particular</bold>, <bold>for example</bold> or any similar expression shall be interpreted as illustrative and shall not limit the sense of the words preceding those terms.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a824363">
            <identifier>2.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Commencement and duration</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a126630" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Commencement and duration</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000015" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause provides for an initial term which is automatically extended for multiple fixed terms. For more information on this clause and alternative drafting, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="2-381-1963" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Commencement and duration</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a404369" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Commencement</ital></link> and <link anchor="a238154" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Duration</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a878765" numbering="none">
            <para>
              <paratext>This agreement commences on the Commencement Date. Unless terminated earlier in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a789858"><ital>clause 3.5</ital></internal.reference>, <internal.reference refid="a443046"><ital>clause 14</ital></internal.reference> or this clause, this agreement continues [until [DATE] <bold>OR</bold> for [PERIOD]] (<bold>Initial Term</bold>) and automatically extends for [PERIOD] (<bold>Extended Term</bold>) at the end of the Initial Term and at the end of each Extended Term. Either party may give written notice to the other party, not later than [PERIOD] before the end of the Initial Term or the relevant Extended Term, to terminate this agreement at the end of the Initial Term or the relevant Extended Term, as the case may be.</paratext>
            </para>
          </clause>
          <clause condition="optional" id="a779820">
            <identifier>3.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Inspection of the Equipment</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a560251" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Inspection of the equipment (optional wording)</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000016" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a779820"><ital>Clause 3</ital></internal.reference> provides a mechanism for the supplier to check that the equipment is in good working order at the start of the lifetime of the agreement. It envisages the payment of an initial inspection fee. If remedial work is required, the supplier provides a quotation for the work which, if rejected by the customer, will cause the agreement to terminate automatically.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a552125">
              <identifier>3.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Inspection.</bold> On or shortly after the Commencement Date and upon payment by the Customer of the Inspection Fee, the Supplier shall carry out an inspection of the Equipment to determine whether it is in Good Working Order.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a437812">
              <identifier>3.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Good Working Order Certificate</bold>. If the Supplier finds the Equipment to be in Good Working Order, it shall promptly issue a certificate to the Customer confirming this.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a690156">
              <identifier>3.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Quotation to restore to Good Working Order.</bold> If the Supplier finds the Equipment not to be in Good Working Order, it shall issue a quotation to the Customer for the work and parts required to restore the Equipment to Good Working Order.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a937310">
              <identifier>3.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Acceptance of quotation.</bold> If the Customer accepts the quotation referred to in <internal.reference refid="a690156"><ital>clause 3.3</ital></internal.reference>, the Supplier shall carry out the work in accordance with the quotation, to the standard set out in <internal.reference refid="a178416"><ital>clause 10.1</ital></internal.reference>. Upon completion of the work it shall submit its invoice for the work and upon payment of that invoice it shall issue a certificate to the Customer confirming that the Equipment is in Good Working Order.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a789858">
              <identifier>3.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Automatic termination on rejection of quotation.</bold> If the Customer refuses the quotation, this agreement shall terminate automatically and without notice and without liability to either party, save that the Supplier shall be entitled to retain the Inspection Fee.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a930451">
            <identifier>4.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Supplier's obligations</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a699002" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Supplier's obligations</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000017" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause sets out the principal obligations of the supplier relating to the services (see also <internal.reference refid="a788944"><ital>Drafting note, Implied terms</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                </para>
                <division id="a909831" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Maintenance services</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This clause sets out three main types of maintenance services to be provided by the supplier under this agreement. These are:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Routine maintenance</bold>. This is where the supplier attends the customer's premises at a prearranged time to assess the equipment with the objective of pre-empting any potential problems, replacing consumables when necessary, and also repairing any equipment which has failed but the failure has gone unnoticed or which is not operating as it should. Consider how frequently the supplier will be required to carry out these pre-emptive visits.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Corrective maintenance</bold>. This is where the supplier attends the customer's premises to repair the equipment in response to a request from the customer. The key distinction between corrective maintenance and emergency maintenance is that corrective maintenance is performed during normal business hours and is subject to the standard maintenance charges. The parties will need to consider and agree the level of commitment that the supplier will give in relation to any response time and fix time service levels.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Emergency maintenance</bold>. This is where the supplier attends the customer's premises outside normal business hours and, as such, is charged at the additional services rates.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Not all agreements for the maintenance of equipment are the same, so the drafter is likely to need to amend the clauses specifying the supplier's maintenance obligation in this <internal.reference refid="a930451"><ital>clause 4</ital></internal.reference> to some degree.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
                <division id="a346367" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Consultancy services</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The services also include a consultancy element (<internal.reference refid="a557319"><ital>clause 4.8</ital></internal.reference>). Delete this clause (and associated definitions) if the supplier will not be providing a consultancy service in respect of the equipment.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
                <division id="a856384" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Mandatory policies</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>In addition, <internal.reference refid="a257869"><ital>clause 11</ital></internal.reference> obliges the supplier to comply with applicable laws and the customer's mandatory policies.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
                <division id="a565651" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Change control</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>A simple maintenance agreement is unlikely to require the inclusion of a change control clause or other mechanism for varying the service description. If one is necessary, see <link href="w-012-9297" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Change control</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a997920">
              <identifier>4.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Supply of Services.</bold> During the Term, the Supplier shall supply the Services to the Customer.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a976016">
              <identifier>4.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Supplier's representative.</bold> A representative of the Supplier shall attend the Location [every [NUMBER] weeks <bold>OR </bold>at such frequency as is reasonably determined by the Supplier [but not more than once in every [PERIOD]] to perform the Routine Maintenance. The Supplier's representative shall perform the Routine Maintenance during Business Hours at such times as may be agreed in advance between the Customer and the Supplier from time to time.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a962469">
              <identifier>4.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Equipment malfunction.</bold> If the Supplier's representative discovers that the Equipment is defective or is malfunctioning or has failed or is not otherwise in Good Working Order during the course of the Routine Maintenance the representative will use all reasonable endeavours to repair it during that visit at the Location. If that is not reasonably practicable (or it is not reasonably practicable to do so during Business Hours) the Supplier's representative shall either arrange for a further visit to the Location within Business Hours to complete the repair, or [remove <bold>OR </bold>arrange for the removal of] the Equipment (or part of the Equipment, if applicable) for repair off-site.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a124288">
              <identifier>4.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Corrective Maintenance.</bold> On the Customer informing the Supplier that the Equipment is defective or is malfunctioning or has failed or is not otherwise in Good Working Order, the Supplier shall [use all reasonable endeavours to] ensure that one of its representatives shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a737189">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>attend the Location during Business Hours within the relevant Response Time to perform Corrective Maintenance; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a903331">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>complete the Corrective Maintenance within the relevant Fix Time.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a468079" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>All reasonable endeavours (optional wording)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000018" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>On the meaning of best or reasonable endeavours, see <link href="6-380-0482" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Best or reasonable endeavours</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a639714">
              <identifier>4.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Emergency Maintenance.</bold> On the Customer informing the Supplier that the Equipment is defective or is malfunctioning or has failed or is not otherwise in Good Working Order, and requires repair outside of Business Hours, the Supplier shall [use all reasonable endeavours to] ensure that one of its representatives shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a109749">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>attend the Location within the relevant Response Time to perform Emergency Maintenance; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a271589">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>complete the Emergency Maintenance within the relevant Fix Time.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a950231">
              <identifier>4.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Further site visits or repair off-site.</bold> Where it is not reasonably practicable for the Supplier's representative to complete Corrective Maintenance or Emergency Maintenance at the Location on their first visit the Supplier's representative shall either arrange for a further visit to the Location within Business Hours to complete the repair, or [remove <bold>OR </bold>arrange for the removal of] the Equipment (or part of the Equipment, if applicable) for repair off-site.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a463558">
              <identifier>4.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Liability for delay if Customer refuses off-site repair.</bold> The Supplier shall not be liable for any delay in providing the relevant Maintenance Service if in the Supplier's reasonable opinion it needs to remove the Equipment (or part of the Equipment, if applicable) for repair off-site and the Customer refuses this request.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a493002" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Effect of removal of equipment</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000019" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Depending on the importance of the equipment to the customer's business and the relationship of the parties, consider whether it is appropriate to include an obligation on the part of the supplier to loan replacement equipment to the customer during the period of the equipment's removal off site.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a557319">
              <identifier>4.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Provision of information.</bold> The Supplier shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a899471">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>provide to the Customer from time in writing with such up to date and accurate information as to the application and use of the Equipment as may be available to the Supplier and as the Supplier may reasonably determine to be necessary or desirable to be provided; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a568178">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>without prejudice to <internal.reference refid="a826814"><ital>clause 5</ital></internal.reference>, [use all reasonable endeavours to] respond promptly [and during the relevant Response Time], during Business Hours, by telephone[, video call] or in writing, as appropriate, to any request from the Customer for information concerning the application and use of the Equipment, or the repair of any defect in or malfunctioning of the Equipment.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a167113">
              <identifier>4.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Health and safety compliance.</bold> The Supplier shall procure that its representatives shall, while on site at the Location, comply with the Customer's reasonable health and safety and security policies provided that these have been made available to its representatives [in writing].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a925936">
              <identifier>4.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Services manager.</bold> The Supplier shall appoint a manager for the Services. That person shall have authority to contractually bind the Supplier on all matters relating to the Services. The Supplier [shall use all reasonable endeavours to ensure that the same person acts as the Supplier's manager throughout the Term, but] may replace that person from time to time where reasonably necessary in the interests of the Supplier's business.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a826814">
            <identifier>5.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Service levels</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a414949" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Service levels</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000020" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The detail of the service levels will be set out in <internal.reference refid="a980188"><ital>Schedule 3</ital></internal.reference>. The provisions in this <internal.reference refid="a826814"><ital>clause 5</ital></internal.reference> set out how the service levels operate. The key principles are:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The supplier must provide the services so as to meet or exceed the service levels.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The supplier must report its actual performance (measured against the service levels) to the customer on a periodic (in this case monthly) basis.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The supplier will explain how it will meet any failure to perform to the required service levels.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The customer will be entitled to service credits if the supplier fails to meet any of the service levels.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This service level clause is short form. In particular, it does not include:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Provision for a detailed remediation plan.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Any step-in rights, where the customer takes over managerial control of the services pending the supplier demonstrating that it can resume control.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Graduated service credits.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>A mechanism for dealing with the introduction of improvements.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The service levels regime in this standard document includes Critical Service Levels. If the supplier's performance falls below this level an agreed number of times, the customer will be entitled to terminate (<internal.reference refid="a305128"><ital>clause 14.4(a)</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>See <internal.reference refid="a965553"><ital>clause 12.4</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a848792"><ital>clause 12.5</ital></internal.reference> for the interaction with the service credit regime with the agreement's limitation of liability clause.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For longer form wording, see <link anchor="a816726" href="0-202-4551" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Outsourcing agreement: long form: clause 13</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This agreement does not set out a template for the service credit regime as these vary so much from agreement to agreement. For guidance on drafting a service credit schedule, see <link anchor="a69409" href="1-211-9964" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Service levels and service credit schemes in outsourcing: Service credits</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a857112">
              <identifier>5.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Service Levels.</bold> The Supplier shall ensure that the Services meet or exceed the Service Levels at all times from the Commencement Date.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a621636">
              <identifier>5.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Service Levels report. </bold>The Supplier shall provide the Customer with a [monthly] report detailing its performance in respect of each of the Service Levels.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a351155">
              <identifier>5.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Service Failure.</bold> If there is a Service Failure, the Supplier shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a131493">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>notify the Customer immediately of the Service Failure;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a627605">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>arrange all additional resources necessary to perform the Services in accordance with the Service Levels as soon as possible and at no additional charge to the Customer; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a345627">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>credit the Customer with the Service Credits, which shall take effect as an adjustment to the Standard Maintenance Charges.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a745437" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Remediation of service failure</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000021" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This is a very short form clause. For a longer form alternative, see <link anchor="a113713" href="5-213-3958" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Outsourcing agreement: shorter form: clause 7</ital></link>, which includes provision for a remediation plan.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a271422">
              <identifier>5.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Notification of prospective failure to achieve Service Levels.</bold> The Supplier shall notify the Customer promptly of any prospective failure to meet the Service Levels and the parties' respective Services Managers shall meet as soon as practicable to discuss how to remedy this.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a731470">
            <identifier>6.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Spare parts and consumables</headtext>
            </head>
            <subclause1 id="a494885">
              <identifier>6.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Supply of Spare Parts and Consumables.</bold> The Supplier shall supply and fit such Spare Parts and Consumables as required to maintain the Equipment in Good Working Order or to restore the Equipment to Good Working Order. The cost of such Spare Parts and Consumables shall be borne in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a300760"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a300760">
              <identifier>6.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Cost of Spare Parts and Consumables.</bold> The Customer shall reimburse the Supplier in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a740878"><ital>clause 9.7</ital></internal.reference> for the Spare Parts and Consumables at actual cost provided that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a889991">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer shall not reimburse the cost of any Spare Parts or Consumables unless they are approved in advance [in writing] by the Customer; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a597549">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier shall not be entitled to reimbursement unless it promptly provides the Customer with evidence reasonably requested to verify the accuracy of the costs it has incurred for the Spare Parts and Consumables (including receipts and invoices).</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a897312" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Cost of spare parts and consumables</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000022" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>There are several alternative approaches beyond that set out in <internal.reference refid="a300760"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference>, which is that the customer must approve the cost of spare parts and consumables in advance. This approach is better suited to equipment which will not regularly require replacement spare parts and consumables: Alternatives include:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>The supplier can incur expenses up to an agreed amount per item and an agreed aggregate amount over a period, but amounts above that threshold require the customer's consent. Pre-agreed costs could be set out in a schedule to the agreement.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>The supplier bears all the costs. If this approach is adopted, the supplier must ensure its pricing structure captures the cost of spare parts and consumables.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>The supplier may insist on a mark-up on the actual cost price, giving it a profit element.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Where the supplier finds a defect or malfunctioning in the equipment, it issues a quotation for the cost of the remedial work, including spare parts.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The customer may require that:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>The expenses must be incurred in accordance with the customer's expenses policy, as updated from time to time.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>The supplier uses its best (or all reasonable) endeavours to minimise the costs.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For more suggested drafting, see <link href="w-042-9727" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Pass-through expenses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a876288">
              <identifier>6.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Quality of Spare Parts and Consumables and transfer of title in Spare Parts and Consumables.</bold> All Spare Parts shall be either new, or reconditioned or reassembled Spare Parts which are equivalent to new Spare Parts in performance. All Consumables shall be new. The Supplier will transfer to the Customer, with full title guarantee and free from all third party rights, all the Spare Parts and Consumables that it provides to the Customer, and the Spare Parts [and Consumables] shall become part of the Equipment upon their installation in the Equipment.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a161618">
            <identifier>7.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Customer's obligations</headtext>
            </head>
            <subclause1 id="a485676">
              <identifier>7.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Proper use of Equipment</bold>. The Customer shall at all times during the Term:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a304678">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>use the Equipment only in accordance with the [Operating Manual <bold>OR </bold>instructions and recommendations of the manufacturer of the Equipment] or as may be advised [in writing] from time to time by the Supplier;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a336671">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>permit only trained and competent personnel to use the Equipment;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a367682">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>notify the Supplier promptly and in the manner set out in <internal.reference refid="a154107"><ital>clause 7.4</ital></internal.reference> if the Equipment is discovered to be defective or malfunctioning or has failed or is otherwise not in Good Working Order;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a824213">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>keep the Equipment in the environmental conditions recommended [in the Operating Manual <bold>OR </bold>by the manufacturer of the Equipment] or as may be advised [in writing] from time to time by the Supplier;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a365639">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>not allow any other person than the Supplier's representatives to adjust, maintain, repair, replace or remove the Equipment or any part of it, unless otherwise agreed [in writing] by the Supplier; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a532498">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>not move the Equipment from the Location without the prior [written] consent of the Supplier (such consent not to be unreasonably withheld or delayed).</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a478639">
              <identifier>7.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Access to Equipment.</bold> The Customer shall ensure that the Supplier's representatives have:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a452404">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>full and free access to the Location and to the Equipment [and to a power supply and other facilities necessary to operate the Equipment]; [and]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a355958">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>full and free access to any records of its use kept by the Customer[; and <bold>OR</bold> ,]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a749081">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[adequate and safe working space and facilities,]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext>to enable the Supplier to perform its obligations under this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a756473">
              <identifier>7.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Provision of information to Supplier.</bold> The Customer shall provide the Supplier with such information concerning the Equipment, its application, use, location and environment as the Supplier may reasonably request to enable it to perform its obligations under this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a154107">
              <identifier>7.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Malfunction reports.</bold> The Customer shall report that the Equipment is defective or malfunctioning or has failed or is otherwise not in Good Working Order either in writing or by telephone [or video call], or in such other manner as the Supplier may reasonably require from time to time.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a272744">
              <identifier>7.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Safety.</bold> The Customer shall take all such steps as may be necessary to ensure the safety of any of the Supplier's representatives when attending the Location.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a505666">
              <identifier>7.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Customer Services manager.</bold> The Customer shall appoint a manager for the Services. That person shall have authority to contractually bind the Customer on all matters relating to the Services. The Customer [shall use all reasonable endeavours to ensure that the same person acts as the Customer's manager throughout the Term, but] may replace that person from time to time where reasonably necessary in the interests of the Customer's business.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a871996">
              <identifier>7.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Delay due to Customer.</bold> If the Supplier's performance of its obligations under this agreement is prevented or delayed by any act or omission of the Customer, its agents, subcontractors, consultants or employees, then, without prejudice to any other right or remedy it may have, the Supplier shall be allowed an extension of time to perform its obligations equal to the delay caused by the Customer.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a733301" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Failure or delay caused by customer</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000023" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This clause provides for an automatic extension of time for performance where the supplier's inability or delay to provide the services is caused by the customer. It is without prejudice to any other rights and remedies the supplier may have, including at common law. At common law, if the customer fails to perform or delays in performing its obligations:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier will not be liable for its breaches to the extent that these are caused by the customer.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier may, subject to its duty to mitigate, claim damages for any losses or additional costs incurred.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier may have a right to terminate for breach.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Some agreements set out the above remedies specifically. However, this is generally a pro-customer approach, as it is often used to restrict the remedies that the supplier would otherwise have at common law, for example by removing the right to terminate and restricting the sums which may be claimed or by making the supplier's right to claim subject to the supplier giving the customer notice of the delay and taking specified steps to mitigate its effects.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a265321">
            <identifier>8.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Excluded maintenance</headtext>
            </head>
            <subclause1 id="a501392">
              <identifier>8.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>No obligation to perform Excluded Maintenance. </bold>The Supplier is not obliged to perform any Excluded Maintenance.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a426716">
              <identifier>8.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Additional Services Charges.</bold> Where the Supplier is performing or has performed the Maintenance Services in circumstances where it is established that the Equipment was not in Good Working Order due to any of the Excluded Causes, the Supplier may charge, and the Customer shall pay, the Additional Services Charges in respect of that work.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a788588">
              <identifier>8.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Investigation charges.</bold> If on investigation the Supplier reasonably determines that any defect in or malfunctioning of the Equipment is the result of an Excluded Cause, the Customer shall pay Additional Services Charges in respect of the time incurred by the Supplier in making the investigation and determining the cause of the defect in or malfunctioning of the Equipment.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a386761">
            <identifier>9.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Charges and payment</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a270890" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Charges and payment</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000024" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>There are several options for pricing arrangements including:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Time (and materials).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Fixed price.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Hybrid arrangements of the two.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause assumes that <internal.reference refid="a721318"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference> will specify the charges.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a676790"><ital>Clause 9.4</ital></internal.reference> provides some detail on how the daily rates work, which should be amended to reflect the actual position (and alternatively could be set out in <internal.reference refid="a721318"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>See <internal.reference refid="a300760"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference> concerning payment for spare parts and consumables.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a341624">
              <identifier>9.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Standard Maintenance Charges.</bold> In consideration of the performance of the Routine Maintenance and the Corrective Maintenance the Customer shall pay to the Supplier the Standard Maintenance Charges.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a884254">
              <identifier>9.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Additional Services Charges.</bold> In consideration of the performance of any Additional Services the Customer shall pay to the Supplier the Additional Services Charges.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a406443">
              <identifier>9.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Consultancy Services Charges.</bold> In consideration of the performance of any Consultancy Services the Customer say pay to the Supplier the Consultancy Services Charges.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a676790">
              <identifier>9.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Time and materials.</bold> Where the Charges are calculated on a time and materials basis:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a484526">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier's daily fee rates for each individual person as set out in <internal.reference refid="a721318"><ital>Schedule 4</ital></internal.reference> shall be calculated on the basis of an eight-hour day, worked during Business Hours;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a957442">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier shall ensure that every individual whom it engages on the Services completes time sheets to record time spent on the Services, and the Supplier shall indicate the time spent per individual in its invoices.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a731189" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Time and materials (optional wording)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000025" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Delete this clause if none of the charges will be calculated on a time and materials basis.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a590970">
              <identifier>9.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Inclusive charges.</bold> The Charges shall be inclusive of all expenses and the cost to the Supplier of any materials or services procured by the Supplier from third parties for the provision of the Services (other than those recoverable in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a300760"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a96752" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Costs and expenses</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000026" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext><internal.reference refid="a590970"><ital>Clause 9.5</ital></internal.reference> provides that the charges are inclusive of expenses and third-party charges. Amend if this is not the agreed commercial position and ensure that this clause is consistent with <internal.reference refid="a300760"><ital>clause 6.2</ital></internal.reference> concerning spare parts and consumables.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier should ensure that its pricing structure incorporates costs associated with the removal of equipment from the premises (and storage costs, if applicable) .</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a980636">
              <identifier>9.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Charges increases.</bold> The Supplier may increase the Charges on an annual basis with effect from each anniversary of the Commencement Date in line with the percentage increase in the [Consumer Prices Index (all items)] in the preceding 12-month period, and the first such increase shall take effect on the first anniversary of the Commencement Date and shall be based on the latest available figure for the percentage increase in the [Consumer Prices Index (all items)].</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a970305" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Increase in charges</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000027" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This clause allows the supplier to increase the charges annually by reference to a recognised index, in this case the Consumer Prices Index (all items). This provision guarantees a minimum increase for the supplier, who is always free to negotiate a higher one. At the very least the customer is likely to insist on minimum notice of the increase in charges. The customer may also seek to agree a cap limiting the amount by which the supplier may increase its prices, each year. Finally, the customer may also wish to have the right to terminate if it finds the increase unacceptable, although this may be commercially impractical.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more detail on price variation clauses, see <link href="0-219-5963" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Price change</ital></link> and <link href="w-038-1950" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Choosing a price index for a price variation clause</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a740878">
              <identifier>9.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Monthly invoices.</bold> The Supplier shall invoice the Customer at the end of each month for Services performed during that month and the cost of any Spare Parts and Consumables incurred during that month.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a494683">
              <identifier>9.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Payment timing.</bold> The Customer shall pay each invoice submitted to it by the Supplier within [30] days of receipt to a bank account nominated in writing by the Supplier from time to time.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a967938">
              <identifier>9.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Failure to pay.</bold> Without prejudice to any other right or remedy that it may have, if the Customer fails to make a payment due to the Supplier under this agreement by the due date, then:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a667182">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer shall pay interest on the overdue sum from the due date until payment of the overdue sum, whether before or after judgment. Interest under this <internal.reference refid="a667182"><ital>clause 9.9(a)</ital></internal.reference> will accrue each day at 4% a year above the Bank of England's base rate from time to time, but at 4% a year for any period when that base rate is below 0%; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a445118">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier may suspend all or part of the Services until payment has been made in full.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a763039" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Interest and suspension</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000028" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This clause allows the supplier to charge interest and suspend performance if invoices are not paid on time. Consider whether it would be preferable for the supplier to rely on the statutory right to interest on late payments.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The customer may require the supplier to give notice of its intention to charge interest and suspend performance and give the customer a grace period in which to pay the outstanding amount.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For a discussion on interest clauses, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="3-107-3800" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Interest</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a203896">
              <identifier>9.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Tax and set-off.</bold> All sums payable to the Supplier under this agreement:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a1018068">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>are exclusive of VAT, and the Customer shall in addition pay an amount equal to any VAT chargeable on those sums on delivery of a VAT invoice; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a608133">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>shall be paid in full without any set-off, counterclaim, deduction or withholding (other than any deduction or withholding of tax as required by law).</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a314424" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Set-off</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000029" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a608133"><ital>Clause 9.10(b)</ital></internal.reference> is supplier-friendly. As the payment obligation is one way, a supplier will wish to exclude a right of set-off, while a customer may want to add to the common law and equitable right of set-off with a contractual right of set-off.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For a discussion on set-off clauses, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="9-107-3802" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Set-off</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a309178">
            <identifier>10.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Warranties</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Supplier warrants on an ongoing basis that:</paratext>
            </para>
            <subclause1 id="a178416">
              <identifier>10.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>it shall discharge its obligations under this agreement using personnel of the required skill, experience and qualifications and with all due skill, care and diligence including in accordance with Good Industry Practice[. <bold>OR </bold>; and</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a901303">
              <identifier>10.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>all Spare Parts, Consumables and equipment supplied or used in the course of the provision of the Services shall operate materially in accordance with their technical specifications.]</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a721084" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Quality of services and spare parts and consumables</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000030" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The customer may also consider seeking a time-limited warranty as to the effectiveness of repairs to the equipment undertaken by the supplier.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause condition="optional" id="a257869">
            <identifier>11.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Compliance with laws and policies</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a327275" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Compliance with laws and policies (optional wording)</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000031" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For information on this clause, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-618-9498" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Compliance with laws and policies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The supplier may wish to reserve the right to increase its charges where there is a change in law which impacts on the cost to the supplier of providing the services. For a more sophisticated clause, which distinguishes between types of changes in law and provides that the customer need only bear the costs of unanticipated changes in legislation, see <link anchor="a598462" href="5-213-3958" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Outsourcing agreement: shorter form: clause 27</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A supplier may wish to reserve the right to terminate if it is unwilling or unable to comply with an update to one of the mandatory policies notified to it by the customer.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <para>
              <paratext>In performing its obligations under this agreement, the Supplier shall comply with:</paratext>
            </para>
            <subclause1 id="a69713">
              <identifier>11.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>the Applicable Laws; and</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a439645">
              <identifier>11.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>the Mandatory Policies, provided that the Customer shall give the Supplier not less than [NUMBER] months' notice of any change to such policies.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a618544">
            <identifier>12.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Limitation of liability</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a954172" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Limitation of liability</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000032" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>Limitation of liability is always a key issue in a contract for services. Always tailor this clause to the particular transaction. It is likely to be the subject of considerable negotiation between the parties.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>We strongly recommend reading the following practice notes relating to limiting liability in B2B contracts:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="2-520-5359" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: drafting and negotiating</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="w-006-5549" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: interpretation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="9-617-5230" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: statutory and common law controls on limitation clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <division id="a575246" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Approach in this clause</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This clause sets out a fairly basic structure for a limitation of liability clause which is commonly found in negotiated agreements. It is divided into the following sections:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Unlimited liabilities.</bold> Neither party limits those liabilities which cannot be limited as a matter of law.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Capped liabilities.</bold> Each party limits all other liabilities which might arise to a capped amount. The cap applies to each contract year and is the higher of a fixed sum or a percentage of that year's charges.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><bold>Treatment of certain categories of loss.</bold> The clause provides wording to exclude certain categories of loss, such as indirect and consequential loss. There is also an option to carve out certain sub-categories or specific losses from these exclusions. So, for example, the agreement could specify that wasted expenditure in general is excluded but that certain specific costs are not. Or that loss of business in general is excluded but loss of a particular client or contract is not.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
                <division id="a990588" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Why have a limitation clause if acting for the customer?</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Sometimes pro-customer agreements do not contain any limitation or exclusion of liability for breach of contract for either party. Obviously, this approach favours a customer, as it is the supplier, as the performing party, who takes on the greater risk under the contract. This also means the customer's own liability under the contract is unlimited, but the customer may be prepared to accept such a risk if its principal obligation is only to pay the charges.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>However, in practice in negotiated agreements, it would be extremely unusual for a supplier to accept such an approach, because as the performing party it will always look to limit its liability. The supplier could argue that to remain in business and continue serving the customer it needs to cap its liability in a sensible way.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>A customer may prefer to include a limitation clause which is acceptable to it as a starting point for negotiations.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For detailed information on this clause, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="w-010-2114" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Limitation of liability</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a109266">
              <identifier>12.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Scope of this clause.</bold> The following definitions apply in this <internal.reference refid="a618544"><ital>clause 12</ital></internal.reference>:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a804718">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>liability:</bold> every kind of liability arising under or in connection with this agreement including liability in contract, tort (including negligence) or otherwise.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a752889">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext><bold>default:</bold> any act or omission resulting in one party incurring liability to the other.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a995681">
              <identifier>12.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Unlimited liabilities. </bold>Nothing in this agreement limits or excludes:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a589978">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>liability for deliberate default;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a847220">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>liability for death or personal injury caused by negligence to the extent preserved by section 2(1) of the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a741030">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>liability for fraud or fraudulent misrepresentation;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a537694">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>liability for breach of the terms implied by section 12 of the Sale of Goods Act 1979 or section 2 of the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a919289">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any liability that cannot legally be limited; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a914034">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer's payment obligations under this agreement.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a591461">
              <identifier>12.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Supplier's liability cap.</bold> Subject to <internal.reference refid="a995681"><ital>clause 12.2</ital></internal.reference>, the Supplier's total liability:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a713669">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>in respect of Service Credits, shall be limited, in each Contract Year, to [PERCENTAGE]% of the charges paid [or payable] to the Supplier under this agreement in that Contract Year; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a366090">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>in respect of all other defaults occurring within a Contract Year shall not exceed [£[AMOUNT]] <bold>OR</bold> [[PERCENTAGE]% <bold>OR</bold> the greater of £[MINIMUM AMOUNT] and [PERCENTAGE]%] of the charges paid [or payable] to the Supplier under this agreement in that Contract Year].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a965553">
              <identifier>12.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Service Credits.</bold> The Service Credits shall be the exclusive financial remedy for the Customer for each Service Failure for which a Service Credit has been set, unless:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a688016">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any failure to meet the Service Levels (either on an individual basis or in aggregate) constitutes a failure beyond that for which the Service Credits have been set; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a950280">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer is otherwise entitled to terminate this agreement for the Supplier's breach; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a860210">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the failure to perform the Services in accordance with the Service Levels has arisen due to theft, gross negligence, fraud, fraudulent misrepresentation or wilful default.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a475817" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Service credits as sole remedy</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000033" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Consider carefully whether service credits should be the customer's sole financial remedy for the applicable default. Any pre-determined deductions must not give rise to a penalty payment (see <link anchor="a574254" href="9-582-2885" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: agreed remedies: The rule against penalties</ital></link>). However, in practice, service credits are often set at a level which is much lower than the actual losses. As such, they operate principally as a tool to encourage the supplier to perform to the required level rather than to compensate the customer fully for all the losses which arise.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>One solution is to provide that the customer reserves its right to claim damages if the supplier's performance drops below a given threshold provided always that any service credits which have already been paid to the customer should be deducted from the value of the total claim.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>In this agreement, the customer has the right to terminate where the supplier commits a set number of Critical Service Failures (<internal.reference refid="a305128"><ital>clause 14.4(a)</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a848792">
              <identifier>12.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Service credits and cap on liability of Supplier.</bold> [No <bold>OR</bold> The] amounts awarded or agreed to be paid under <internal.reference refid="a345627"><ital>clause 5.3(c)</ital></internal.reference> shall count towards the cap on the Supplier's liability under <internal.reference refid="a366090"><ital>clause 12.3(b)</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a600038">
              <identifier>12.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Customer's liability cap.</bold> Subject to <internal.reference refid="a995681"><ital>clause 12.2</ital></internal.reference>, the Customer's total liability shall not exceed [£[AMOUNT]] <bold>OR</bold> [[PERCENTAGE]% <bold>OR</bold> the greater of £[MINIMUM AMOUNT] and [PERCENTAGE]%] of the charges paid [or payable] to the Supplier under this agreement].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a314547">
              <identifier>12.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Losses that are excluded.</bold> Subject to <internal.reference refid="a995681"><ital>clause 12.2</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a263027"><ital>clause 12.8</ital></internal.reference> neither party shall have any liability for:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a557395">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of profits (including loss of anticipated savings);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a236781">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of sales or business;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a225413">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of agreements or contracts;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a567266">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of use or corruption of software, data or information;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a351631">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>loss of or damage to goodwill; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a888256">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>indirect or consequential loss.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a263027">
              <identifier>12.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Losses that are not excluded. </bold><internal.reference refid="a314547"><ital>Clause 12.7</ital></internal.reference> does not exclude any liability the Supplier may have for<bold>:</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a884195">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>wasted expenditure;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a682673">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[reasonable] costs and expenses [necessarily] incurred by the Customer in remedying the Supplier's default. These include consultancy costs, additional costs of management time and other personnel costs, and costs of equipment and materials;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a855362">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[reasonable] costs incurred by the Customer in procuring and implementing replacements for, or alternatives to, goods or services not provided in accordance with this agreement;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a263544">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[losses incurred by the Customer arising out of or in connection with any third party claim against the Customer which has been caused by the Supplier's default. For these purposes, third party claims include [but are not limited to] demands, fines, penalties, actions, regulatory investigations or proceedings <bold>OR</bold> fines, penalties or similar amounts imposed on the Customer by any regulator as a result of, and increased compliance costs caused by, the Supplier's default];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a646548">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the loss of anticipated savings in respect of [SOURCE OF SAVINGS]; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a314469">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[OTHER SPECIFIC LOSSES].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a570868">
              <identifier>12.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Exclusion of statutory implied terms.</bold> The Supplier has given commitments as to the performance of the Services in <internal.reference refid="a826814"><ital>clause 5</ital></internal.reference> and a warranty in respect of performance of the Services and the performance of Spare Parts, Consumables and equipment supplied or used in the course of the provision of the Services in <internal.reference refid="a901303"><ital>clause 10.2</ital></internal.reference>. In view of these commitments, all conditions, warranties, representations or other terms that might otherwise be implied into this agreement are, to the fullest extent permitted by law, excluded from this agreement, including the conditions and terms implied by sections 3 to 5 and 13 of the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a213174" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Exclusion of statutory implied terms (optional wording)</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000034" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier's argument for excluding the statutory implied terms is that <internal.reference refid="a826814"><ital>clause 5</ital></internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a901303"><ital>clause 10.2</ital></internal.reference> set out the full quality requirements to which it is committing. These bespoke commitments may well influence whether the exclusion is reasonable and for this reason they are referred to in the clause.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>On the implied terms, see <internal.reference refid="a788944"><ital>Drafting note, Implied terms</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a547107">
              <identifier>12.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>No liability for claims not notified within [NUMBER] months.</bold> Unless a party notifies the other party that it intends to make a claim within the notice period, the other party shall have no liability for that claim. The <bold>notice period</bold> shall start on the day on which the party wishing to make a claim became[, or ought reasonably to have become,] aware of its having grounds to make a claim and shall expire [NUMBER] months from that date. The notice must be in writing and must identify the grounds for the claim in reasonable detail.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a373444">
            <identifier>13.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Non-solicitation</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a554252" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Non-solicitation</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000035" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause is a form of restraint of trade clause and restricts each party from attempting to "poach" the other's employees or contractors for a set period. The clause is limited to solicitation. Thus:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>It does not prevent a party from hiring the other's employees where the employee makes an unsolicited approach.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>It does not apply to an employee/contractor of one party applying for a nationally advertised position with the other party.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A non-solicitation clause is only enforceable if the restriction on solicitation goes no further than is reasonably necessary to protect the legitimate interest of the party seeking to enforce it. It will not usually be reasonable to prevent a business from approaching employees whose departure is unlikely to be capable of causing damage to the party wanting to enforce the restriction, for example:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Employees in junior positions.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Employees with whom it has had no involvement during the lifetime of the contract or who are not involved in the provision of the services.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The approach in this clause is therefore to restrict the scope of the restrictive covenant to employees above a certain level of seniority involved in the services or the management of the agreement. The drafting also gives the option of restricting solicitation to six or 12 months post-termination or expiry. The longer term may be more appropriate in respect of more senior employees although the reasonableness of the term will depend on the nature of the agreement and factual matrix.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The clause could be further refined by defining more precisely the categories of employees.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This restriction will capture persons employed or engaged by the covenantee during the lifetime of the agreement but not persons employed or engaged after its termination (or expiry). As persons appointed post-termination (or expiry) will not have been involved in the subject matter of the agreement it would usually be unreasonable to make such persons subject to the restriction.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a169724">
              <identifier>13.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>No solicitation of Restricted Persons.</bold> To protect their respective legitimate business interests each party covenants with the other for itself and as agent for each member of its Group that it shall not (and shall procure that no member of its Group shall) (except with the prior written consent of the other party):</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a313431">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>attempt to solicit or entice away; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a579327">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>solicit or entice away,</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext>from the employment or service of the other party or any member of its Group the services of any Restricted Person other than by means of a national advertising campaign open to all-comers and not specifically targeted at the staff of the other party or any member of its Group.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a845042">
              <identifier>13.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Term of restrictive covenant.</bold> The parties shall be bound by the covenant set out in <internal.reference refid="a169724"><ital>clause 13.1</ital></internal.reference> during the Term, and for a period of [6 <bold>OR </bold>12] months after termination or expiry of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a737454">
              <identifier>13.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Restricted Persons.</bold> For the purposes of this <internal.reference refid="a373444"><ital>clause 13</ital></internal.reference>, a <bold>Restricted Person</bold> shall mean any firm, company or person employed or engaged by a party or any member of its Group during the Term [at the level of [POSITION] or above], who has been engaged in the provision of the Services or the management of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a919167">
              <identifier>13.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Consent.</bold> Any consent given in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a169724"><ital>clause 13.1</ital></internal.reference> shall be subject to payment to the consenting party of a sum equivalent to [20%] of the then current annual remuneration of the Restricted Person or, if higher, [20%] of the annual remuneration to be paid to the Restricted Person.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a443046">
            <identifier>14.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Termination</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a718901" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Termination</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000036" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For a discussion on termination clauses, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="3-107-4673" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Termination</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The clause provides three sets of termination rights:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a993391"><ital>Clause 14.1</ital></internal.reference> is a mutual termination clause which enables either party to terminate upon the occurrence of specific events such as material breach, non-payment and insolvency-related events (but see <internal.reference refid="a249290"><ital>Drafting note, Termination for insolvency</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a492375"><ital>Clause 14.3</ital></internal.reference> gives the supplier an additional termination right if it determines that the equipment can no longer be maintained in good working order or it is damaged beyond economic repair (unless caused by the supplier's own default).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><internal.reference refid="a235203"><ital>Clause 14.4</ital></internal.reference> gives the customer an additional termination right if the supplier either commits an agreed number of critical service failures or it fails to comply with applicable law or the customer's mandatory policies.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <division id="a249290" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Termination for insolvency</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>From 26 June 2020, it has become difficult or impossible for a supplier to terminate many contracts for goods or (non-financial) services on the grounds that the customer has entered a corporate insolvency procedure (<link href="w-026-3710" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 233B</ital></link>, <ital>Insolvency Act 1986</ital>). See <link href="w-025-9457" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Restrictions on terminating supply contracts in insolvency proceedings</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>To overcome this, <internal.reference refid="a241905"><ital>clause 14.1(n)</ital></internal.reference> provides that either party can terminate if in its reasonable opinion the other's financial position has deteriorated to the point where its ability to perform its obligations under the agreement is in jeopardy. In practice, however, this trigger may be difficult to invoke. The supplier would need to be confident it could justify the necessary opinion and may lack access to full information or the resources to monitor the customer's financial position. If the supplier terminates without the legal and factual grounds to do so it risks liability for wrongful termination, as discussed in <link anchor="a503283" href="5-559-4767" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: termination: Getting termination wrong</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
                <division id="a524445" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Termination for convenience</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This agreement does not include a right to terminate for convenience. For suggested wording and drafting considerations if a termination for convenience is needed, see <link anchor="a390931" href="3-623-0753" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-customer): clause 19.4</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a993391">
              <identifier>14.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Termination by either party</bold>. Without affecting any other right or remedy available to it, either party may terminate this agreement with immediate effect by giving [written] notice to the other party if:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a962801">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party fails to pay any amount due under this agreement on the due date for payment and remains in default not less than [NUMBER] days after being notified in writing to make such payment;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a822291">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party commits a material breach of any other term of this agreement and (if such breach is remediable) fails to remedy that breach within a period of [NUMBER] days after being notified [in writing] to do so;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a387158">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party repeatedly breaches any of the terms of this agreement in such a manner as to reasonably justify the opinion that its conduct is inconsistent with it having the intention or ability to give effect to the terms of this agreement;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a472777">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party suspends, or threatens to suspend, payment of its debts or is unable to pay its debts as they fall due or admits inability to pay its debts or is deemed unable to pay its debts within the meaning of section 123 of the Insolvency Act 1986 as if the words "it is proved to the satisfaction of the court" did not appear in sections 123(1)(e) or 123(2) of the Insolvency Act 1986;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a237207">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party commences negotiations with all or any class of its creditors with a view to rescheduling any of its debts, or makes a proposal for or enters into any compromise or arrangement with any of its creditors [other than for the sole purpose of a scheme for a solvent amalgamation of that other party with one or more other companies or the solvent reconstruction of that other party];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a991055">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party applies to court for, or obtains, a moratorium under Part A1 of the Insolvency Act 1986;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a937618">
                <identifier>(g)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a petition is filed, a notice is given, a resolution is passed, or an order is made, for or in connection with the winding up of the other party [other than for the sole purpose of a scheme for a solvent amalgamation of that other party with one or more other companies or the solvent reconstruction of that other party];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a160177">
                <identifier>(h)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>an application is made to court, or an order is made, for the appointment of an administrator, or a notice of intention to appoint an administrator is given or an administrator is appointed, over the other party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a406586">
                <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the holder of a qualifying floating charge over the assets of that other party has become entitled to appoint or has appointed an administrative receiver;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a234094">
                <identifier>(j)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a person becomes entitled to appoint a receiver over all or any of the assets of the other party or a receiver is appointed over all or any of the assets of the other party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a422553">
                <identifier>(k)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a creditor or encumbrancer of the other party attaches or takes possession of, or a distress, execution, sequestration or other such process is levied or enforced on or sued against, the whole or any part of the other party's assets and such attachment or process is not discharged within [14] days;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a367322">
                <identifier>(l)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any event occurs, or proceeding is taken, with respect to the other party in any jurisdiction to which it is subject that has an effect equivalent or similar to any of the events mentioned in <internal.reference refid="a472777"><ital>clause 14.1(d)</ital></internal.reference> to <internal.reference refid="a422553"><ital>clause 14.1(k)</ital></internal.reference> (inclusive);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a151363">
                <identifier>(m)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party suspends or ceases, or threatens to suspend or cease, carrying on all or a substantial part of its business;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a241905">
                <identifier>(n)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party's financial position deteriorates so far as to reasonably justify the opinion that its ability to give effect to the terms of this agreement is in jeopardy; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a643520">
                <identifier>(o)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>there is a change of control of the other party.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a410939">
              <identifier>14.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Material breach</bold>. For the purposes of <internal.reference refid="a822291"><ital>clause 14.1(b)</ital></internal.reference>, <bold>material breach</bold> means:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a324511">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a breach of any of the obligations set out in clauses [NUMBERS]; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a472499">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a breach that has a serious effect on the benefit the terminating party would otherwise derive from this agreement [over any [NUMBER]-month period during the Term].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a492375">
              <identifier>14.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Termination by Supplier</bold>. Without affecting any other right or remedy available to it, the Supplier may terminate this agreement with immediate effect by giving written notice to the Customer if the Supplier reasonably determines that the Equipment can no longer be maintained in Good Working Order by the provision of Spare Parts or Consumables or the Equipment is damaged beyond economic repair otherwise than through the Supplier's fault.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a235203">
              <identifier>14.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Termination by Customer</bold>. Without affecting any other right or remedy available to it, the Customer may terminate this agreement with immediate effect by giving written notice to the Supplier if:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a305128">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier has committed [NUMBER] Critical Service Failure(s) [in any [PERIOD]]; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a847578">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier commits a breach of <internal.reference refid="a257869"><ital>clause 11</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a848912" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Customer's right to terminate for supplier's breach</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000037" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Delete <internal.reference refid="a305128"><ital>clause 14.4(a)</ital></internal.reference> if this agreement does not contain critical service levels. Depending on the nature of the critical service failures, the supplier may wish to include the optional wording in longer-term agreements so that historic failures are not taken into account years later.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The supplier may seek to amend <internal.reference refid="a847578"><ital>clause 14.4(b)</ital></internal.reference> by including a materiality qualification. Alternatively, the drafting could be amended to state that breach of <internal.reference refid="a257869"><ital>clause 11</ital></internal.reference> is a material breach within <internal.reference refid="a324511"><ital>clause 14.2(a)</ital></internal.reference>, giving the supplier the opportunity to remedy the breach (if it is capable of remedy) (<internal.reference refid="a822291"><ital>clause 14.1(b)</ital></internal.reference>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a299816">
            <identifier>15.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Consequences of termination and survival</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a444828" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Consequences of termination and survival</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000038" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See the integrated drafting notes to <link href="3-203-1593" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Survival</ital></link> for a discussion of consequences of termination clauses including:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Why a survival clause is necessary.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Obligations on termination: payment obligations and return of materials.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Exit management: handover of service provision to the customer or a new supplier.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <division id="a556318" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Exit services</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the services require a transition back to the customer or a new supplier when the agreement terminates or expires, the parties may wish to consider including provisions for an exit plan.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For a discussion of exit management generally, see <link href="6-107-4775" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Main issues in outsourcing contracts: Exit management</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For a very short form exit assistance clause, see <link anchor="a587954" href="3-623-0753" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-customer): clause 20.2</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
                <division id="a350495" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Return of materials</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This standard document does not envisage the supplier having to hand over any materials to the customer on termination. If the customer envisages the need to include such an obligation, most obviously to ensure it has copies of maintenance records, see <link anchor="a589454" href="3-623-0753" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-customer): clause 20.1(a)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a915094">
              <identifier>15.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Unpaid invoices and survival.</bold> On termination [or expiry] of this agreement:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a274598">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer shall immediately pay to the Supplier all the Supplier's outstanding unpaid invoices and interest and, in respect of the Services supplied but for which no invoice has been submitted, the Supplier may submit an invoice, which shall be payable immediately on receipt; and</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a743450" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Payment of outstanding invoices</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000039" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>If payments are made in advance, consider including a requirement for the return of payments in advance for a service that has not been, and will not now be, provided.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a274406">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any provision of this agreement that expressly or by implication is intended to come into or continue in force on or after termination [or expiry] of this agreement shall remain in full force and effect.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a748810">
              <identifier>15.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Accrued rights.</bold> Termination [or expiry] of this agreement shall not affect any rights, remedies, obligations or liabilities of the parties that have accrued up to the date of termination [or expiry], including the right to claim damages in respect of any breach of the agreement which existed at or before the date of termination [or expiry].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a563361">
            <identifier>16.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Confidentiality</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a166388" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Confidentiality</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000040" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>If confidentiality is a major issue, the most effective method to prevent disclosure of the information is to attach a schedule of specified individuals who are permitted to receive the information and then to inform each individual that the information handled is to be treated as confidential. If necessary, the individuals concerned could each be asked to sign a specific confidentiality undertaking with the supplier of this information.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For information on confidentiality and a longer form alternative, see <link href="2-107-3829" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Confidentiality</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a925800">
              <identifier>16.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>No disclosure of confidential information</bold>. Each party undertakes that it shall not [at any time <bold>OR</bold> at any time during this agreement, and for a period of [two] years after termination [or expiry] of this agreement,] disclose to any person any confidential information concerning the business, assets, affairs, customers, clients or suppliers of the other party [or of any member of the Group to which the other party belongs], except as permitted by <internal.reference refid="a940556"><ital>clause 16.2</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a940556">
              <identifier>16.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Exceptions.</bold> Each party may disclose the other party's confidential information:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a350843">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>to its employees, officers, representatives, contractors, subcontractors or advisers who need to know such information for the purposes of exercising the party's rights or carrying out its obligations under or in connection with this agreement. Each party shall ensure that its employees, officers, representatives, contractors, subcontractors or advisers to whom it discloses the other party's confidential information comply with this <internal.reference refid="a563361"><ital>clause 16</ital></internal.reference>; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a728607">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>as may be required by law, a court of competent jurisdiction or any governmental or regulatory authority.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a215097">
              <identifier>16.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Restrictions on use of confidential information.</bold> No party may use any other party's confidential information for any purpose other than to exercise its rights and perform its obligations under or in connection with this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a307182">
            <identifier>17.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Dispute resolution procedure</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a551231" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Dispute resolution procedure</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000041" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a307182"><ital>Clause 17</ital></internal.reference> sets out a basic procedure which provides for the escalation of a dispute through several escalation levels before the notional referral of the dispute to mediation.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on dispute resolution clauses, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="3-369-3959" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Multi-tiered dispute resolution procedure</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a205472">
              <identifier>17.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Dispute notices, escalation, and mediation.</bold> If a dispute arises out of or in connection with this agreement or its performance, validity or enforceability (<bold>Dispute</bold>), then the parties shall follow the procedure set out in this clause:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a253086">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>either party shall give to the other written notice of the Dispute, setting out its nature and full particulars (<defn.term>Dispute notice</defn.term>), together with relevant supporting documents. On service of the Dispute notice, the Services Managers shall attempt in good faith to resolve the Dispute;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a765006">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>if the Services Managers are for any reason unable to resolve the Dispute within [30] [working] days of service of the Dispute notice, the Dispute shall be referred to the [SENIOR OFFICER TITLE] of the Supplier and [SENIOR OFFICER TITLE] of the Customer who shall attempt in good faith to resolve it;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a411285">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>if the [SENIOR OFFICER TITLE] of the Supplier and [SENIOR OFFICER TITLE] of the Customer are for any reason unable to resolve the Dispute within [30] [working] days of it being referred to them, the parties agree to enter into mediation in good faith to settle the Dispute and will do so in accordance with [the CEDR Model Mediation Procedure <bold>OR </bold>[PROCEDURE]]. Unless otherwise agreed between the parties within [NUMBER] [working] days of service of the Dispute notice, the mediator will be nominated by [CEDR <bold>OR </bold>[BODY] <bold>OR </bold>[PERSON]]. To initiate the mediation, a party must give notice in writing (<defn.term>ADR notice</defn.term>) to the other party to the Dispute, referring the dispute to mediation. [A copy of the ADR notice should be sent to [CEDR <bold>OR </bold>[PROVIDER]]; [and]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a980306">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[if there is any point on the logistical arrangements of the mediation, other than nomination of the mediator, on which the parties cannot agree within [NUMBER] [working] days from the date of the ADR notice, where appropriate, in conjunction with the mediator, [CEDR <bold>OR</bold> [PROVIDER]] will be requested to decide that point for the parties having consulted with them; and]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a131705">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>unless otherwise agreed between the parties, the mediation will start not later than [NUMBER] [working] days after the date of the ADR notice.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a786370">
              <identifier>17.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Mediation and court proceedings</bold>. The commencement of mediation shall not prevent the parties commencing or continuing court proceedings.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a806880">
              <identifier>17.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Exhaustion of mediation process. </bold>If for any reason the Dispute is not resolved within [NUMBER] [working] days of commencement of the mediation, the Dispute shall be referred to and finally resolved by the courts of England and Wales in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a463526"><ital>clause 18.12</ital></internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a396536">
            <identifier>18.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>General</headtext>
            </head>
            <subclause1 id="a460749">
              <identifier>18.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Force majeure</bold>. Neither party shall be liable for any delay or failure in the performance of its obligations for so long as and to the extent that such delay or failure results from events, circumstances or causes beyond its reasonable control. If the period of delay or non-performance continues for [NUMBER] [days], the party not affected may terminate this agreement by giving [not less than [NUMBER] days'] written notice to the affected party.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a688291" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Force majeure</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000042" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="6-107-3808" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Force majeure</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><link anchor="a226743" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Force majeure</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a303586">
              <identifier>18.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Assignment and other dealings</bold>.<bold> </bold>This agreement is personal to the parties and neither party shall assign, novate, transfer, mortgage, charge, subcontract, delegate, declare a trust over or deal in any other manner with any of its rights and obligations under this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a921188" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Assignment and other dealings</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000043" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>This is a short form assignment clause which precludes either party from assigning the benefit of the contract or subcontracting its obligations. Consider, in particular, whether the customer may wish to assign intra-group.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="5-107-3823" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital> Standard clause, Assignment and other dealings</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><link anchor="a120126" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Assignment and other dealings</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a929152">
              <identifier>18.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Entire agreement</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a529906">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This agreement constitutes the entire agreement between the parties.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a61361">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Each party acknowledges that in entering into this agreement it does not rely on any statement, representation, assurance or warranty (whether made innocently or negligently) that is not set out in this agreement. Each party agrees that it has no claim for innocent or negligent misrepresentation [or negligent misstatement] based on any statement in this agreement.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a229499" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Entire agreement</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000044" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Entire agreement clauses, see <link href="3-503-7049" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: entire agreement clauses</ital></link> and <link anchor="a102696" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Entire agreement</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>This entire agreement clause, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="2-107-3834" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Entire agreement</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a494350">
              <identifier>18.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Waiver</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a857029">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A waiver of any right or remedy is only effective if given in writing [and shall not be deemed a waiver of any subsequent right or remedy].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a340024">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A delay or failure to exercise, or the single or partial exercise of, any right or remedy does not waive that or any other right or remedy, nor shall it prevent or restrict the further exercise of that or any other right or remedy.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a724866" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Waiver</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000045" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="0-107-3806" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Waiver</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><link anchor="a947318" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Waiver</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a921600">
              <identifier>18.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Severance</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a933461">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>If any provision or part-provision of this agreement is or becomes invalid, illegal or unenforceable, it shall be deemed deleted, but that shall not affect the validity and enforceability of the rest of this agreement.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a777709">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>If any provision or part-provision of this agreement is deemed deleted under <internal.reference refid="a933461"><ital>clause 18.5(a)</ital></internal.reference> the parties shall negotiate in good faith to agree a replacement provision that, to the greatest extent possible, achieves the intended commercial result of the original provision.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a299926" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Severance</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000046" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on this severance clause, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="9-107-3840" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Severance</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a681102">
              <identifier>18.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Variation</bold>. No variation of this agreement shall be effective unless it is in writing and signed by the parties (or their authorised representatives).</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a837918" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Variation</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000047" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For information on:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Variation, see <link href="7-380-8331" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: variation</ital></link> and <link anchor="a436667" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Variation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>This variation clause, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="3-107-3838" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Variation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a982171">
              <identifier>18.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Third party rights</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a338022">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Unless it expressly states otherwise, this <bold>OR</bold> This] agreement does not give rise to any rights under the Contracts (Rights of Third Parties) Act 1999 to enforce any term of this agreement.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a938602">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The rights of the parties to rescind or vary this agreement are not subject to the consent of any other person.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a297362" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Third party rights</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000048" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For information on:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>Third party rights, see <link href="8-380-8057" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: privity and third party rights and obligations</ital></link> and <link anchor="a867788" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Third party rights</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>This clause, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-107-3846" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Third party rights</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a522675">
              <identifier>18.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Conflict</bold>. If there is an inconsistency between any of the provisions in the main body of this agreement and the Schedules, the provisions in the main body of this agreement prevail.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a801122" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Conflict</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000049" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="7-107-3836" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Conflict</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><link anchor="a195430" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Conflict</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a176065">
              <identifier>18.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Rights and remedies</bold>. [Except as expressly provided in this agreement, the <bold>OR</bold> The] rights and remedies provided under this agreement are in addition to, and not exclusive of, any rights or remedies provided by law.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a967024" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Rights and remedies</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000050" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For information on provisions regarding the parties' rights and remedies, see:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The integrated drafting notes to <link href="2-203-0725" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Rights and remedies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext><link anchor="a778211" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Rights and remedies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a595928">
              <identifier>18.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Notices</bold></paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a205806">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Any notice given to a party under or in connection with this agreement shall be in writing and shall be:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a512723">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>delivered by hand or by pre-paid first-class post or other next working day delivery service at its registered office (if a company) or its principal place of business (in any other case); [or]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a177703">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>sent by email to the following addresses (or an address substituted in writing by the party to be served):</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Supplier: [ADDRESS].</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Customer: [ADDRESS]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a355945">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Any notice shall be deemed to have been received:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a614484">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>if delivered by hand, at the time the notice is left at the proper address;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a990753">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>if sent by [pre-paid first-class post or other] next working day delivery service, at [9.00 am] on the [second] Business Day after posting[; or]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a133341">
                  <identifier>(iii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>if sent by email, at the time of transmission, or, if this time falls outside Business Hours in the place of receipt, when Business Hours resume.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a493696">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause does not apply to the service of any proceedings or other documents in any legal action or, where applicable, any arbitration or other method of dispute resolution.</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a436770" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Notices</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000051" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="5-107-3842" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clauses, Notices</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                      <list.item>
                        <para>
                          <paratext><link href="3-107-3843" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Notice clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </list.item>
                    </list>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a411251">
              <identifier>18.11</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Governing law</bold>. This agreement and any dispute or claim (including non-contractual disputes or claims) arising out of or in connection with it or its subject matter or formation shall be governed by and construed in accordance with the law of England and Wales.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a955541" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Governing law</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000052" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For information on:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Governing law clauses, see <link href="4-107-3852" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Governing law and jurisdiction clauses</ital></link> and <link anchor="a742310" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Governing law.</ital></link></paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>This governing law clause, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="8-107-3850" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Governing law</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a463526">
              <identifier>18.12</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Jurisdiction</bold>. Each party irrevocably agrees that the courts of England and Wales shall have exclusive jurisdiction to settle any dispute or claim (including non-contractual disputes or claims) arising out of or in connection with this agreement or its subject matter or formation.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a199698" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Jurisdiction</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000053" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For information on:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Jurisdiction clauses, see <link href="4-107-3852" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice notes, Governing law and jurisdiction clauses</ital></link> and <link anchor="a783056" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Jurisdiction</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>This jurisdiction clause, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="9-522-6848" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Jurisdiction</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
        </operative>
        <testimonium default="true" wording="contract">
          <para>
            <paratext>This agreement has been entered into on the date stated at the beginning of it.</paratext>
          </para>
        </testimonium>
        <disclosure.schedule>
          <schedule id="a187097">
            <identifier>Schedule 1</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Equipment</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a142308" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Equipment</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000054" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The customer must ensure that the definition of Equipment is drafted sufficiently widely to cover, for example, associated cabling, tools and other ancillaries. For its part, the supplier will want to ensure it is not assuming responsibility for maintaining items that it considers to be out of scope.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
          </schedule>
          <schedule id="a296072">
            <identifier>Schedule 2</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Location</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a788404" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Location</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000055" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>Specify the location of the equipment.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
          </schedule>
          <schedule id="a980188">
            <identifier>Schedule 3</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Service levels</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a625351" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Service levels</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000056" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This agreement requires the supplier to perform the services in accordance with a set of service levels. Details of the service levels and applicable service credits should be included here.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Although the precise service level requirements will vary from agreement to agreement, it will always be the case that the service levels must focus on the crucial elements of the services and the standard to which these services must be performed, notably availability, response times and overall quality of service. In this agreement, the supplier is required to deliver within defined "fix times" and "response times", which should be set out in this schedule. Include other service levels, as applicable.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on service levels and service credits, see <link href="1-211-9964" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Service levels and service credit schemes in outsourcing</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <part id="a745564">
              <identifier>Part 1</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Response Times</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part id="a1015113">
              <identifier>Part 2</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Fix Times</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part condition="optional" id="a812168">
              <identifier>Part 3</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>[Others]</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part condition="optional" id="a870479">
              <identifier>Part 4</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Critical Service Levels</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part id="a421005">
              <identifier>Part 5</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Service Credits</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
          </schedule>
          <schedule id="a721318">
            <identifier>Schedule 4</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Charges</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a269048" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Charges, costs and payment</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000057" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This standard document envisages three sets of charges: for standard maintenance, for additional services and for consultancy services. Set out the applicable charges for each, which may be fixed price, time (and materials) or a mixture of the two. The consultancy services are likely to be on a time basis.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>If setting out the daily rates for the supplier, ensure that any higher rates for more senior members of the team are specified.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The inspection fee, if one is included, is likely to be a fixed fee.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <part id="a292235">
              <identifier>Part 1</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Standard Maintenance Charges</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part id="a344459">
              <identifier>Part 2</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Additional Services Charges</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part id="a336351">
              <identifier>Part 3</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Consultancy Services Charges</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
            <part condition="optional" id="a551145">
              <identifier>Part 4</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Inspection Fee</headtext>
              </head>
            </part>
          </schedule>
          <schedule condition="optional" id="a660852">
            <identifier>Schedule 5</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Mandatory Policies</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a943296" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Mandatory Policies: list and attach? (optional schedule)</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000058" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For a discussion of whether or not the mandatory policies should also be attached to the agreement, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-618-9498" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Compliance with laws and policies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Delete from the list those policies that are inapplicable.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <para>
              <paratext>[LIST [AND ATTACH] THE MANDATORY POLICIES HERE]</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Mandatory Policies are:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Modern Slavery and Human Trafficking Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Corporate and Social Responsibility Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Data and Privacy Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Ethics and Anti-Bribery Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Expenses Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Health and Safety Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Security Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Use and Access to Premises Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </schedule>
        </disclosure.schedule>
        <signature default="true" pagebreak="true" signaturemessage="no">
          <para>
            <paratext>
              <table frame="none" pgwide="1">
                <tgroup cols="3">
                  <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="64"/>
                  <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="3"/>
                  <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="31"/>
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Signed by [NAME OF DIRECTOR]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>……………….………….…….….</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>for and on behalf of [NAME OF <bold>Supplier</bold>]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Director</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
              <table frame="none" pgwide="1">
                <tgroup cols="3">
                  <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="64"/>
                  <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="3"/>
                  <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="31"/>
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Signed by [NAME OF DIRECTOR]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>……………….………….…….….</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>for and on behalf of [NAME OF <bold>Customer</bold>]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Director</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
            </paratext>
          </para>
        </signature>
      </body>
    </standard.doc>
  </n-docbody>
</n-document>