<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><n-document xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" guid="0" synced="true" validated="true">
  <n-docbody>
    <standard.doc precedenttype="agreement">
      <prelim>
        <product.name>product.name0</product.name>
        <title>Software as a service (SaaS) subscription agreement (pro-supplier)</title>
        <author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT and Richard Kemp and Deirdre Moynihan of Kemp IT Law</author>
        <resource.type>Standard documents</resource.type>
        <juris>juris0</juris>
        <juris>juris1</juris>
      </prelim>
      <abstract>
        <para>
          <paratext>An agreement, drafted from the supplier's viewpoint, which creates a "software as a service" (SaaS) arrangement, providing for the secure delivery of services to the user's terminal on a pay-per-use basis over a network (typically the internet) from processors hosted remotely by the SaaS provider, as distinct from the more traditional "software as a licence" which is normally installed on the customers' servers, or on third party provided hosting solutions.</paratext>
        </para>
      </abstract>
      <toc.identifier hasToc="true"/>
      <body>
        <drafting.note id="a982149" jurisdiction="">
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>About this document</headtext>
          </head>
          <division id="a000009" level="1">
            <para>
              <paratext>Software as a service or SaaS is an evolution of the software hosting or Application Service Provider ("ASP") model that emerged in the late nineties. The ASP model was an early beneficiary of the convergence of computing and communications that the first stage of the "internet revolution" enabled between 1995 and 2005. Although it remains important for many customers and their software providers across many industries, the popularity of software hosting is being displaced as increasing broadband speed, reliability and ease of use fuel a new generation of internet-based software delivery techniques.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>SaaS is securely delivered to the user's terminal at the customer on a pay-per-use basis over a network (typically the Internet) from processors hosted remotely by the SaaS provider – as distinct from "software as a licence" installed on the customers' servers, or more recently in third party provided hosting solutions. ASP and SaaS share the essential features of service, rather than licence, delivery from a "one-to-many" (rather than "one-to-one") computer centre.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>For more information on the different ways in which different vendors use the term "software as a service", see <link href="7-107-4789#a256253" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Main issues in software licensing and maintenance contracts: Software as a service</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>The speed of cloud and SaaS adoption has increased significantly over recent years, driven by the move to en masse home working and the need for reliable, accessible services. The balance between traditional enterprise computing (hardware, services, applications and staffing), on the one hand, and the private cloud and the Infrastructure (IaaS), Platform (PaaS) and Software (SaaS) elements of the public cloud, on the other hand, has now shifted significantly in favour of the latter. Today SaaS and cloud offerings are increasingly synonymous.  Cloud computing can be described as the harnessing of the internet cloud for the aggregation of computing tasks performed at multiple computer centres and locations. The final destination on this road is "utility computing" – use of software resources genuinely "at the flick of a switch".</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>The standard document and drafting note should be used for the non- (or less) customised, more generic, "built for the internet", "web-ready" services that characterise SaaS. In the case of the separate <link href="4-201-4258" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Application service provision agreement</ital></link>, ASP is synonymous with "hosted application management" whose essentials are the provisions of hosting, access and support services with an element of specific installation/configuration for the customer.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>It is common for SaaS providers to host their service and store all of their customers' data in the "cloud" - the internet environment which enables customers to use the software services without knowledge or expertise of, or control over, the technology infrastructure (including the actual processing capacity) that are used to host the software application. All of the data belonging to each customer is stored, or "stacked" on shared computer platforms operated by the SaaS provider in the cloud, but each customer's data is capable of being kept (virtually) separate from that belonging to others. This multi-tenant architecture allows vendors to offer customers cost savings as a result of economies of scale achieved by managing multiple customer solutions in a single operation. Vendors are also able to reduce costs by using open source software in their software applications. SaaS is also offered, usually more expensively, on the basis of customer-dedicated infrastructure. This is usually favoured by regulated entities or those who are concerned with the security risks associated with a multi-tenant architecture.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>SaaS vendors benefit from only having to support one version of their software and delivering their service on a single platform. In addition, SaaS providers can make enhancements to the software on a regular basis fairly simply, as the software is located at the SaaS provider's data centre and not at the customer's premises. The vendor can then implement enhancements and upgrades at its data centre and then make those changes available to its entire customer base. Some vendors may offer customers the ability to delay or reject changes for limited periods of time, however, the ultimate aim is for all customers to be running on the same version of the software and supporting infrastructure.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>Customers can also benefit from the SaaS model by not having to invest heavily in hardware and other software to obtain a wide range of functional capabilities. As payments under a SaaS contract are typically operating expenditure for the purposes of the P&amp;L account and not capital expenditure (requiring a much larger initial outlay, which appears on the balance sheet and is brought back to the P&amp;L as depreciation), customers have less of an investment in the supplier's software than is the case with "software as a licence" and so are arguably less inhibited in switching suppliers. This is likely to make the software market significantly more competitive and further reduce costs over time, a particularly important consideration in today's economic conditions.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>The objective of a supplier-side SaaS subscription agreement is to protect the supplier as far as reasonably possible in the context of a market-acceptable agreement, first by extending the responsibilities of the customer; secondly, by limiting the scope of the contractual obligations and the liability of the supplier for failure to perform; and thirdly, through clarity in delineating the services that the supplier is providing. The standard document has been drafted on the assumption that it will be used for B2B arrangements, as opposed to those involving consumers. It should be used for relatively standard SaaS deals and will usually be presented as a set of non-negotiable terms and conditions for signature by the customer.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>The standard document is drafted from the perspective of the supplier of the services. Nevertheless, it adopts a reasonably balanced approach to the relevant issues on the basis that an agreement which is drafted too much in favour of either party serves only to increase the time and cost of negotiations. That said, the increase in SaaS deals has resulted in suppliers’ contractual positions hardening, meaning that terms are becoming more favourable to suppliers.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>From the customer perspective, things that the customer will need to think about include:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>In current economic conditions:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>supplier financial stability;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>supplier dependence on particular resources and the financial stability of the providers of those resources to the supplier;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>the supplier's own disaster recovery/business continuity arrangements;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>dependence on the supplier and the services;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>impact on the customer's business in each case of a small, moderate or severe service outage; and</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>how easy or difficult it is (and hence the time and resources required) to switch to an alternative source of supply.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </list.item>
            </list>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The usual IT services deals points about:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>service levels and credits;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>price increases during the agreement;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>business continuity/disaster recovery;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>exit/disengagement management and replacement contractors; and</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>return of data.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </list.item>
            </list>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Regulatory points such as:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>data and service security;</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>compliance with any regulatory audit obligations applicable to the customer; and</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>compliance with any other (sector-specific or generally applicable) regulatory obligations on the supplier and the customer.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </division>
          <division id="a171653" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Legal issues</headtext>
            </head>
            <division id="a781700" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Competition issues</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>Under UK competition law, the <link href="6-107-5888" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Chapter II prohibition</ital></link> of the <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/5-505-5914?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=PLDocumentLink&amp;amp;contextData=%28sc.Default%29&amp;amp;comp=pluk" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Competition Act 1998</ital></link> (Competition Act) is based on <link href="8-107-6434" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Article 102</ital></link> of the<ital> </ital><link href="8-505-5578" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union</ital></link><ital> (TFEU)</ital>, and prohibits abuses of dominance in a market which may have an affect on trade within the UK or any part of it.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>In addition, the <link href="8-107-5887" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Chapter I prohibition</ital></link> of the Competition Act, based on <link href="0-107-6433" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Article 101 </ital></link> of the TFEU, prohibits anti-competitive agreements between undertakings (that is, any natural or legal person carrying on economic activities, including companies, sole traders and trading divisions of public bodies), which have the object or effect of restricting competition within the UK and which affect trade within the UK or any part of it.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>Entering into an agreement that breaches UK competition law can result in:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The agreement (or particular sections of it) being null and void.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The parties being subject to investigation and enforcement proceedings by UK competition authority, the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Potential exposure to large fines and private actions for damages.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>The EU competition rules (Articles 101 and 102 of the TFEU) will continue to apply, at the end of the <link href="w-023-9796" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>UK-EU transition period</ital></link>, to agreements or conduct of UK companies that have an effect within the EU, see <link href="w-016-5380" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Extraterritorial application of EU competition law</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>At the EU level, an agreement that is caught by Article 101(1) TFEU may nevertheless escape prohibition (and therefore voidness) under Article 101(3) TFEU if it subject to either an individual or block exemption. For more information, see <link anchor="a1037249" href="0-107-3707" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Competition regime: Article 101: Exemption under Article 101(3)</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>In the UK, <link href="0-107-6961" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>parallel exemptions</ital></link> apply to agreements which are covered by an EU Commission individual or block exemption under Article 101(3) of the TFEU, or would be covered by an EU Commission block exemption if the agreement had an appreciable effect on trade between EU member states. Agreements covered by parallel exemptions are automatically exempt from the Chapter I prohibition.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>In the licensing context, <link href="9-566-2085" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Commission Regulation 316/2014 (Technology Transfer Block Exemption Regulation)</ital></link> (TTBER) is relevant. Although it is not expressed to apply to copyright, it is likely that both the Commission and the national courts would have regard to its provisions and may apply them by analogy. However, they may choose not to do so, as here the licence is ancillary to the provision of services. For more information, see <link href="1-107-3721" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Flowchart guides: Technology transfer block exemption</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>Ofcom is currently considering competition aspects of cloud services provision, in particular barriers to switching or multi-cloud usage, and whether regulatory interventions would assist. See <link href="w-041-0791" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Legal update, CMA issues statement in cloud services market investigation</ital></link>. The findings will also be considered in the context of new legislation intended to implement a new pro-competition regime for digital markets, see <link href="w-039-2648" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Legal update, Digital Markets, Competition and Consumer Bill introduced into Parliament: digital markets and competition aspects</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For more information, see the following Practice notes:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="0-566-9265" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Competition law in copyright exploitation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="0-107-3689" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Transactions and practices: UK Intellectual property transactions</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="7-107-3704" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Transactions and practices: EU Intellectual property transactions</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-019-1992?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Brexit: implications for UK merger control</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-019-5177?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Brexit: implications for UK competition law enforcement</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
            </division>
            <division id="a345826" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Supply chain issues: slavery and human trafficking</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The <link href="2-607-4606" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Modern Slavery Act 2015</ital></link> (MSA) is aimed at combating crimes of slavery and human trafficking. <link href="7-608-3825" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Section 54</ital></link> of the MSA requires commercial organisations having a global turnover of £36 million or more to publish an annual slavery and human trafficking statement for each financial year that ends on or after 31 March 2016. The statement must disclose what steps the organisation has taken to ensure that human trafficking is not taking place in any of its supply chains or its business; or state that it has taken no such steps. Including anti-slavery and trafficking obligations in its contracts (through business policies or otherwise) is one of the steps an organisation can take.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>The supplier should note that the customer may want to include wording in its supply agreements that have a connection with a supply chain to prohibit the use of forced or trafficked labour. For example, by stating that the supplier will comply with the customer's policy on slavery (and possibly its other business policies too such as anti-bribery and corruption and data protection and security). But depending on the bargaining strengths of the parties, the supplier may require the customer to comply with the supplier's business policies for reputational reasons, for example. The outcome of such negotiations would ultimately depend on the parties and how keen each of them wants to do the transaction.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For further information on the MSA including links to example clauses, see <link href="8-618-8657" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Modern Slavery Act 2015 toolkit</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
            <division id="a403037" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Data protection</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>Where <link href="8-200-3413" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>personal data</ital></link> will be processed under this agreement, the parties will need to consider the impact of any applicable data protection legislation and, where appropriate, suitable data protection clauses will need to be inserted at clause 5, or, alternatively, as part of a data protection schedule to be annexed to this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>The clauses which are appropriate to include, in each case, will depend upon the relationship of the parties, the context of the processing, and the capacity in which each party processes the personal data.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For some specimen personal data processing clauses designed for use in an IT agreement, see:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="w-027-4499" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Personal data processing clauses for IT agreements (UK) (pro-customer version)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><link href="w-026-6854" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Personal data processing clauses for IT agreements (UK) (pro-supplier version)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each set of clauses provide alternative options to cater for different processing scenarios.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For a note setting out the key issues to address when considering the impact of the UK and EU data protection legislation on rights and obligations commonly found in IT contracts, see <link href="w-027-2423" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Data protection issues in IT contracts</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
            <division id="a267131" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Network and Information Systems Regulations 2018</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The parties should consider any obligations they may have under the <link href="https://uk.westlaw.com/Document/IF7301F10477211E8BDBEA2DE5A7DC62E/View/FullText.html?transitionType=Default&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)&amp;amp;firstPage=true" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Network and Information Systems Regulations 2018 (SI 2018/506)</ital></link> (NIS Regulations). The NIS Regulations specify minimum cybersecurity standards and obligations that apply to certain operators of essential services (OES) in the key sectors of energy, transport, health, drinking water supply and distribution, and digital infrastructure, and relevant digital service providers (RDSP) namely, cloud computing service providers, online search engines and online marketplaces. Although the NIS Regulations do not set out prescriptive cybersecurity requirements, compliance with their terms requires appropriate and proportionate security measures to be implemented. This will depend on the cybersecurity risk which is identified. For more information, see <link href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity Directive: UK implementation</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>Where the services are used within the EU, it may also be necessary to consider compliance with any minimum cybersecurity requirements set out in current and planned EU regulations. In particular, where the parties using the services are involved in the provision of certain in-scope services, they will need to consider whether <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/Document/IB4278FC385C011ED95D489F4A09D5022/View/FullText.html?transitionType=Default&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Directive (EU) 2022/2555</ital></link> applies to them. If it does, then similar considerations (to those discussed in relation to the NIS Regulations) will apply. For more information, see <link href="w-037-2098" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, NIS 2 Directive: overview</ital></link> and <link href="7-628-0350" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, EU cybersecurity framework</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <division id="a343779" level="3">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Supplier as an RDSP</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>An RDSP is defined as:</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>"a person who provides a digital service in the UK and satisfies the following conditions:</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>(i) the head office for that provider is in the UK or that provider has nominated a representative who is established in the UK;</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>(ii) the provider is not a micro or small enterprise as defined in Commission Recommendation 2003/361/EC(8)."</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>(<link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-014-4447?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=PLDocumentLink&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)&amp;amp;ppcid=384f14b7774f431c9777775f64b1b58d" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Regulation 1(3)</ital></link><ital>, NIS Regulations</ital>.)</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Regulation 14a requires any RDSP which has its head office outside the UK, but which offers digital services within the UK to nominate in writing a representative in the UK and notify the ICO of the name and contact details of that representative.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>A small enterprise is defined as an enterprise that employs fewer than 50 persons and whose annual turnover or annual balance sheet total does not exceed EUR10 million <link href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CElEX:32003H0361" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>(Commission Recommendation of 6 May 2003 concerning the definition of micro, small and medium-sized enterprises)</ital></link>. A microenterprise is defined as an enterprise that employs fewer than ten persons and whose annual turnover or annual balance sheet total does not exceed EUR2 million.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>In <link href="https://uk.westlaw.com/Document/I81C45920477311E8AE1D8EE57AB3ECF5/View/FullText.html" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>regulation 1(2)</ital></link>, "digital service" is defined as:</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>"a service within the meaning of point (b) of Article 1(1) of Directive 2015/1535 which is of any the following kinds:</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>(a) online marketplace;</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>(b) online search engine;</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>(c) cloud computing service."</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Determining what constitutes a cloud computing service is not clear cut but the UK government has clarified that SaaS services will be covered to the extent they are scalable and elastic, see <link anchor="a322046" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Is my organisation an RDSP?</ital></link></paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Accordingly, the supplier is likely to fall within the definition of an RDSP under the NIS Regulations and will need to decide whether it wishes to add any additional obligations to the agreement to address any of the obligations imposed on it under that legislation.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The main obligations imposed on RDSPs under <link href="_blank" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Regulation 12</ital></link> are that RDSPs:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>must identify and take appropriate and proportionate measures to manage the risks posed to the security of network and information systems on which it relies to provide, within the EU, either an online marketplace, online search engine or cloud computing service.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>must notify the Information Commissioner's Office (ICO) without undue delay and in any event <bold>no later than 72 hours after becoming aware of </bold>any incident having a substantial impact on the provision of any of the digital services mentioned above, providing sufficient information to enable the ICO to determine the significance of any cross-border impact.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information, see <link anchor="a382583" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity Directive: UK implementation: RDSPs: security obligations</ital></link> and <link anchor="a483636" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>RDSPs: incident reporting</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a480483" level="3">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Cybersecurity drafting issues</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The supplier should consider whether it wishes to impose some basic cybersecurity obligations on the customer and to ensure it does not introduce viruses or vulnerability into the supplier's systems. The supplier may also may wish to define the scope of its obligations around compliance with security standards (for example, ISO 27001), the supplier's data encryption obligations and frequency of vulnerability testing. This could be done by including a mandatory cybersecurity policy in <internal.reference refid="a486123">Schedule 3</internal.reference>. Whether this is sufficient to ensure a supplier has taken appropriate and proportionate measures to manage the risk posed will depend on the specific cybersecurity risks the supplier has identified and the level of interaction the customer's system and data will have with that of the supplier. For more information on assessing cybersecurity risk, see <link href="w-034-5348" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity risk assessments and reporting (UK)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The supplier may also want to consider introducing some mechanism whereby the customer is obliged to report cyber incidents to it that may impact the services, so it can assess whether it needs to make a corresponding report to the ICO. This might not be necessary depending on the level of control and monitoring the supplier already exercises over the services. See, for example, <internal.reference refid="a768414">drafting note, Audit</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For an example of more extensive cyber obligations which could be imposed, see <link anchor="a743741" href="1-501-4459" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Managed services agreement: clause 10. Warranties</ital></link> and <link anchor="a313997" href="1-501-4459" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>clause 8. Security</ital></link>. These are drafted in the context of a managed services agreement (and impose obligations on the supplier, rather than the customer) so would need to be adapted.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
              <division id="a626794" level="3">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Customer as a potential RDSP or OES</headtext>
                </head>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The customer may, itself, be an RDSP or an OES and therefore subject to its own cybersecurity obligations under the NIS Regulations.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For a definition of an OES, see <link anchor="a873370" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity Directive: UK implementation: Identification or Designation as an OES</ital></link>. For the main obligations imposed on an OES, see <link anchor="a773160" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity Directive: UK implementation: OESs: security obligations</ital></link> and <link anchor="a478782" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>OESs: incident reporting</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>If this is the case, the customer may look to impose reciprocal obligations on the supplier, in order to manage any risks posed to the security of its network and information systems through its interactions with the supplier, and ensure it can notify incidents to its relevant competent authority.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Again, this would be fact dependant and it may be unlikely that the customer would have any negotiating power to introduce such provisions, particularly as it is purchasing non- (or less) customised, more generic, "built for the internet", "web-ready" services that characterise SaaS.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>In such case, the customer may be limited to exercising appropriate due diligence over the supplier and managing its own customer-side risks, see <link anchor="a824363" href="w-034-5348" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity risk assessments and reporting (UK): Service provider and supply chain risk assessment</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The National Cyber Security Centre has published guidance for OESs which includes advice on how to pass obligations up the supply chain and what considerations should be made in different circumstances (see <link href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/nis-guidance-collection" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>National Cyber Security Centre: NCSC CAF guidance</ital></link>).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>If the customer is an OES it should also refer to any specific guidance issued by its relevant competent authority. The ICO has issued <link href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/the-guide-to-nis/digital-service-providers/" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>guidance</ital></link> for potential RDSPs. For more information, see <link anchor="a982045" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity Directive: UK implementation: Achieving compliance in practice</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </division>
            <division id="a536378" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Online intermediation service providers</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The <link href="w-019-6282" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>retained EU law</ital></link> version of the <link href="w-023-2903" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Platform to Business Regulation</ital></link> (Regulation (EU) 2019/1150), which has applied since 12 July 2020, requires online intermediation service providers (such as providers of online e-commerce market places, software application services and social media services) and online search engines to comply with certain transparency obligations, mainly by including information in their terms and conditions or, for search engines, publishing it on their websites. For more information on the rules see <link href="w-021-0867" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Online platforms: dealings with consumers and business users</ital></link> and in particular the sections <link anchor="a233509" href="w-021-0867" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Who is covered?</ital></link> And<link anchor="a642656" href="w-021-0867" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital> What rules does the Platform to Business Regulation contain?</ital></link></paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For an OIS to be in scope for the Platform to Business Regulation it must allow business users to offer goods or services to consumers, with a view to facilitating the initiating of direct transactions between those business users and consumers, irrespective of where those transactions are ultimately concluded (<ital>Article 2(2)(b), Platform to Business Regulation</ital>).</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>This document assumes that the services in question are not being used to facilitate direct transactions (for example, the service is not underpinning an e-commerce market place), and therefore not caught by the Platform to Business Regulation.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>However this assumption should be interrogated and if this is not the case, then the parties will need to consider these requirements further and decide whether they need to be reflected in any terms and conditions that may be formed between them and their business user.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
            <division id="a952746" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Video-sharing platforms</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>A service providing a video-sharing platform (VSP) as defined in <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-027-8914?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=PLDocumentLink&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL">section 368S of the Communications Act 2003</link> (CA 2003) must take appropriate measures to prevent harmful content being uploaded, which could include imposing additional terms and conditions. For details, see <link anchor="co_anchor_a999145" href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-024-1729?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL">Practice note, Video-sharing platforms: Content uploaded on VSP service</link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>The rules affect VSP services, that is, certain social media sites that allow audiovisual content to be shared and live-streaming audiovisual services such as pornography websites.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For the purposes of this standard document, we have assumed that these requirements will not apply because neither the supplier nor the services nor the software is providing a VSP service (see <internal.reference refid="a860362">Drafting note, Assumptions</internal.reference>). However, if the supplier is providing a VSP service then it will need to consider the obligation to take appropriate measures against harmful content and whether it needs to include any additional obligations in the terms and conditions.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Online Safety Act 2023 (OSA) will replace the legislation covering VSPs, once the relevant provisions commence. From then on, VSPs will be regulated by the OSA (although no longer defined as such).  The OSA regulates services that enable users to share user generated content (user-to-user services) and search engine services with a view, in particular, to protecting children and tackling illegal content online. The parties should consider whether the provisions of the OSA may apply to them and whether any preparatory activities are required. For more information see <link href="w-030-3139" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Online Safety Act 2023</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>A VSP operating in the EU is designated as a core platform service under the Digital Markets Act, see <internal.reference refid="a310692">Drafting note, Digital Markets Act (EU)</internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
            <division id="a310692" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Digital Markets Act (EU)</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The <link href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=uriserv%3AOJ.L_.2022.265.01.0001.01.ENG&amp;amp;toc=OJ%3AL%3A2022%3A265%3ATOC%20" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>EU Digital Markets Act</ital></link> ((EU) 2022/1925) (DMA) entered force on 1 November 2022. It provides new rules for "gatekeeper" platforms that provide "core platform services". Cloud computing services are one of the ten core platform services designated under the DMA, which also include social networks, search engines and VSP, see <internal.reference refid="a952746">Drafting note, Video-sharing platforms</internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>To qualify as a gatekeeper, an undertaking must provide services in the EU and satisfy three qualitative criteria:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>it has a significant impact on the EU market.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>its core platform service is an important gateway for business users to reach end users.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>it has an entrenched and durable position.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
              <para>
                <paratext>Gatekeeper status will be presumed if the undertaking has an annual EU turnover of EUR7.5 billion in each of the last three financial years and it provides the same core platform service in at least three EU member states and in the last financial year has at least 45 million monthly active end users and 10,000 yearly active business users. An undertaking which is designated as a gatekeeper must comply with a number of restrictions and obligations. For more information see <link href="w-038-9380" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Digital Markets Act (EU): overview</ital></link> and <link href="w-040-0659" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Article, Digital markets regulation: comparing the new EU and UK regimes</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For the purposes of this standard document, we have assumed that the DMA will not apply because the supplier and customer are both UK registered businesses, operating in the UK and the services will only be provided in the UK.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
            <division id="a717833" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Digital Services Act (EU)</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>The parties should consider any obligations they may have under the <link href="https://uk.westlaw.com/Document/I67497F4155CD11EDBB23C6AE78B90E18/View/FullText.html" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Digital Services Act (Regulation (EU) 2022/2065)</ital></link> (DSA). The DSA applies to intermediary services provided to service recipients established or resident in an EU member state, irrespective of where the service provider is established. The DSA imposes requirements on providers which range from "mere conduits" to "hosting services providers" and ultimately to those designated "very large platforms"; the broader the scope of the provider's activities, the more obligations that apply.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Recitals provide helpful clarification on how the DSA treats cloud services. Hosting services include cloud computing (Recital 29), however cloud computing or web-hosting services are not likely to be online platforms and so will not be subject to the additional obligations that those service providers incur (Recital 13).</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For the purposes of this standard document, we have assumed that the DSA will not apply because the services will only be provided to service recipients established or resident in the UK.</paratext>
              </para>
              <para>
                <paratext>For more information see <link href="w-038-4350" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Digital Services Act (EU): overview</ital></link> and for drafting clarifying that a service is only provided in the UK, <link href="w-039-2355" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Online marketplace terms between operator and suppliers</ital></link>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
            <division id="a860362" level="2">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Assumptions</headtext>
              </head>
              <para>
                <paratext>This standard document is drafted on the following assumptions:</paratext>
              </para>
              <list type="bulleted">
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier and the customer are limited companies incorporated in the UK and the service is intended for use in the UK. If either party is organised or operates in a non-UK jurisdiction, or the service may be used or accessed from a non-UK jurisdiction, the agreement may need to be modified to comply with applicable local laws.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The parties are dealing with each other in the course of their respective businesses. This means that the UK rules protecting consumers will not apply. (For more information on those rules, see <link href="w-022-4729" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice notes, Consumer contracts: is it a consumer contract?</ital></link>, <link href="w-022-3748" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Consumer contracts: which rules apply?</ital></link><ital>, </ital><link href="w-023-1479" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Consumer contracts: supplying services</ital></link><ital> </ital> and <link href="w-023-1455" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Consumer contracts: suppling digital content</ital></link>.) Note that this agreement should not be used in a business-to-consumer transaction.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Any assumptions regarding <link href="8-200-3413" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>personal data</ital></link> set out in any drafting notes or resources relating to data protection are correct.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The customer is not acting as an OES or RDSP under the NIS Regulations, see <internal.reference refid="a267131">Drafting note, Network and Information Systems Regulations 2018</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier is not an online intermediation service provider, or an online search engine, for the purposes of the <link href="w-019-6282" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>retained EU law</ital></link> version of the <link href="w-023-2903" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Platform to Business Regulation</ital></link> (Regulation (EU) 2019/1150), and the services and the software will not be used for such purposes, see <internal.reference refid="a536378">Drafting note, Online intermediation service providers</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier does not provide a video-sharing platform (VSP) as defined in <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-027-8914?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=PLDocumentLink&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL">section 368S of the Communications Act 2003</link> (CA 2003) and the services and the software will not be used for such purposes, see <internal.reference refid="a952746">Drafting note, Video-sharing platforms</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
                <list.item>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The EU Digital Markets Act and the EU Digital Services Act do not apply see <internal.reference refid="a310692">Drafting note, Digital Markets Act (EU)</internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a717833">Drafting note, Digital Services Act (EU)</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </list.item>
              </list>
            </division>
          </division>
          <division id="a455608" level="1">
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Drafting for Brexit</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>On 31 January 2020 (<link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-015-8342?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL">exit day</link>), the UK left the EU and the UK-EU withdrawal agreement entered into force. Following the end of the <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-023-9796?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL">UK-EU transition period</link> at 11.00 pm UK time on 31 December 2020, <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-019-6282?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL">retained EU law</link> and the remaining withdrawal agreement provisions entered into force, and the <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-029-0843?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL">future relationship agreements</link> (including the UK-EU trade and co-operation agreement) started to apply on a provisional basis, eventually entering into force at 11.00 pm (UK time) on 30 April 2021. This resource has been reviewed and reflects the position from the end of the transition period.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>For general information on the withdrawal agreement, future relationship agreements, and the operation of UK law following the end of the transition period, see <link href="https://1.next.westlaw.com/Document/I1821dcc40c0211e89bf099c0ee06c731/View/FullText.html?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;ppcid=ea4156ebfba94e05992fecd56fe3d415&amp;amp;contextData=(sc.Default)" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>UK legal change post-transition and UK-EU agreements toolkit</ital></link> and Practical Law’s <link href="_new" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Brexit page</ital></link>.</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>For more information on the impact of Brexit on the specific practice areas covered by this resource, see  the following Practice notes:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="w-017-3813" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Brexit: implications for intellectual property rights</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link anchor="a871801" href="3-107-3683" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Overview: UK competition law: Brexit and competition law</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="w-016-7309" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Brexit: implications for data protection</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="w-004-3766" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Brexit: implications for commercial law</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link href="w-018-9870" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Brexit: implications for cybersecurity in the UK</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </division>
        </drafting.note>
        <cover.sheet>
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>Software as a service subscription agreement</headtext>
          </head>
          <party.name>Supplier</party.name>
          <AdditionalPartyType>
            <static.and>and</static.and>
            <party.name>Customer</party.name>
          </AdditionalPartyType>
        </cover.sheet>
        <intro default="true">
          <intro.date>This agreement is dated [DATE]</intro.date>
        </intro>
        <parties>
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>PARTIES</headtext>
          </head>
          <party executionmethod="contract" id="a732213" status="individual">
            <identifier>(1)</identifier>
            <defn.item>
              <defn>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[FULL COMPANY NAME] incorporated and registered in England and Wales with company number [NUMBER] whose registered office is at [REGISTERED OFFICE ADDRESS]</paratext>
                </para>
              </defn>
              <defn.term>Supplier</defn.term>
            </defn.item>
          </party>
          <party executionmethod="contract" id="a146404" status="individual">
            <identifier>(2)</identifier>
            <defn.item>
              <defn>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[FULL COMPANY NAME] incorporated and registered in England and Wales with company number [NUMBER] whose registered office is at [REGISTERED OFFICE ADDRESS]</paratext>
                </para>
              </defn>
              <defn.term>Customer</defn.term>
            </defn.item>
          </party>
        </parties>
        <recitals>
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>BACKGROUND</headtext>
          </head>
          <clause id="a299878">
            <identifier>(A)</identifier>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Supplier has developed certain software applications and platforms which it makes available to subscribers via the internet on a pay-per-use basis for the purpose of [DETAILS].</paratext>
            </para>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a122341">
            <identifier>(B)</identifier>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Customer wishes to use the Supplier's service in its business operations.</paratext>
            </para>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a389374">
            <identifier>(C)</identifier>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Supplier has agreed to provide and the Customer has agreed to take and pay for the Supplier's service subject to the terms and conditions of this agreement.</paratext>
            </para>
          </clause>
        </recitals>
        <operative xrefname="clause">
          <head align="left" preservecase="true">
            <headtext>Agreed terms</headtext>
          </head>
          <clause id="a588274">
            <identifier>1.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Interpretation</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a726334" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Interpretation</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000010" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause contains definitions used in the rest of the agreement, and interpretation provisions.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>See <link href="5-107-3795" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Interpretation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a945568">
              <identifier>1.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The definitions and rules of interpretation in this clause apply in this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
              <defn.item id="a951312">
                <defn.term>Authorised Users</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>those employees, agents and independent contractors of the Customer who are authorised by the Customer to use the Services and the Documentation, as further described in <internal.reference refid="a859728">clause 2.2(d)</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a455822">
                <defn.term>Business Day</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>a day other than a Saturday, Sunday or public holiday in England when banks in London are open for business.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a170593">
                <defn.term>Change of Control</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>[shall be as defined in section 1124 of the Corporation Tax Act 2010, and the expression <bold>change of control</bold> shall be interpreted accordingly <bold>OR</bold> the beneficial ownership of more than 50% of the issued share capital of a company or the legal power to direct or cause the direction of the general management of the company, and <bold>controls</bold>, <bold>controlled</bold> and the expression <bold>change of control</bold> shall be interpreted accordingly.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a260945">
                <defn.term>Confidential Information</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>information that is proprietary or confidential and is either clearly labelled as such or identified as Confidential Information in <internal.reference refid="a811676">clause 11.1</internal.reference><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a119221">
                <defn.term>Customer Data</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the data inputted by the Customer, Authorised Users, or the Supplier on the Customer's behalf for the purpose of using the Services or facilitating the Customer's use of the Services.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a739652" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Customer Data</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000011" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Most suppliers are moving towards adding express terms to their agreements that permit them to collect and analyse data related to the “use” of the SaaS service on an aggregated anonymised basis, for example, size of database, number of log-ins, duration of log-ins and number of processes/queries run.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a926035">
                <defn.term>Documentation</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the document made available to the Customer by the Supplier online via [INSERT WEB ADDRESS] or such other web address notified by the Supplier to the Customer from time to time which sets out a description of the Services and the user instructions for the Services.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a997257">
                <defn.term>Effective Date</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the date of this agreement.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a836428">
                <defn.term>Heightened Cybersecurity Requirements</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any laws, regulations, codes, guidance (from regulatory and advisory bodies. Whether mandatory or not), international and national standards, [industry schemes] and sanctions, which are applicable to either the Customer or an Authorised User [(but not the Supplier)] relating to security of network and information systems and security breach and incident reporting requirements, which may include the cybersecurity Directive ((EU) 2016/1148), Commission Implementing Regulation ((EU) 2018/151), the Network and Information systems Regulations 2018 (SI 506/2018), all as amended or updated from time to time.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a209098" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Heightened cybersecurity Requirements (optional)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000012" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This definition is used in <internal.reference refid="a604086">clause 7.3(a)(iv)</internal.reference> as part of the supplier's warranty disclaimer. A customer may only accept <internal.reference refid="a604086">clause 7.3(a)(iv)</internal.reference> where the wording in the second set of square brackets is included (i.e. where this definition only covers those more stringent cybersecurity requirements which the Supplier itself would not otherwise be subject to).</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>From the customer's perspective, it is key to understand what the supplier's processes and procedures are. This allows the customer to assess the suitability of these measures to ensure that they are "appropriate technical and organisational measures" from a UK GDPR and EU GDPR perspective and also suitably protect confidential data of the customer.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a246852">
                <defn.term>Initial Subscription Term</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the initial term of this agreement as set out in <internal.reference refid="a325941">Schedule 2</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a541869">
                <defn.term>[Mandatory Policies</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the [Customer's <bold>OR</bold> Supplier's] business policies [and codes] [attached <bold>OR</bold> listed] in <internal.reference refid="a486123">Schedule 3</internal.reference>, as amended by notification to the [Supplier <bold>OR</bold> Customer] from time to time.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a110245" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Mandatory Policies</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000013" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This definition relates to the optional compliance requirement at <internal.reference refid="a907343">clause 11.12</internal.reference> which offers two drafting options. The first is a requirement on the customer to comply with the supplier's policies, and the second is a requirement on the supplier to comply with the customer's policies. Ensure that this definition is consistent with the approach taken in <internal.reference refid="a907343">clause 11.12</internal.reference></paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>See further the integrated drafting notes at <internal.reference refid="a622355">clause 11</internal.reference> and also <internal.reference refid="a345826">Drafting note, Supply chain issues: slavery and human trafficking</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a735260">
                <defn.term>Normal Business Hours</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>[8.00 am to 6.00 pm] local UK time, each Business Day.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a595679">
                <defn.term>Renewal Period</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the period described in <internal.reference refid="a819484">clause 14.1</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a525598">
                <defn.term>Services</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the subscription services provided by the Supplier to the Customer under this agreement via [INSERT WEB ADDRESS] or any other website notified to the Customer by the Supplier from time to time, as more particularly described in the Documentation.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a839242">
                <defn.term>Software</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the online software applications provided by the Supplier as part of the Services.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a973374">
                <defn.term>Subscription Fees</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the subscription fees payable by the Customer to the Supplier for the User Subscriptions, as set out in <internal.reference refid="a171538">paragraph 1</internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a417671">
                <defn.term>Subscription Term</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>has the meaning given in <internal.reference refid="a819484">clause 14.1</internal.reference>  (being the Initial Subscription Term together with any subsequent Renewal Periods).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a625548">
                <defn.term>Support Services Policy</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Supplier's policy for providing support in relation to the Services as made available at [INSERT WEB ADDRESS] or such other website address as may be notified to the Customer from time to time.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a954152">
                <defn.term>User Subscriptions</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the user subscriptions purchased by the Customer pursuant to <internal.reference refid="a877439">clause 9.1</internal.reference> which entitle Authorised Users to access and use the Services and the Documentation in accordance with this agreement.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item id="a373261">
                <defn.term>Virus</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>any thing or device (including any software, code, file or programme) which may: prevent, impair or otherwise adversely affect the operation of any computer software, hardware or network, any telecommunications service, equipment or network or any other service or device; prevent, impair or otherwise adversely affect access to or the operation of any programme or data, including the reliability of any programme or data (whether by re-arranging, altering or erasing the programme or data in whole or part or otherwise); or adversely affect the user experience, including worms, trojan horses, viruses and other similar things or devices.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
              </defn.item>
              <defn.item condition="optional" id="a407908">
                <defn.term>Vulnerability</defn.term>
                <defn>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>a weakness in the computational logic (for example, code) found in software and hardware components that when exploited, results in a negative impact to the confidentiality, integrity, or availability, and the term <defn.term>Vulnerabilities</defn.term> shall be interpreted accordingly.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </defn>
                <drafting.note id="a880875" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Vulnerability (optional)</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000014" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>This concept concerns security vulnerabilities that may be present in software or hardware and is based on the definition used by US National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </defn.item>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a209059">
              <identifier>1.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Clause, schedule and paragraph headings shall not affect the interpretation of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a646994">
              <identifier>1.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A person includes an individual, corporate or unincorporated body (whether or not having separate legal personality) [and that person's legal and personal representatives, successors or permitted assigns].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a67611">
              <identifier>1.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to a company shall include any company, corporation or other body corporate, wherever and however incorporated or established.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a163350">
              <identifier>1.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Unless the context otherwise requires, words in the singular shall include the plural and in the plural shall include the singular.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a779026">
              <identifier>1.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Unless the context otherwise requires, a reference to one gender shall include a reference to the other genders.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a339116">
              <identifier>1.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to a statute or statutory provision is a reference to it as it is in force as at the date of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a326664">
              <identifier>1.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to a statute or statutory provision shall include all subordinate legislation made as at the date of this agreement under that statute or statutory provision.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a114753">
              <identifier>1.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A reference to <bold>writing</bold> or <bold>written</bold> excludes fax [and email <bold>OR</bold> but not email].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a176250">
              <identifier>1.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>References to clauses and schedules are to the clauses and schedules of this agreement; references to paragraphs are to paragraphs of the relevant schedule to this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a522918">
            <identifier>2.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>User subscriptions</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a935915" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>User subscriptions</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000015" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>Under this clause, the supplier grants to the customer a right to permit the authorised users to use the services and the documentation during the subscription term and sets out a number of usage restrictions. This right is conditional on the customer having purchased the user subscriptions.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Clear drafting of this licence scope is key. See, for example, <link href="D-101-1451" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>SAP UK Ltd v Diageo Great Britain Ltd [2017] EWHC 189 (TCC)</ital></link><ital> </ital>and <link href="w-025-9434" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Article, Indirect licensing: update on SAP v Diageo</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>It is assumed that the supplier and the customer will agree that a certain number of authorised users will have access to the services on a "one use per user subscription" basis (<internal.reference refid="a767641">clause 2.2(a)</internal.reference>) and that user subscriptions cannot be used by more than one authorised user (<internal.reference refid="a684781">clause 2.2(b)</internal.reference>). An authorised user will typically be an employee of the contractor, but may also include the customer's consultants and other independent contractors, and conceivably customers, suppliers or other business "partners" of the customer.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a464519">clause 2.2(c)</internal.reference> to <internal.reference refid="a496563">clause 2.2(f)</internal.reference> set out the customer's obligations in relation to its authorised users, including the use of passwords and other security matters.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a793646">clause 2.3</internal.reference> sets out certain fairly standard terms that the supplier would normally wish to see in this type of arrangement in order to protect its services and related documentation, including preventing the customer from using the services to store or transmit unlawful, infringing and discriminating material; copying, duplicating and creating derivative works of the services and/or documentation; accessing the services and/or documentation to build a competing service and so on.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a997761">
              <identifier>2.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Subject to the Customer purchasing the User Subscriptions in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a801736">clause 3.3</internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a877439">clause 9.1</internal.reference>, the  restrictions set out in this <internal.reference refid="a522918">clause 2</internal.reference> and the other terms and conditions of this agreement, the Supplier hereby grants to the Customer a non-exclusive, non-transferable right and licence, without the right to grant sublicences, to permit the Authorised Users to use the Services and the Documentation during the Subscription Term solely for the Customer's internal business operations.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a491978">
              <identifier>2.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>In relation to the Authorised Users, the Customer undertakes that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a767641">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the maximum number of Authorised Users that it authorises to access and use the Services and the Documentation shall not exceed the number of User Subscriptions it has purchased from time to time;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a684781">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>it will not allow or suffer any User Subscription to be used by more than one individual Authorised User unless it has been reassigned in its entirety to another individual Authorised User, in which case the prior Authorised User shall no longer have any right to access or use the Services and/or Documentation;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a464519">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>each Authorised User shall keep a secure password for their use of the Services and Documentation, that such password shall be changed no less frequently than [FREQUENCY] and that each Authorised User shall keep their password confidential;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a859728">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>it shall maintain a written, up to date list of current Authorised Users and provide such list to the Supplier within [5] Business Days of the Supplier's written request at any time or times;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a674100">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>it shall permit the Supplier or the Supplier's designated auditor to audit the Services in order to establish the name and password of each Authorised User and the Customer's data processing facilities to audit compliance with this agreement. Each such audit may be conducted no more than once per quarter, at the Supplier's expense, and this right shall be exercised with reasonable prior notice, in such a manner as not to substantially interfere with the Customer's normal conduct of business;</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a768414" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Audit</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000016" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Ensure that any rights of audits, which may require the processing of personal data by the supplier, are undertaken in compliance with applicable data protection law. This is likely to require the supplier and the customer to work together.</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>As this agreement is drafted from the perspective of the supplier, <internal.reference refid="a674100">clause 2.2(e)</internal.reference> contains broad rights of audit. For a more detailed, and comprehensive, audit clause, see <link href="w-008-9824" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Audit </ital></link>(and its embedded drafting notes).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a496563">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>if any of the audits referred to in <internal.reference refid="a674100">clause 2.2(e)</internal.reference> reveal that any password has been provided to any individual who is not an Authorised User, then without prejudice to the Supplier's other rights, the Customer shall promptly disable such passwords and the Supplier shall not issue any new passwords to any such individual; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a776211">
                <identifier>(g)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>if any of the audits referred to in <internal.reference refid="a674100">clause 2.2(e)</internal.reference> reveal that the Customer has underpaid Subscription Fees to the Supplier, then without prejudice to the Supplier's other rights, the Customer shall pay to the Supplier an amount equal to such underpayment as calculated in accordance with the prices set out in <internal.reference refid="a171538">paragraph 1</internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference> within [10] Business Days of the date of the relevant audit.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a793646">
              <identifier>2.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall not access, store, distribute or transmit any Viruses, or any material during the course of its use of the Services that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a555949">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>is unlawful, harmful, threatening, defamatory, obscene, infringing, harassing or racially or ethnically offensive;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a951157">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>facilitates illegal activity;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a765530">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>depicts sexually explicit images;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a587993">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>promotes unlawful violence;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a855026">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>is discriminatory based on race, gender, colour, religious belief, sexual orientation, disability; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a631375">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>is otherwise illegal or causes damage or injury to any person or property;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext>and the Supplier reserves the right, without liability or prejudice to its other rights to the Customer, to disable the Customer's access to any material that breaches the provisions of this clause.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a1053926">
              <identifier>2.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall not:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a348904">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>except as may be allowed by any applicable law which is incapable of exclusion by agreement between the parties and except to the extent expressly permitted under this agreement:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a342267">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>attempt to copy, modify, duplicate, create derivative works from, frame, mirror, republish, download, display, transmit, or distribute all or any portion of the Software and/or Documentation (as applicable) in any form or media or by any means; or</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a283548">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>attempt to de-compile, reverse compile, disassemble, reverse engineer or otherwise reduce to human-perceivable form all or any part of the Software or the Services; or</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a1020559">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>access all or any part of the Services and Documentation in order to build a product or service which competes with the Services and/or the Documentation; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a543944">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>use the Services and/or Documentation to provide services to third parties; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a973788">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>subject to <internal.reference refid="a761267">clause 22.1</internal.reference>, license, sell, rent, lease, transfer, assign, distribute, display, disclose, or otherwise commercially exploit, or otherwise make the Services and/or Documentation available to any third party except the Authorised Users, or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a153098">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>attempt to obtain, or assist third parties in obtaining, access to the Services and/or Documentation, other than as provided under this <internal.reference refid="a522918">clause 2</internal.reference>; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a495433">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>introduce or permit the introduction of, any Virus [or Vulnerability] into the Services or the Supplier's network and information systems.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a428221">
              <identifier>2.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall use all reasonable endeavours to prevent any unauthorised access to, or use of, the Services and/or the Documentation and, in the event of any such unauthorised access or use, promptly notify the Supplier.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a907209">
              <identifier>2.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The rights provided under this <internal.reference refid="a522918">clause 2</internal.reference> are granted to the Customer only, and shall not be considered granted to any subsidiary or holding company of the Customer.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a154220">
            <identifier>3.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Additional user subscriptions</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a759832" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Additional user subscriptions</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000017" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a154220">clause 3</internal.reference> allows the customer to purchase additional user subscriptions during the subscription term and sets out the procedure for doing so. The customer must pay the relevant fee for the additional user subscriptions as set out in <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference>. If additional user subscriptions are purchased part way through the initial subscription term or any renewal period, then the fee payable by the customer for the additional user subscriptions will be pro-rated for the remainder of that term or period.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a541339">
              <identifier>3.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Subject to <internal.reference refid="a911140">clause 3.2</internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a801736">clause 3.3</internal.reference>, the Customer may, from time to time during any Subscription Term, purchase additional User Subscriptions in excess of the number set out in <internal.reference refid="a171538">paragraph 1</internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference> and the Supplier shall grant access to the Services and the Documentation to such additional Authorised Users in accordance with the provisions of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a911140">
              <identifier>3.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If the Customer wishes to purchase additional User Subscriptions, the Customer shall notify the Supplier in writing. The Supplier shall evaluate such request for additional User Subscriptions and respond to the Customer with approval or rejection of the request [(such approval not to be unreasonably withheld)]. Where the Supplier approves the request, the Supplier shall activate the additional User Subscriptions within [NUMBER] days of its approval of the Customer's request.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a801736">
              <identifier>3.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If the Supplier approves the Customer's request to purchase additional User Subscriptions, the Customer shall, within 30 days of the date of the Supplier's invoice, pay to the Supplier the relevant fees for such additional User Subscriptions as set out in <internal.reference refid="a898768">paragraph 2</internal.reference> of <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference> and, if such additional User Subscriptions are purchased by the Customer part way through the Initial Subscription Term or any Renewal Period (as applicable), such fees shall be pro-rated from the date of activation by the Supplier for the remainder of the Initial Subscription Term or then current Renewal Period (as applicable).</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a207627">
            <identifier>4.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Services</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a627611" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Services</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000018" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>Under <internal.reference refid="a381119">clause 4.1</internal.reference>, the supplier is placed under a general obligation to provide the services and make available the documentation to the customer. More specifically, the supplier agrees to use commercially reasonable endeavours to make the services available 24 hours a day, seven days a week, except for planned maintenance carried out during the maintenance window and unscheduled maintenance performed outside normal business hours (<internal.reference refid="a789714">clause 4.2</internal.reference>).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The supplier also agrees to provide the customer with the supplier's standard customer support services during normal business hours in accordance with its current support services policy. The supplier should state whether this is included within the fees or is subject to additional cost. This clause states that the customer may purchase <bold>enhanced</bold> support services separately at the supplier's then current rates (<internal.reference refid="a522681">clause 4.3</internal.reference>).</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a381119">
              <identifier>4.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall, during the Subscription Term, provide the Services and make available the Documentation to the Customer on and subject to the terms of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a789714">
              <identifier>4.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall use commercially reasonable endeavours to make the Services available 24 hours a day, seven days a week, except for:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a142199">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>planned maintenance carried out during the maintenance window of [10.00 pm to 2.00 am UK time]; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a84747">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>unscheduled maintenance performed outside Normal Business Hours, provided that the Supplier has used reasonable endeavours to give the Customer at least [[6] Normal Business Hours'] notice in advance.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a522681">
              <identifier>4.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier will, as part of the Services [and at no additional cost to the Customer <bold>OR</bold> and in consideration of the support fees set out in Schedule 1], provide the Customer with the Supplier's standard customer support services during Normal Business Hours in accordance with the Supplier's Support Services Policy in effect at the time that the Services are provided.  The Supplier may amend the Support Services Policy in its sole and absolute discretion from time to time.  The Customer may purchase enhanced support services separately at the Supplier's then current rates.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a391801">
            <identifier>5.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Data protection</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a505340" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Data protection</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000019" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on data protection, and the appropriate clauses to be inserted here, see <internal.reference refid="a403037">Drafting note, Data protection</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a328299">
              <identifier>5.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[INSERT APPROPRIATE DATA PROTECTION CLAUSES].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a248076">
            <identifier>6.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Third party providers</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a635701" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Third party providers</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000020" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a248076">Clause 6</internal.reference> states that the supplier excludes its liability in relation to the content of, and the customer's use of, or correspondence with, any third party websites accessible via the supplier's services, and that the supplier does not endorse or approve any such third party website. A supplier could argue that its position in relation to liability for such third party content is, under general law, analogous to that of an Internet Service Provider (ISP). Under the <link href="1-508-2467" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>E-Commerce (EC Directive) Regulations 2002</ital></link>, an ISP is considered to be an intermediary or a "mere conduit" of information and, as such, escapes liability for damages or criminal or civil action, provided that certain conditions are met. Furthermore, it could be argued that a supplier cannot be expected to be responsible for, or be aware of, the content of third parties' websites which are accessible by the customer via the subscription services that it provides. That said, it would be wise for a supplier that does become aware of illegal content of a site accessible via its services to promptly block its customers' access to that site.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a465229">
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer acknowledges that the Services may enable or assist it to access the website content of, correspond with, and purchase products and services from, third parties via third-party websites and that it does so solely at its own risk. The Supplier makes no representation, warranty or commitment and shall have no liability or obligation whatsoever in relation to the content or use of, or correspondence with, any such third-party website, or any transactions completed, and any contract entered into by the Customer, with any such third party.  Any contract entered into and any transaction completed via any third-party website is between the Customer and the relevant third party, and not the Supplier.  The Supplier recommends that the Customer refers to the third party's website terms and conditions and privacy policy prior to using the relevant third-party website. The Supplier does not endorse or approve any third-party website nor the content of any of the third-party website made available via the Services.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a646812">
            <identifier>7.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Supplier's obligations</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a307171" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Supplier's obligations</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000021" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause sets out fairly standard supplier warranties, exclusions and obligations. Specifically, the supplier will perform the services substantially in accordance with the documentation and with reasonable skill and care. In the event that the services do not conform with such warranty, the supplier will use all reasonable commercial endeavours to correct such non-performance. This is the customer's sole and exclusive remedy for the supplier's non-conformance (<internal.reference refid="a736307">clause 7.2</internal.reference>). If the "sole and exclusive remedy" wording was not included in the agreement, the customer may be able to bring an action for breach of contract against the supplier, in addition to the customer's existing remedies of correcting any non-performance or providing an alternative means of accomplishing the desired performance. This may, subject to the caps and limits on liability set out in <internal.reference refid="a990385">clause 13</internal.reference>, result in the supplier being liable for any direct loss suffered by the customer. Note that any exclusion clauses included in a party's standard terms will be subject to the reasonableness test set out in the <link href="7-505-7728" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977</ital></link> (UCTA) and will be interpreted against the party seeking to rely on them. For a further explanation of the scope of each party's liability under the agreement, please see <internal.reference refid="a901257">Drafting note, Limitation of liability</internal.reference> below.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>In addition, the supplier specifically states that it is not responsible for any delays, delivery failures, or other damage resulting from the transfer of data over communications networks and facilities, including the internet (<internal.reference refid="a604086">clause 7.3(a)(iv)</internal.reference>).</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a836484">
              <identifier>7.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall perform the Services substantially in accordance with the Documentation and with reasonable skill and care.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a736307">
              <identifier>7.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier's obligations at <internal.reference refid="a836484">clause 7.1</internal.reference> shall not apply to the extent of any non-conformance which is caused by use of the Services contrary to the Supplier's instructions, or modification or alteration of the Services by any party other than the Supplier or the Supplier's duly authorised contractors or agents. If the Services do not conform with the terms of clause 7.1, Supplier will, at its expense, use reasonable commercial endeavours to correct any such non-conformance promptly. Such correction constitutes the Customer's sole and exclusive remedy for any breach of the undertaking set out in <internal.reference refid="a836484">clause 7.1</internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a188652">
              <identifier>7.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a302418">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>does not warrant that:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a148941">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Customer's use of the Services will be uninterrupted or error-free; [or]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 condition="optional" id="a358865">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>that the Services, Documentation and/or the information obtained by the Customer through the Services will meet the Customer's requirements; [or]</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 condition="optional" id="a357996">
                  <identifier>(iii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Software or the Services will be free from Vulnerabilities or Viruses; [or]</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <drafting.note id="a548914" jurisdiction="">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>No warranty as to software vulnerabilities (optional)</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <division id="a000022" level="1">
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier may be justified in including the statement at <internal.reference refid="a357996">clause 7.3(a)(iii)</internal.reference> on the basis that it is difficult for any technology provider to guarantee its network and information systems will be free from software vulnerabilities.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>However, this statement might serve as a red flag for customers and alert them to an issue that might not otherwise be raised (for example, it may trigger them to request specific cybersecurity warranties from the supplier). As such, the supplier might choose not to include the language at <internal.reference refid="a357996">clause 7.3(a)(iii)</internal.reference> and rely instead on its general disclaimer of heightened cybersecurity standards at <internal.reference refid="a604086">clause 7.3(a)(iv)</internal.reference> (see <internal.reference refid="a618288">Drafting note, Excluding heightened cybersecurity requirements (optional)</internal.reference>) or choose to remain silent altogether on this point.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </drafting.note>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 condition="optional" id="a604086">
                  <identifier>(iv)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the Software, Documentation or Services will comply with any Heightened Cybersecurity Requirements.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <drafting.note id="a618288" jurisdiction="">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Excluding heightened cybersecurity requirements (optional)</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <division id="a000023" level="1">
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier might consider stating explicitly here that it cannot guarantee that its software will meet any heightened cybersecurity requirements that the customer or its end users may be subject to (whether under the NIS Regulations or otherwise, <internal.reference refid="a267131">Drafting note, Network and Information Systems Regulations 2018</internal.reference></paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The supplier may be justified in doing so, as if the customer, or its end users, are classified as an OEM or RDSP under the NIS Regulations, it may be subject to stricter cybersecurity standards than would otherwise be applicable, and the supplier's software or services may not have been designed with such requirements in mind. In such circumstances, the supplier may require the customer to review the Documentation to reach its own conclusions as to whether the software and services are sufficient to meet any heightened cybersecurity standards that the customer or its end users might be subject to.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>However, as the inclusion of such caveats may only serve to flag a potential issue to the customer, the supplier may prefer to stay silent on this point and rely on an assumption that no such standards would be implied in any event. This approach carries more risk where the customer imposes a general obligation on the supplier to comply "with all applicable laws" as the supplier will want to avoid any arguments as to which laws were applicable in the circumstances.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The customer may only accept <internal.reference refid="a604086">clause 7.3(a)(iv)</internal.reference> where the definition of Heightened Cybersecurity Requirements is limited to those requirements that would not otherwise apply to the supplier anyway, see <internal.reference refid="a209098">Drafting note, Heightened cybersecurity Requirements (optional)</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </drafting.note>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a587661">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>is not responsible for any delays, delivery failures, or any other loss or damage resulting from the transfer of data over communications networks and facilities, including the internet, and the Customer acknowledges that the Services and Documentation may be subject to limitations, delays and other problems inherent in the use of such communications facilities.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a1026977">
              <identifier>7.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement shall not prevent the Supplier from entering into similar agreements with third parties, or from independently developing, using, selling or licensing documentation, products and/or services which are similar to those provided under this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a414097">
              <identifier>7.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier warrants that it has and will maintain all necessary licences, consents, and permissions necessary for the performance of its obligations under this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a352298">
              <identifier>7.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall follow its archiving procedures for Customer Data as set out in its [Back-Up Policy] available at [[WEB ADDRESS] or such other website address as may be notified to the Customer from time to time], as such document may be amended by the Supplier in its sole discretion from time to time. In the event of any loss or damage to Customer Data, the Customer's sole and exclusive remedy against the Supplier shall be for the Supplier to use reasonable commercial endeavours to restore the lost or damaged Customer Data from the latest back-up of such Customer Data maintained by the Supplier in accordance with the archiving procedure described in its [Back-Up Policy]. The Supplier shall not be responsible for any loss, destruction, alteration or disclosure of Customer Data caused by any third party (except those third parties sub-contracted by the Supplier to perform services related to Customer Data maintenance and back-up for which it shall remain fully liable.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a865656" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Customer Data</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000024" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The treatment of data security and back-ups is extremely important in this type of SaaS arrangement. Under clause 7.6, the supplier is under an obligation to comply with its privacy and security policy and its back-up policy.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a783898">
            <identifier>8.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Customer's obligations</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a225766" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Customer's obligations</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000025" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause sets out the customer's main obligations under the agreement. In a SaaS arrangement like this, the supplier will regard it as essential for the customer to give basic commitments about co-operation, access and information.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a264558">clause 8.1(b)</internal.reference> is an obligation on the customer to comply with applicable laws. This provision is especially valuable where the scope of services might change with legislation (for example, in the areas of tax and accounting).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a232514">clause 8.1(c)</internal.reference> relieves the supplier of any responsibility for delays that are caused by the customer.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Under <internal.reference refid="a328646">clause 8.1(d)</internal.reference>, the customer must ensure that the authorised users use the services and the documentation in accordance with the agreement and shall be responsible for the authorised user's breach of any of the terms of it.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a1040249">clause 8.1(e)</internal.reference> requires the customer to make sure that it has obtained all necessary consents that are necessary to enable the supplier to perform its obligations.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a905437">clause 8.1(f)</internal.reference> requires the customer to ensure that its network and systems comply with the relevant specifications provided by the supplier, and <internal.reference refid="a1044295">clause 8.1(g)</internal.reference> makes the customer responsible for the integrity of its network connections and telecommunications links from the customer's systems to the supplier's data centres, and for all problems, loss or damage arising from its network connections or telecommunications links, or caused by the internet.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a674493">
              <identifier>8.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a471548">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>provide the Supplier with:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a80385">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all necessary co-operation in relation to this agreement; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a253877">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>all necessary access to such information as may be required by the Supplier;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <para>
                  <paratext>in order to provide the Services, including but not limited to Customer Data, security access information and configuration services;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a264558">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>without affecting its other obligations under this agreement, comply with all applicable laws and regulations with respect to its activities under this agreement;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a232514">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>carry out all other Customer responsibilities set out in this agreement in a timely and efficient manner. In the event of any delays in the Customer's provision of such assistance as agreed by the parties, the Supplier may adjust any agreed timetable or delivery schedule as reasonably necessary;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a328646">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>ensure that the Authorised Users use the Services and the Documentation in accordance with the terms and conditions of this agreement and shall be responsible for any Authorised User's breach of this agreement;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a1040249">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>obtain and shall maintain all necessary licences, consents, and permissions necessary for the Supplier, its contractors and agents to perform their obligations under this agreement, including without limitation the Services;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a905437">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>ensure that its network and systems comply with the relevant specifications provided by the Supplier from time to time; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a1044295">
                <identifier>(g)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>be, to the extent permitted by law and except as otherwise expressly provided in this agreement, solely responsible for procuring, maintaining and securing its network connections and telecommunications links from its systems to the Supplier's data centres, and all problems, conditions, delays, delivery failures and all other loss or damage arising from or relating to the Customer's network connections or telecommunications links or caused by the internet.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a101858">
              <identifier>8.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall own all right, title and interest in and to all of the Customer Data that is not personal data and shall have sole responsibility for the legality, reliability, integrity, accuracy and quality of all such Customer Data.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a416065" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Customer Data</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000026" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Clause 8.2 makes it clear that the customer owns and is responsible for the accuracy, quality, and so on of the customer data, and also the means by which the customer data is acquired.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a627723">
            <identifier>9.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Charges and payment</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a289854" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Charges and payment</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000027" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>In essence, there are four types of fees payable under this agreement:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Subscription fee payable in respect of the user subscriptions. This fee will be paid in advance and will be based on the number of user subscriptions purchased (<internal.reference refid="a171538">paragraph 1</internal.reference><ital>, Schedule 1</ital>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Fees payable in respect of any additional user subscriptions purchased by the customer during the subscription term (<internal.reference refid="a898768">paragraph 2</internal.reference><ital>, Schedule 1</ital>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Fees payable in respect of any data stored by the customer in excess of the data storage limit set out in the documentation (<internal.reference refid="a657963">paragraph 3</internal.reference><ital>, Schedule 1</ital>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Support fees payable in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a522681">clause 4.3</internal.reference>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a468771">Clause 9.6</internal.reference> provides that the supplier may increase the subscription fees, the additional user subscription fees and/or the excess storage fees at the start of each renewal period upon 90 days' prior notice to the customer.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a877439">
              <identifier>9.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall pay the Subscription Fees to the Supplier for the User Subscriptions in accordance with this <internal.reference refid="a627723">clause 9</internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference> [and the support fees in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a522681">clause 4.3</internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference>].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a862712">
              <identifier>9.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall on the Effective Date provide to the Supplier valid, up-to-date and complete credit card details or approved purchase order information acceptable to the Supplier and any other relevant valid, up-to-date and complete contact and billing details and, if the Customer provides:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a172471">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>its credit card details to the Supplier, the Customer hereby authorises the Supplier to bill such credit card:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a243196">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>on the Effective Date for the Subscription Fees payable in respect of the Initial Subscription Term; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a296602">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>subject to <internal.reference refid="a819484">clause 14.1</internal.reference>, on each anniversary of the Effective Date for the Subscription Fees payable in respect of the next Renewal Period;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a136382">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>its approved purchase order information to the Supplier, the Supplier shall invoice the Customer:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a617042">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>on the Effective Date for the Subscription Fees payable in respect of the Initial Subscription Term; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a909483">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>subject to <internal.reference refid="a819484">clause 14.1</internal.reference>, at least 30 days prior to each anniversary of the Effective Date for the Subscription Fees payable in respect of the next Renewal Period,</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <para>
                  <paratext>and the Customer shall pay each invoice within 30 days after the date of such invoice.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a766580">
              <identifier>9.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If the Supplier has not received payment within [30 days] after the due date, and without prejudice to any other rights and remedies of the Supplier:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a460867">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier may, on no less than 5 Business Days' notice to the Customer and without liability to the Customer, disable the Customer's password, account and access to all or part of the Services and the Supplier shall be under no obligation to provide any or all of the Services while the invoice(s) concerned remain unpaid; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a112429">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>interest shall accrue on a daily basis on such due amounts at an annual rate equal to [3]% over the then current base lending rate of [the Supplier's bankers in the UK] from time to time, commencing on the due date and continuing until fully paid, whether before or after judgment.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a157745">
              <identifier>9.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>All amounts and fees stated or referred to in this agreement:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a366003">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>shall be payable in [pounds sterling];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a914796">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>are, subject to <internal.reference refid="a97199">clause 13.3(b)</internal.reference>, non-cancellable and non-refundable;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a1002837">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>are exclusive of value added tax, which shall be added to the Supplier's invoice(s) at the appropriate rate.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a269871">
              <identifier>9.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If, at any time whilst using the Services, the Customer exceeds the amount of disk storage space specified in the Documentation, the Supplier shall charge the Customer, and the Customer shall pay, the Supplier's then current excess data storage fees. The Supplier's excess data storage fees current as at the Effective Date are set out in <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a468771">
              <identifier>9.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall be entitled to increase the Subscription Fees, the fees payable in respect of the additional User Subscriptions purchased pursuant to <internal.reference refid="a801736">clause 3.3</internal.reference>, the support fees payable pursuant to <internal.reference refid="a522681">clause 4.3</internal.reference> and/or the excess storage fees payable pursuant to <internal.reference refid="a269871">clause 9.5</internal.reference> at the start of each Renewal Period upon 90 days' prior notice to the Customer and <internal.reference refid="a167493">Schedule 1</internal.reference> shall be deemed to have been amended accordingly.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a872071">
            <identifier>10.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Proprietary rights</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a663383" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Proprietary rights</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000028" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>This clause confirms the supplier's ownership of all intellectual property rights in the services and the documentation.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a131014">
              <identifier>10.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer acknowledges and agrees that the Supplier and/or its licensors own all intellectual property rights in the Services and the Documentation. Except as expressly stated herein, this agreement does not grant the Customer any rights to, under or in, any patents, copyright, database right, trade secrets, trade names, trade marks (whether registered or unregistered), or any other rights or licences in respect of the Services or the Documentation.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a885343">
              <identifier>10.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier confirms that it has all the rights in relation to the Services and the Documentation that are necessary to grant all the rights it purports to grant under, and in accordance with, the terms of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a622355">
            <identifier>11.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Confidentiality [and compliance with policies]</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a385669" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Confidentiality</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000029" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="http://www.practicallaw.com/2-107-3829" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Standard clause, Confidentiality</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a263683" href="http://www.practicallaw.com/w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Confidentiality</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <division id="a68832" level="2">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Compliance with policies</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <para>
                    <paratext><internal.reference refid="a907343">clause 11.12</internal.reference> can be used where the customer or supplier has specific business policies and wants to ensure that the other party complies with them. The policies might reflect a party's legal obligations, for instance, its obligations under instruments such as the Modern Slavery Act 2015, the Bribery Act 2010 or the data protection legislation. Alternatively, a party may have adopted business social responsibility policies voluntarily.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>In most goods or services agreements, the obligation is usually on the supplier to comply with the customer's policies. But this may not always be the case: depending on the bargaining strengths of the parties, a supplier may well require the customer to comply with the supplier's policies instead. As this is a pro-supplier agreement, the supplier may want to omit this clause altogether from the first draft provided to the customer.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If the supplier does choose to include this clause, there are two drafting options:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The first is a requirement on the customer to comply with the supplier's policies. This is slightly unusual (the usual position is that a supplier agrees to comply with the customer's policies), but a supplier who is concerned about its reputation may well want to ensure that it is only supplying goods or services to customers who are willing to comply with the supplier's policies on issues such as anti-bribery, modern slavery and ethics.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>The second option is a requirement on the supplier to comply with the customer's policies. This is the more usual approach in a goods or services agreement. A supplier may include this option if, for instance, it has already agreed in principle that it is able to comply with the customer's policies, or the parties already have an ongoing relationship where the supplier is comfortable with complying with the customer's policies.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Whatever approach is taken, check that the definition of <internal.reference refid="a541869">[Mandatory Policies</internal.reference> above is consistent with the approach in this clause.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Note also that if the customer agrees to comply with the supplier's policies, the supplier may want a subsequent right to terminate the agreement if the customer breaches those policies. If this is desired, the supplier could include this additional right to terminate at <internal.reference refid="a236056">clause 14</internal.reference>. For an example of this, see <link anchor="a115208" href="7-623-0751" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, Services agreement (pro-supplier): clause 14.3</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information on general compliance clauses, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-618-9498" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Compliance with laws and policies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a811676">
              <identifier>11.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext><defn.term>Confidential Information</defn.term> means all confidential information (however recorded or preserved) disclosed by a party or its Representatives (as defined below) to the other party and that party's Representatives [whether before or] [after the date of this agreement] in connection with [DESCRIBE TRANSACTION OR CONTRACT], including but not limited to:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a432058">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the [existence and] terms of this agreement [or any agreement entered into in connection with this agreement];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a159289">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any information that would be regarded as confidential by a reasonable business person relating to:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a941556">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the business, assets, affairs, customers, clients, suppliers, [or] plans [, intentions, or market opportunities] of the disclosing party [(or of any member of the group of companies to which the disclosing party belongs)]; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a854244">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>the operations, processes, product information, know-how, designs, trade secrets or software of the disclosing party [(or of any member of the group of companies to which the disclosing party belongs)];</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a218376">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any information developed by the parties in the course of carrying out this agreement and the parties agree that:</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a449840">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>details of the Services, and the results of any performance tests of the Services, shall constitute Supplier Confidential Information; and</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a931085">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Customer Data shall constitute Customer Confidential Information;</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a458681">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any information detailed in Schedule [NUMBER].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext><bold>Representatives</bold> means, in relation to a party, its employees, officers, contractors, subcontractors, representatives and advisers.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a246730">
              <identifier>11.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The provisions of this clause shall not apply to any Confidential Information that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a454891">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>is or becomes generally available to the public (other than as a result of its disclosure by the receiving party or its Representatives in breach of this clause);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a194401">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>was available to the receiving party on a non-confidential basis before disclosure by the disclosing party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a653003">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>was, is or becomes available to the receiving party on a non-confidential basis from a person who, to the receiving party's knowledge, is not bound by a confidentiality agreement with the disclosing party or otherwise prohibited from disclosing the information to the receiving party; [or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a164390">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the parties agree in writing is not confidential or may be disclosed[; or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a278554">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>is developed by or for the receiving party independently of the information disclosed by the disclosing party.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a983265">
              <identifier>11.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party shall keep the other party's Confidential Information secret and confidential and shall not:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a793364">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>use such Confidential Information except for [the purpose of exercising or performing its rights and obligations under or in connection with this agreement <bold>OR</bold> [SPECIFY PURPOSE]] (<defn.term>Permitted Purpose</defn.term>); or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a528766">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>disclose such Confidential Information in whole or in part to any third party, except as expressly permitted by this clause 11.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a469489">
              <identifier>11.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A party may disclose the other party's Confidential Information to those of its Representatives who need to know such Confidential Information for the Permitted Purpose, provided that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a957272">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>it informs such Representatives of the confidential nature of the Confidential Information before disclosure; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a618722">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>at all times, it is responsible for such Representatives' compliance with the confidentiality obligations set out in this clause.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a841356">
              <identifier>11.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A party may disclose Confidential Information to the extent such Confidential Information is required to be disclosed by law, by any governmental or other regulatory authority (including, without limitation, [ANY RELEVANT SECURITIES EXCHANGES]) or by a court or other authority of competent jurisdiction provided that, to the extent it is legally permitted to do so, it gives the other party as much notice of such disclosure as possible [and, where notice of disclosure is not prohibited and is given in accordance with this clause 11.5, it takes into account the reasonable requests of the other party in relation to the content of such disclosure].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a388011">
              <identifier>11.6</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A party may, provided that it has reasonable grounds to believe that the other party is involved in activity that may constitute a criminal offence under the Bribery Act 2010, disclose Confidential Information to the Serious Fraud Office without first informing the other party of such disclosure.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a862414">
              <identifier>11.7</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party reserves all rights in its Confidential Information. No rights or obligations in respect of a party's Confidential Information other than those expressly stated in this [clause <bold>OR</bold> agreement] are granted to the other party, or to be implied from this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a357138">
              <identifier>11.8</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>On termination [or expiry] of this agreement, each party shall:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a821165">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>destroy or return to the other party all documents and materials (and any copies) containing, reflecting, incorporating or based on the other party's Confidential Information;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a709830">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>erase all the other party's Confidential Information from computer and communications systems and devices used by it, including such systems and data storage services provided by third parties (to the extent technically and legally practicable); and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a414410">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>certify in writing to the other party that it has complied with the requirements of this clause, provided that a recipient party may retain documents and materials containing, reflecting, incorporating or based on the other party's Confidential Information to the extent required by law or any applicable governmental or regulatory authority. The provisions of this clause shall continue to apply to any such documents and materials retained by a recipient party, subject to clause [NUMBER] (Termination).</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a1017310">
              <identifier>11.9</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>No party shall make, or permit any person to make, any public announcement concerning this agreement without the prior written consent of the other parties (such consent not to be unreasonably withheld or delayed), except as required by law, any governmental or regulatory authority (including, without limitation, any relevant securities exchange), any court or other authority of competent jurisdiction.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a927990">
              <identifier>11.10</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Except as expressly stated in this agreement, no party makes any express or implied warranty or representation concerning its Confidential Information.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a981475">
              <identifier>11.11</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The above provisions of this <internal.reference refid="a622355">clause 11</internal.reference> shall [continue to apply after termination [or expiry] of this agreement OR survive for a period of [five] years from termination [or expiry] of this agreement].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a907343">
              <identifier>11.12</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[In performing its obligations under this agreement the [Supplier <bold>OR</bold> Customer] shall comply with the Mandatory Policies.]</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a333959">
            <identifier>12.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Indemnity</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a620658" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Indemnity</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000030" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>In <internal.reference refid="a276508">clause 12.1</internal.reference>, the customer gives a broad indemnity for claims and losses "arising out of … the Customer's use of the Services and/or the Documentation".</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a455499">clause 12.2</internal.reference> is a more limited indemnity in the customer's favour in respect of intellectual property infringement claims. For further discussion of intellectual property indemnity provisions, see <link anchor="a735753" href="7-107-4789" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Main issues in software licensing and maintenance contracts: Intellectual property and indemnities</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Also consider whether the supplier's liability under the indemnity is to be limited to the liability cap in <internal.reference refid="a990385">clause 13</internal.reference> or not.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a276508">
              <identifier>12.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall defend, indemnify and hold harmless the Supplier against claims, actions, proceedings, losses, damages, expenses and costs (including without limitation court costs and reasonable legal fees) arising out of or in connection with the Customer's use of the Services and/or Documentation, provided that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a714442">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer is given prompt notice of any such claim;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a135059">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier provides reasonable co-operation to the Customer in the defence and settlement of such claim, at the Customer's expense; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a607629">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer is given sole authority to defend or settle the claim.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a455499">
              <identifier>12.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier shall defend the Customer, its officers, directors and employees against any claim that the Customer's use of the Services or Documentation in accordance with this agreement infringes any [United Kingdom] patent effective as of the Effective Date, copyright, trade mark, database right or right of confidentiality, and shall indemnify the Customer for any amounts awarded against the Customer in judgment or settlement of such claims, provided that:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a380730">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier is given prompt notice of any such claim;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a667354">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer does not make any admission, or otherwise attempt to compromise or settle the claim and provides reasonable co-operation to the Supplier in the defence and settlement of such claim, at the Supplier's expense; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a994430">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier is given sole authority to defend or settle the claim.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a406858">
              <identifier>12.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>In the defence or settlement of any claim, the Supplier may procure the right for the Customer to continue using the Services, replace or modify the Services so that they become non-infringing or, if such remedies are not reasonably available, terminate this agreement on [2] Business Days' notice to the Customer without any additional liability or obligation to pay liquidated damages or other additional costs to the Customer.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a278782">
              <identifier>12.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>In no event shall the Supplier, its employees, agents and sub-contractors be liable to the Customer to the extent that the alleged infringement is based on:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a691308">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a modification of the Services or Documentation by anyone other than the Supplier; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a453728">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer's use of the Services or Documentation in a manner contrary to the instructions given to the Customer by the Supplier; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a635310">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer's use of the Services or Documentation after notice of the alleged or actual infringement from the Supplier or any appropriate authority; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a197417">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer's breach of this agreement.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a90563">
              <identifier>12.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The foregoing  [and <internal.reference refid="a97199">clause 13.3(b)</internal.reference>] state[s] the Customer's sole and exclusive rights and remedies, and the Supplier's (including the Supplier's employees', agents' and sub-contractors') entire obligations and liability, for infringement of any patent, copyright, trade mark, database right or right of confidentiality.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a990385">
            <identifier>13.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Limitation of liability</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a901257" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Limitation of liability</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000031" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The IT industry has since the mid-1990s been the crucible in which the UK courts have hammered out the judicial response under <link href="7-505-7728" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>UCTA</ital></link> and related UK contract and statute law on the effectiveness of contractual clauses seeking to limit contract terms and restrict liability.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a990385">Clause 13</internal.reference> seeks first to confirm that the customer is responsible for results obtained from the service and that the supplier has no liability in relation to what the customer chooses to do with the services (<internal.reference refid="a866254">clause 13.1(a)</internal.reference>); and then, to negate all implied terms (<internal.reference refid="a663309">clause 13.1(b)</internal.reference>), so seeking to cut down the extent and scope of the supplier's obligations at the outset.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Secondly, <internal.reference refid="a445638">clause 13.2</internal.reference> makes a virtue of necessity by stating that death or personal injury arising from negligence cannot be excluded (<link href="4-506-5560" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 2(1)</ital></link><ital>, UCTA</ital>), and nor can liability for fraud or fraudulent misrepresentation. For more information see <link anchor="a1018838" href="9-617-5230" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Limiting liability: statutory and common law controls on limitation clauses: Liabilities parties cannot limit</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Thirdly, <internal.reference refid="a97199">clause 13.3(b)</internal.reference> seeks to limit the supplier's aggregate liability under the contract (and consideration should be given here as to whether or not the indemnity is inside or outside the liability cap – see also in relation to <internal.reference refid="a333959">clause 12</internal.reference> above) to a pre-set sum, either by reference to the contract price or a fixed amount.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The customer should watch out for any attempt by the supplier to seek to include compliance with <internal.reference refid="a391801">clause 5</internal.reference> (data protection) and/or any cybersecurity obligations (including the NIS Regulations) within the supplier's liability cap in <internal.reference refid="a97199">clause 13.3(b)</internal.reference>. For more information on this topic, see <link anchor="a881775" href="w-027-2423" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Data protection issues in IT contracts: Liability for data protection compliance in IT contracts</ital></link> and <link anchor="a629286" href="w-013-8329" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Cybersecurity Directive: UK implementation: Penalties</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>As a rule of thumb, if this is a contract to which UCTA potentially applies (that is, if it is, or could be considered to be, effectively on the supplier's standard terms) then there is a risk that if the liability cap is significantly below the contract price, it could be struck down by the courts as unreasonable. In this situation, damages would be recoverable without limitation, on the basis of the ordinary contract law rules of remoteness. Depending on which formulation is chosen, these rules say that recoverable loss is either:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>Loss which arises naturally from the breach or which may reasonably be supposed to have been in the contemplation of the parties when they made the contract as the probable result of the breach (the classic formulation in <link href="D-000-1778" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Hadley v Baxendale (1854) 9 Exch 341</ital></link>); or</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>All loss which at the time the contract was made was reasonably foreseeable as liable to result from the breach (<link href="D-016-1528" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Victoria Laundry (Windsor) v Newman Industries [1949] 2 KB 528</ital></link>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a97199">Clause 13.3(b)</internal.reference> limits the supplier's liability for all claims to a monetary amount. This is generally the starting point for suppliers.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>Finally, <internal.reference refid="a966431">clause 13.3(a)</internal.reference> in any event seeks to exclude all loss that is special, indirect or consequential. The distinction between "direct" and "indirect" loss is not clear-cut, and there is no easy formulation to determine on which side of the line a particular category or type of loss falls in any specific case. A particular difficulty arises when deciding whether loss of profits is direct or indirect. Recent case law has tended to hold that loss of profits can be a direct loss. In a limitation of liability clause such as this, loss of profits should therefore always be specifically excluded, and described in a way that does not link it with indirect loss. Otherwise, direct loss of profit is unlikely to be excluded, since exclusion clauses are interpreted by the courts <ital>contra proferentem</ital>: that is, against the person seeking to rely on them - in this case, the supplier.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>See the following Practice notes:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="2-520-5359" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: drafting and negotiating</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="6-519-2010" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Excluding or limiting liability for negligence</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="w-006-5549" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: interpretation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="9-617-5230" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Limiting liability: statutory and common law controls on limitation clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <para>
              <paratext><bold>WARNING: you are strongly advised to read the </bold><internal.reference refid="a901257">Drafting note, Limitation of liability</internal.reference><bold> on this clause.</bold></paratext>
            </para>
            <subclause1 id="a710080">
              <identifier>13.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Except as expressly and specifically provided in this agreement:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a866254">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Customer assumes sole responsibility for results obtained from the use of the Services and the Documentation by the Customer, and for conclusions drawn from such use. The Supplier shall have no liability for any damage caused by errors or omissions in any Customer Data, information, instructions or scripts provided to the Supplier by the Customer in connection with the Services, or any actions taken by the Supplier at the Customer's direction;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a663309">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>all warranties, representations, conditions and all other terms of any kind whatsoever implied by statute or common law are, to the fullest extent permitted by applicable law, excluded from this agreement; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a272145">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Services and the Documentation are provided to the Customer on an "as is" basis.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a445638">
              <identifier>13.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Nothing in this agreement excludes the liability of the Supplier:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a456319">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>for death or personal injury caused by the Supplier's negligence; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a424275">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>for fraud or fraudulent misrepresentation.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a394157">
              <identifier>13.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Subject to <internal.reference refid="a710080">clause 13.1</internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a445638">clause 13.2</internal.reference>:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a966431">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier shall have no liability for any loss of profits, loss of business, wasted expenditure, depletion of goodwill and/or similar losses or loss or corruption of data or information, or pure economic loss, or for any special, indirect or consequential loss, costs, damages, charges or expenses; and</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a560751" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Exclusions of liability</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000032" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The customer should scrutinise the list in <ital>clause 13.3(a)</ital> closely and assess whether exclusions of loss or corruption of data or information, loss of profits or loss of goodwill are appropriate or acceptable.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a97199">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier's total aggregate liability to the Customer [(including in respect of the indemnity at <internal.reference refid="a455499">clause 12.2</internal.reference>)], in respect of all breaches of duty occurring within any contract year shall not exceed the cap. [If breaches committed in more than one contract year give rise to a single claim or a series of connected claims, the Supplier’s total liability for those claims shall not exceed the single highest annual cap for those contract years.]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a991199">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[In clause 13.3(b):</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a970882">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>[cap] The cap is the greater of £[MINIMUM AMOUNT] and [NUMBER IN WORDS] per cent ([PERCENTAGE]%) of the total Subscription Fees paid in the contract year in which the breaches occurred. [For a worked example, see [Schedule [NUMBER]];</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a576295">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>[contract year.] A contract year means a 12 month period commencing on the Effective Date or any anniversary of it.]</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <drafting.note id="a245962" jurisdiction="">
                    <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                      <headtext>Supplier's total aggregate liability</headtext>
                    </head>
                    <division id="a000033" level="1">
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Rather than having a liability cap equal to the total fees over the contract term, the supplier is likely to want to ring fence liability in any contract year to an amount equal to the fees paid in that contract year. However, care must be taken when drafting this option to avoid the possibility of introducing multiple liability caps for multiple claims. This issue has been the subject of recent case law, see <link href="w-039-8395" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Legal update, Single not multiple liability cap in IT contract (High Court)</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>If the Supplier prefers to have a liability cap equal to a fixed amount over the term (perhaps where the contract term is for two years or less)  then see <link anchor="a325636" href="w-021-8628" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard document, SaaS subscription agreement (pro-customer): clause 13.3(c)</ital></link>. If this approach is taken then <internal.reference refid="a97199">clause 13.3(b)</internal.reference> can be simplified and <internal.reference refid="a991199">clause 13.3(c)</internal.reference> is no longer required.</paratext>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>For a consideration of the potential pitfalls to avoid and an explanation of why a worked example may be helpful, see <link anchor="a255920" href="w-010-2114" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Limitation of liability: Cap on the supplier's liability</ital></link>.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </division>
                  </drafting.note>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a656813">
              <identifier>13.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>References to liability in this clause 13 include every kind of liability arising under or in connection with this agreement including but not limited to liability in contract, tort (including negligence), misrepresentation, restitution or otherwise.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a571500" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Definition of liability</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000034" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Recent case law has confirmed the importance of consistency between different sub-clauses in a limitation of liability clause, particularly when these sub-clauses are negotiated at different times during a transaction. Using a common definition throughout clause 13 eliminates the issue of ambiguity in interpretation which may weaken contractual protection.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a738740">
              <identifier>13.5</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Nothing in this agreement excludes the liability of the Customer for any breach, infringement or misappropriation of the Supplier’s Intellectual Property Rights.</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a303425" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Customer's liability for IPR infringement</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000035" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Suppliers are routinely carving out IPR infringement from caps on customers’ liability (and some are asking for it on an indemnity basis).</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a236056">
            <identifier>14.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Term and termination</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a894327" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Term and termination</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000036" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext><internal.reference refid="a819484">clause 14.1</internal.reference> provides for the agreement to last for an initial subscription term (as set out in <internal.reference refid="a325941">Schedule 2</internal.reference>), and after that for successive periods of 12 months (renewal periods), unless either party notifies the other of its intention to terminate the agreement at least 60 days before the end of the initial subscription term or any renewal period. The supplier and customer alike should consider whether 60 days is a sufficient period of time. Each party has the right to terminate the contract in the event of the other's insolvency or default (<internal.reference refid="a743645">clause 14.2</internal.reference>). See <link href="3-107-4673" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Termination</ital></link>. <internal.reference refid="a964212">clause 14.3</internal.reference> sets out fairly standard provisions for the consequences of termination. See <link href="3-203-1593" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Consequences of termination</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a819484">
              <identifier>14.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement shall, unless otherwise terminated as provided in this <internal.reference refid="a236056">clause 14</internal.reference>, commence on the Effective Date and shall continue for the Initial Subscription Term and, thereafter, this agreement shall be automatically renewed for successive periods of 12 months (each a <defn.term>Renewal Period</defn.term>), unless:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a135780">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>either party notifies the other party of termination, in writing, at least [60 days] before the end of the Initial Subscription Term or any Renewal Period, in which case this agreement shall terminate upon the expiry of the applicable Initial Subscription Term or Renewal Period; or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a214594">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>otherwise terminated in accordance with the provisions of this agreement;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <para>
                <paratext>and the Initial Subscription Term together with any subsequent Renewal Periods shall constitute the <defn.term>Subscription Term</defn.term>.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a743645">
              <identifier>14.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Without affecting any other right or remedy available to it, either party may terminate this agreement with immediate effect by giving written notice to the other party if:</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a727976" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Termination for cause</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000037" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For further guidance on termination, see <link href="https://uk.practicallaw.thomsonreuters.com/3-107-4673?originationContext=document&amp;amp;transitionType=DocumentItem&amp;amp;contextData=%28sc.Default%29&amp;amp;comp=pluk" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Standard clause, Termination</ital></link> and associated drafting notes, including information on the Corporate Insolvency and Governance Act 2020, which came into force on 26 June 2020.  See also<ital> </ital><link anchor="a387269" href="w-025-9457" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Restrictions on terminating supply contracts in insolvency proceedings: What is a contract for the supply of goods and Software licence agreements services</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>The supplier should also consider whether it wishes to be able to terminate if the customer undergoes a change of control or in the event of a sale of the customer's assets, merger or re-organisation in which the customer is not the surviving entity (see <internal.reference refid="a825057">Drafting note, Assignment</internal.reference>).</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For more information, see <link anchor="a863026" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Termination</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
              <subclause2 id="a672297">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party fails to pay any amount due under this agreement on the due date for payment and remains in default not less than [NUMBER] days after being notified in writing to make such payment;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a207796">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party commits a material breach of any other term of this agreement and (if such breach is remediable) fails to remedy that breach within a period of [NUMBER] days after being notified [in writing] to do so;</paratext>
                </para>
                <drafting.note id="a379204" jurisdiction="">
                  <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                    <headtext>Termination for material breach</headtext>
                  </head>
                  <division id="a000038" level="1">
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The terms "material breach" or "repeatedly breaches", or a breach which is or is not "remediable" are not terms with precise legal definitions. It is not certain, for example, that a material breach equates to a repudiatory breach entitling the innocent party to terminate at common law. Consequently, there will always be some uncertainty as to the sorts of breaches which will give rise to the supplier's right to terminate (see <link anchor="a162091" href="5-559-4767" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts; termination: Termination for material breach</ital></link>).</paratext>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>For more information see <link href="w-016-7906" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Contracts: when can I terminate my contract?</ital></link></paratext>
                    </para>
                  </division>
                </drafting.note>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a188329">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party suspends, or threatens to suspend, payment of its debts or is unable to pay its debts as they fall due or admits inability to pay its debts or is deemed unable to pay its debts within the meaning of section 123 of the Insolvency Act 1986 (<bold>IA 1986</bold>) as if the words "it is proved to the satisfaction of the court" did not appear in sections 123(1)(e) or 123(2) of the IA 1986 <bold>OR</bold> (being an individual) is deemed either unable to pay its debts or as having no reasonable prospect of so doing, in either case, within the meaning of section 268 of the IA 1986 <bold>OR</bold> (being a partnership) has any partner to whom any of the foregoing apply];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a902553">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party commences negotiations with all or any class of its creditors with a view to rescheduling any of its debts, or makes a proposal for or enters into any compromise or arrangement with its creditors other than for the sole purpose of a scheme for a solvent amalgamation of that other party with one or more other companies or the solvent reconstruction of that other party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a664675">
                <identifier>(e)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party applies to court for, or obtains, a moratorium under Part A1 of the Insolvency Act 1986;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a949673">
                <identifier>(f)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a petition is filed, a notice is given, a resolution is passed, or an order is made, for or in connection with the winding up of that other party other than for the sole purpose of a scheme for a solvent amalgamation of that other party with one or more other companies or the solvent reconstruction of that other party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a385613">
                <identifier>(g)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>an application is made to court, or an order is made, for the appointment of an administrator, or if a notice of intention to appoint an administrator is given or if an administrator is appointed, over the other party (being a company, partnership or limited liability partnership);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a177713">
                <identifier>(h)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the holder of a qualifying floating charge over the assets of that other party (being a company or limited liability partnership) has become entitled to appoint or has appointed an administrative receiver;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a339702">
                <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a person becomes entitled to appoint a receiver over the assets of the other party or a receiver is appointed over the assets of the other party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a132537">
                <identifier>(j)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>a creditor or encumbrancer of the other party attaches or takes possession of, or a distress, execution, sequestration or other such process is levied or enforced on or sued against, the whole or any part of the other party's assets and such attachment or process is not discharged within [14] days;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a458446">
                <identifier>(k)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any event occurs, or proceeding is taken, with respect to the other party in any jurisdiction to which it is subject that has an effect equivalent or similar to any of the events mentioned in <internal.reference refid="a188329">clause 14.2(c)</internal.reference> to <ital>clause 14.2(j)</ital> (inclusive);</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a188413">
                <identifier>(l)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party suspends or ceases, or threatens to suspend or cease, carrying on all or a substantial part of its business;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a318029">
                <identifier>(m)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the other party's financial position deteriorates so far as to reasonably justify the opinion that its ability to give effect to the terms of this agreement is in jeopardy; [or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a362399">
                <identifier>(n)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>there is a change of control of the other party[ (within the meaning of section 1124 of the Corporation Tax Act 2010).</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a964212">
              <identifier>14.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>On termination of this agreement for any reason:</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a974805" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Deletion of electronic data</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000039" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>It can be difficult for organisations (particularly Suppliers) to agree to "delete" electronic data. The word "deletion" can mean different things in relation to electronic data, and it is recognised that it is not always possible to delete or erase all traces of the data. As the ICO has opined that the term "deletion", in relation to personal data, should be taken to mean ensuring that the data is beyond use, we consider this is a reasonable deletion standard to use in most circumstances. If this is appropriate in your agreement, suggested wording is as follows:</paratext>
                  </para>
                  <list type="bulleted">
                    <list.item>
                      <para>
                        <paratext>Any electronic data shall be considered deleted for the purpose of this clause where it has been put beyond used by the deleting party.</paratext>
                      </para>
                    </list.item>
                  </list>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>If it is appropriate to delete personal data from a live system, we recommend that a party should also be expected to delete it from any back-up of the information on that system, and the parties may prefer for this to be made explicit as part of the deletion obligation.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
              <subclause2 id="a615774">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>all licences granted under this agreement shall immediately terminate [and the Customer shall immediately cease all use of the Services and/or the Documentation];</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a661090">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>each party shall return and make no further use of any equipment, property, Documentation and other items (and all copies of them) belonging to the other party;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a1056299">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>the Supplier may destroy or otherwise dispose of any of the Customer Data in its possession unless the Supplier receives, no later than ten days after the effective date of the termination of this agreement, a written request for the delivery to the Customer of the then most recent back-up of the Customer Data. The Supplier shall use reasonable commercial endeavours to deliver the back-up to the Customer within 30 days of its receipt of such a written request, provided that the Customer has, at that time, paid all fees and charges outstanding at and resulting from termination (whether or not due at the date of termination). The Customer shall pay all reasonable expenses incurred by the Supplier in returning or disposing of Customer Data; and</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a384583">
                <identifier>(d)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>any rights, remedies, obligations or liabilities of the parties that have accrued up to the date of termination, including the right to claim damages in respect of any breach of the agreement which existed at or before the date of termination shall not be affected or prejudiced.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a693134">
            <identifier>15.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Force majeure</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a667428" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Force majeure</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000040" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>A <ital>force majeure</ital> clause usually excludes liability for breach of contract where delay or failure to perform is as a result of an event outside the control of the party who is in default. The phrase derives from the codified systems of law on the continent. Those events which are to be considered as being "beyond reasonable control" must be drafted so that they are beyond dispute. This may often involve the listing of various examples - such as acts of God, strikes and defaults of suppliers - with a sweep-up clause which is drafted so as to be interpreted widely and not be limited by other items which have been listed.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>In a business-to-business contract, a <ital>force majeure</ital> provision is likely to be subject to the reasonableness test under <link href="5-505-8743" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 3</ital></link> of UCTA, but may well be held reasonable if it is limited to events which are genuinely outside the control of the party relying on them.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>See <link href="3-518-4224" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC">Standard clause, General Contract Clauses: Force Majeure</link>. Consider the force majeure clause in the context of the termination clause.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a960167">
              <para>
                <paratext>Neither party shall be in breach of this agreement or otherwise liable for any failure or delay in the performance of its obligations if such delay or failure results from events, circumstances or causes beyond its reasonable control. The time for performance of such obligations shall be extended accordingly. If the period of delay or non-performance continues for [NUMBER] [weeks <bold>OR</bold> months], the party not affected may terminate this agreement by giving [NUMBER] [days'] written notice to the affected party.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a164320">
            <identifier>16.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Conflict</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a953233" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Conflict</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000041" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="7-107-3836" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Conflict</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a195430" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Conflict</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a559529">
              <para>
                <paratext>If there is an inconsistency between any of the provisions in the main body of this agreement and the Schedules, the provisions in the main body of this agreement shall prevail.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a594084">
            <identifier>17.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Variation</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a650111" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Variation</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000042" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="3-107-3838" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Variation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a436667" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Variation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a373901">
              <para>
                <paratext>No variation of this agreement shall be effective unless it is in writing and signed by the parties (or their authorised representatives).</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a893488">
            <identifier>18.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Waiver</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a859692" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Waiver</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000043" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="http://www.practicallaw.com/0-107-3806" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Standard clause, Waiver</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a947318" href="http://www.practicallaw.com/w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why? : Waiver</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a811444">
              <identifier>18.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A waiver of any right or remedy is only effective if given in writing [and shall not be deemed a waiver of any subsequent right or remedy].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a284683">
              <identifier>18.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>A delay or failure to exercise, or the single or partial exercise of, any right or remedy shall not waive that or any other right or remedy, nor shall it prevent or restrict the further exercise of that or any other right or remedy.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a949188">
            <identifier>19.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Rights and remedies</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a324244" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Rights and remedies</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000044" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="2-203-0725" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Rights and remedies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a778211" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Rights and remedies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a515299">
              <para>
                <paratext>Except as expressly provided in this agreement, the rights and remedies provided under this agreement are in addition to, and not exclusive of, any rights or remedies provided by law.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a310060">
            <identifier>20.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Severance</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a816967" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Severance</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000045" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="9-107-3840" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Severance</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a117161" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Rights and remedies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a312652">
              <identifier>20.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If any provision or part-provision of this agreement is or becomes invalid, illegal or unenforceable, it shall be deemed deleted, but that shall not affect the validity and enforceability of the rest of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a836036">
              <identifier>20.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>If any provision or part-provision of this agreement is deemed deleted under <internal.reference refid="a312652">clause 20.1</internal.reference> the parties shall negotiate in good faith to agree a replacement provision that, to the greatest extent possible, achieves the intended commercial result of the original provision.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a1000301">
            <identifier>21.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Entire agreement</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a564660" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Entire agreement</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000046" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="2-107-3834" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Entire agreement</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext><link anchor="a102696" href="http://www.practicallaw.com/w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Entire agreement</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a241927">
              <identifier>21.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement constitutes the entire agreement between the parties and supersedes and extinguishes all previous and contemporaneous agreements, promises, assurances and understandings between them, whether written or oral, relating to its subject matter.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a984731">
              <identifier>21.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party acknowledges that in entering into this agreement it does not rely on[, and shall have no remedies in respect of,] any statement, representation, assurance or warranty (whether made innocently or negligently) that is not set out in this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a991046">
              <identifier>21.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party agrees that it shall have no claim for innocent or negligent misrepresentation [or negligent misstatement] based on any statement in this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a575000">
              <identifier>21.4</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Nothing in this clause shall limit or exclude any liability for fraud.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a160522">
            <identifier>22.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Assignment</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a825057" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Assignment</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000047" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The customer is not entitled to assign the contract without the supplier's consent, but the supplier may do so without the customer's consent. See:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="5-107-3823" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Assignment and other dealings </ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a120126" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Assignment and other dealings</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a761267">
              <identifier>22.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Customer shall not, without the prior written consent of the Supplier, assign, transfer, mortgage, charge, subcontract, delegate, declare a trust over or deal in any other manner with any of its rights and obligations under this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a224610">
              <identifier>22.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The Supplier may at any time assign, mortgage, charge, subcontract, delegate, declare a trust over or deal in any other manner with any or all of its rights and obligations under this agreement[, provided that it gives prior written notice of such dealing to the Customer].</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a569003">
            <identifier>23.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>No partnership or agency</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a230948" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>No partnership or agency</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000048" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="4-107-3814" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, No partnership or agency</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a358774" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: No partnership or agency</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a66981">
              <para>
                <paratext>Nothing in this agreement is intended to or shall operate to create a partnership between the parties, or authorise either party to act as agent for the other, and neither party shall have the authority to act in the name or on behalf of or otherwise to bind the other in any way (including, but not limited to, the making of any representation or warranty, the assumption of any obligation or liability and the exercise of any right or power).</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a573048">
            <identifier>24.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Third party rights</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a415122" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Third party rights</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000049" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="6-107-3846" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Third party rights</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a867788" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Third party rights</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a789266">
              <identifier>24.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>[Unless it expressly states otherwise, this OR This] agreement does not give rise to any rights under the Contracts (Rights of Third Parties) Act 1999 to enforce any term of this agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 condition="optional" id="a721895">
              <identifier>24.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>The rights of the parties to rescind or vary this agreement are not subject to the consent of any other person.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a355283">
            <identifier>25.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Counterparts</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a885660" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Counterparts</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000050" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="_blank" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Counterparts</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a684888" href="_blank" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Counterparts</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a521787">
              <identifier>25.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement may be executed in any number of counterparts, each of which shall constitute a duplicate original, but all the counterparts shall together constitute the one agreement.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a741774">
              <identifier>25.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Transmission of [an executed counterpart of this agreement (but for the avoidance of doubt not just a signature page) <bold>OR</bold> the executed signature page of a counterpart of this agreement] by email (in PDF, JPEG or other agreed format) shall take effect as the transmission of an executed "wet-ink" counterpart of this agreement. [If [this <bold>OR</bold> either] method of transmission is adopted, without prejudice to the validity of the agreement thus made, each party shall on request provide the other[s] with the "wet ink" hard copy original[s] of their counterpart.]</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a851073">
              <identifier>25.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>No counterpart shall be effective until each party has [provided <bold>OR</bold> delivered] to the other[s] at least one executed counterpart.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a671771">
            <identifier>26.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Notices</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a579274" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Notices</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000051" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on this clause, see:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext>The drafting notes in <link href="http://www.practicallaw.com/5-107-3842" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Standard clauses, Notices</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="http://www.practicallaw.com/3-107-3843" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Notice clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a616007" href="http://www.practicallaw.com/w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkURL"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Notices</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a928712">
              <identifier>26.1</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Any notice given to a party under or in connection with this agreement shall be in writing and shall be:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a488078">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>delivered by hand or by pre-paid first-class post or other next working day delivery service at its registered office (if a company) or its principal place of business (in any other case); or</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a381299">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>sent by email to the following addresses (or an address substituted in writing by the party to be served):</paratext>
                </para>
                <subclause3 id="a145652">
                  <identifier>(i)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Party 1: [ADDRESS].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
                <subclause3 id="a260522">
                  <identifier>(ii)</identifier>
                  <para>
                    <paratext>Party 2: [ADDRESS].</paratext>
                  </para>
                </subclause3>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a456216">
              <identifier>26.2</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Any notice shall be deemed to have been received:</paratext>
              </para>
              <subclause2 id="a579332">
                <identifier>(a)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>if delivered by hand, at the time the notice is left at the proper address;</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 id="a548895">
                <identifier>(b)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>if sent by [pre-paid first-class post or other] next working day delivery service, at [9.00 am] on the [second] Business Day after posting; [or]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
              <subclause2 condition="optional" id="a226003">
                <identifier>(c)</identifier>
                <para>
                  <paratext>if sent by email, at the time of transmission, or, if this time falls outside Business Hours in the place of receipt, when Business Hours resume.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause2>
            </subclause1>
            <subclause1 id="a86573">
              <identifier>26.3</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>This clause does not apply to the service of any proceedings or other documents in any legal action or, where applicable, any arbitration or other method of dispute resolution.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a196364">
            <identifier>27.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Governing law</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a852739" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Governing law</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000052" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The governing law may affect whether or not the provisions of <link href="_blank" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>UCTA</ital></link> apply (although see <link href="_blank" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>section 27</ital></link> of UCTA concerning whether or not choice of law clauses are effective).</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>The parties should also consider whether any other dispute resolution mechanisms are appropriate, such as expert determination for technical issues (such as whether the software conforms to its specification). Arbitration or alternative dispute resolution are not necessarily faster or cheaper, but consider a (non-binding) commitment to pursue these mechanisms for the resolution of contractual disputes.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>See <link anchor="a742310" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Governing law</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <paratext>For more information on the effect of Brexit on litigation, including governing law and jurisdiction clauses, see <link href="w-019-0548" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Brexit: implications for civil justice and judicial co-operation</ital></link>.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a463397">
              <para>
                <paratext>This agreement and any dispute or claim arising out of or in connection with it or its subject matter or formation (including non-contractual disputes or claims) shall be governed by and interpreted in accordance with the law of England and Wales.</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
          <clause id="a201476">
            <identifier>28.</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Jurisdiction</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a575024" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Jurisdiction</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000053" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See <link href="0-107-3646" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Supply contracts: overview: Export contracts: Choice of law and jurisdiction</ital></link> for a consideration of choice of law and jurisdiction provisions. See also:</paratext>
                </para>
                <list type="bulleted">
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="9-522-6848" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Jurisdiction</ital></link><ital>.</ital></paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link href="4-107-3852" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Governing law and jurisdiction clauses</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                  <list.item>
                    <para>
                      <paratext><link anchor="a783056" href="w-014-1583" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Practice note, Boilerplate: do I really need this clause and why?: Jurisdiction</ital></link>.</paratext>
                    </para>
                  </list.item>
                </list>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <subclause1 id="a662297">
              <para>
                <paratext>Each party irrevocably agrees that the courts of England and Wales shall have exclusive jurisdiction to settle any dispute or claim arising out of or in connection with this agreement or its subject matter or formation (including non-contractual disputes or claims).</paratext>
              </para>
            </subclause1>
          </clause>
        </operative>
        <testimonium default="false" wording="contract">
          <para>
            <paratext>This  has been entered into on the date stated at the beginning of it.</paratext>
          </para>
        </testimonium>
        <disclosure.schedule>
          <schedule id="a167493">
            <identifier>Schedule 1</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Subscription Fees</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a810013" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Subscription Fees</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000054" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See <internal.reference refid="a289854">Drafting note, Charges and payment</internal.reference> above.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <clause id="a171538">
              <identifier>1.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Subscription Fees</headtext>
              </head>
              <subclause1 id="a754965">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Subscription Fees shall amount to a total of £[AMOUNT], based on [NUMBER] User Subscriptions at £[AMOUNT] per User Subscription.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
            </clause>
            <clause id="a898768">
              <identifier>2.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Additional User Subscription Fees</headtext>
              </head>
              <subclause1 id="a878225">
                <para>
                  <paratext>Additional User Subscriptions may be purchased by the Customer in accordance with <internal.reference refid="a154220">clause 3</internal.reference> at £[AMOUNT] per User Subscription.</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
            </clause>
            <clause id="a657963">
              <identifier>3.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Excess Storage Fees</headtext>
              </head>
              <subclause1 id="a115490">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Supplier's excess storage fees current as at the Effective Date are set out below: [INSERT EXCESS STORAGE FEES].</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
            </clause>
            <clause id="a908257">
              <identifier>4.</identifier>
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Support Fees</headtext>
              </head>
              <subclause1 id="a263637">
                <para>
                  <paratext>The Supplier's standard and enhanced support fees are set out below: [INSERT DETAILS]</paratext>
                </para>
              </subclause1>
            </clause>
          </schedule>
          <schedule id="a325941">
            <identifier>Schedule 2</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Subscription Term</headtext>
            </head>
            <drafting.note id="a190497" jurisdiction="">
              <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                <headtext>Subscription Term</headtext>
              </head>
              <division id="a000055" level="1">
                <para>
                  <paratext>See <internal.reference refid="a894327">Drafting note, Term and termination</internal.reference> above.</paratext>
                </para>
              </division>
            </drafting.note>
            <clause id="a806601">
              <identifier>1.</identifier>
              <para>
                <paratext>Initial Subscription Term: [INSERT LENGTH OF INITIAL SUBSCRIPTION TERM].</paratext>
              </para>
              <drafting.note id="a789245" jurisdiction="">
                <head align="left" preservecase="true">
                  <headtext>Mandatory Policies: list and attach?</headtext>
                </head>
                <division id="a000056" level="1">
                  <para>
                    <paratext>For a discussion of whether or not the mandatory policies should also be attached to the agreement, see the integrated drafting notes to <link href="6-618-9498#a609148" style="ACTLinkPLCtoPLC"><ital>Standard clause, Compliance with laws and policies: Schedule of Mandatory Policies</ital></link>.</paratext>
                  </para>
                </division>
              </drafting.note>
            </clause>
          </schedule>
          <schedule id="a486123">
            <identifier>Schedule 3</identifier>
            <head align="left" preservecase="true">
              <headtext>Mandatory Policies</headtext>
            </head>
            <para>
              <paratext>[LIST [AND ATTACH] THE MANDATORY POLICIES HERE]</paratext>
            </para>
            <para>
              <paratext>The Mandatory Policies are:</paratext>
            </para>
            <list type="bulleted">
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Modern Slavery and Human Trafficking Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Corporate and Social Responsibility Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Data and Privacy Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Ethics and Anti-Bribery Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Expenses Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Cybersecurity Policy]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
              <list.item>
                <para>
                  <paratext>[Business Continuity and Disaster Recovery]</paratext>
                </para>
              </list.item>
            </list>
          </schedule>
        </disclosure.schedule>
        <signature default="true" pagebreak="true" signaturemessage="no">
          <para>
            <paratext>
              <table frame="none" pgwide="1">
                <tgroup cols="3">
                  <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="33"/>
                  <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="33"/>
                  <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="33"/>
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Signed by [NAME OF DIRECTOR]  for and on behalf of [NAME OF SUPPLIER]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>....................</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Director</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry nameend="3" namest="1" valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Signed by [NAME OF DIRECTOR]  for and on behalf of [NAME OF CUSTOMER]</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>....................</paratext>
                        </para>
                        <para align="left">
                          <paratext>Director</paratext>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry nameend="3" namest="1" valign="top">
                        <para>
                          <paratext/>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
            </paratext>
          </para>
        </signature>
      </body>
      <rev.history>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Online Safety Act 2023</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20231027</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000001" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have updated this resource to reflect the Online Safety Act 2023 (see <internal.reference refid="a952746">Drafting note, Video-sharing platforms</internal.reference>)</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Update to reflect current market practice</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20230901</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000002" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have made general changes to this resource to reflect market practice, including changes to liability provisions see <internal.reference refid="a394157">clause 13.3</internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a245962">Drafting note, Supplier's total aggregate liability</internal.reference> in the light of the Drax case.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>EU Digital Services Act and EU Digital Markets Act</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20230811</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000003" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have added <internal.reference refid="a310692">Drafting note, Digital Markets Act (EU)</internal.reference> and <internal.reference refid="a717833">Drafting note, Digital Services Act (EU)</internal.reference><ital>.</ital></paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Brexit and general update (September 2022)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20220915</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000004" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have updated this resource to simplify the <internal.reference refid="a455608">Drafting note, Drafting for Brexit</internal.reference> section following the expiry of the transition period and to align with general boilerplate drafting changes, for example the removal of fax as a means of giving notice</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>General update (March 2021)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20210315</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000005" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have made various general updates.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>Brexit: end of UK-EU Transition Period, Corporate Insolvency and Governance Act 2020 (October 2020)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20201123</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000006" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have added links to various materials on Brexit to this resource. We have made changes to this resource so it will continue to work correctly after the end of the UK-EU transition period. We have added new subclauses 14.2(e) and 14.2(m) to the termination clause to reflect the coming into force of the Corporate Insolvency and Governance Act 2020.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>New materials on Brexit (January /February 2020)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20200131</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000007" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have added links to various materials on Brexit to this resource</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
        <rev.item>
          <rev.title>General Update (June 2019)</rev.title>
          <rev.date>20190612</rev.date>
          <rev.author>Practical Law IP&amp;IT</rev.author>
          <rev.body>
            <division id="a000008" level="1">
              <para>
                <paratext>We have revisited the parties' obligations in light of the NIS Regulations and made other general updates.</paratext>
              </para>
            </division>
          </rev.body>
        </rev.item>
      </rev.history>
    </standard.doc>
  </n-docbody>
</n-document>